<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to Mr. Tombes his scepticall examination of infants-baptisme: wherein baptisme is declared to ingraft us into Christ, before any preparation: and the covenant of the gospel to Abraham and the gentiles is proved to be the same, extended to the gentiles children, as well as to Abrahams: together with the reason, why baptize children, is not so plainly set down in the gospel, as circumcise children, in the law, and yet the gospel more plain then the law. / By William Hussey, minister of Chislehurst in Kent.</title>
            <author>Hussey, William, minister of Chiselhurst.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 249 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E343_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861553</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113690</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86928)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113690)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E343[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to Mr. Tombes his scepticall examination of infants-baptisme: wherein baptisme is declared to ingraft us into Christ, before any preparation: and the covenant of the gospel to Abraham and the gentiles is proved to be the same, extended to the gentiles children, as well as to Abrahams: together with the reason, why baptize children, is not so plainly set down in the gospel, as circumcise children, in the law, and yet the gospel more plain then the law. / By William Hussey, minister of Chislehurst in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Hussey, William, minister of Chiselhurst.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Saywell, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Starre in Little Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Tombes, John. Two treatises and an appendix to them concerning infant-baptisme (Wing T1825).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tombes, John, 1603?-1676. --  Two treatises and an appendix to them concerning infant-baptisme --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113690:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113690:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER To M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Tombes</hi> his Scepticall Examination OF INFANTS-BAPTISME:</p>
            <p>Wherein Baptiſme is declared to ingraft us into Chriſt, before any preparation: And the Covenant of the Goſpel to <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Gentiles is proved to be the ſame, extended to the Gentiles children, as well as to <hi>Abrahams:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the Reaſon, why <hi>Baptize children,</hi> is not ſo plainly ſet down in the Goſpel, as <hi>Circumciſe children,</hi> in the Law, and yet the Goſpel more plain then the Law.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Huſſey,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Chiſlehurſt</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HEBREWES 8.5, 6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who ſerve unto the example and ſhadow of heavenly things, as Moſes was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of God when he was about to make the Tabernacle: For ſee (ſaith he) that thou make all things according to the pattern ſhewed to thee in the mount.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But now hath he obtained a more excellent miniſtry, by how much alſo he is the Mediator of a better covenant, which was eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Saywell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Sign of the Starre in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113690:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113690:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Having read and ſeen the Labours of divers learned men that have undertaken the handling of this point; and ſeeing that this Doctrine of Anabaptiſts doth much ſpread, notwithſtanding all the induſtry that hath been uſed by men of ſingular parts and piety; I did wonder that ſuch a growing evill ſhould ſpread and prevail with men that did pretend ſo much to prety; and finding that they cryed up the authority of the Scripture, as of men that did plead for baptiſme of children, had nothing to countenance their doctrine, but humane authority, and ſet up mens inventions contrary to the Scriptures; when I ſaw that theſe An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ptiſts did ſo earneſtly plead for the authority of Scriptures, and declare themſelves ſo devoted to the rule of Gods Word, I had compaſsion on the affections of theſe men, willingly grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that that was indeed the rule we ought all to be guided by, I did as unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially ſift, how truly and faithfully they had dealt in the applying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to this ſacred rule: I perceived, that they did rather ſteal away the heats of men with the ſhew only of pretended reſpect unto the Scriptures, then that they did with d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſing aged ſpirits ſearch into the ſenſe and meaning of the Holy Ghoſt, as men deſirous to be lead by the authority of God. I heard men cry up Scripture, Scripture, nothing would prevail with them but Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I reſolved to concurre with them in this, that the Scripture and only Scripture ought to be our ride, in theſe ſupernaturall things of Gods worſhip: and if I could have found that they had argued rightly out of Scripture, I ſhould have moſt willingly joyned with them; but examining the ſincerity of their dealing herein, I ſaw them carried on with a ſpirit of pride, imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb facs="tcp:113690:3"/>that becauſe children had been baptized, and that thoſe men which had maintained childrens baptiſme, had maintained other errors; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the diſaffection that they bear unto former times, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to wrap up baptiſme of children among other things, and throw out it alſo, together with thoſe things that were indeed ſpurious and humane, out of the worſhip of God: they could not endure mans inventions in Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and therein their zeal was good, if their knowledge had been anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: but here I ſaw much pride, vailed under the cloak of piety, men car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on their opinions with oppoſition and clamour of multitudes, rather then with ſobriety and diligent enquiry into the ſtate of the queſtion: But whileſt I ſaw this humour, wandering in the lower region of the unlearned, I did not ſo much wonder, though I were much moved for their ſakes, becauſe their ſouls were as pretious to me as other mens, yet when I heard that it ſoared aloft among the learned, I thought it then high time to beſtir my ſelf, to ſearch into the ground and reaſon, why they alſo with others might be deceived in that point: wherein I took ſome pains to ſearch into the cauſe, and have for the publike good given ſome ſmall account thereof: and here I will turn ſceptique with <hi>Mr. Tombes,</hi> and examine whether our books have ſtated up the queſtion of Anabaptiſts high enough, and have ſufficiently clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thoſe Scriptures that are cited in the controverſies. For my part, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that the main reaſon that hath ſo much prevailed with the multitude, is, becauſe the ceremony of circumciſion being put down, and that being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the Iews; ſo as that every circumſtance of time, qualification of the perſon is expreſſe, he muſt be a male in the family of ſome believer: and no ſuch plainneſſe is uſed in the matter of the Sacrameut of baptiſme; for want whereof, ignorant perſons have proclaimed the baptiſme of Infants, will-worſhip, becauſe it is not ſaid in plain terms, ye ſhall baptize children; this may be an excuſe to men at firſt ſight and conſideration, but upon neerer enquiry; let it be conſidered, whether the different manner of the phraſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Goſpel and the Law, hath not put the difference. The ſervice of the Law was in ſhadows and types; therefore the externall rise was plain: they had not any ground at all from reaſon, no, not grounded upon the Word for the uſe of them: the authority of God did fall upon the rise it ſelf imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly, without any other explication, but that it was the confirmation and
<pb facs="tcp:113690:3"/>ſeal of the Covenant made with Abraham and his ſeed, whereby they were made partakers of the bleſsing in Chriſt, the ſeed of Abraham: Now, the Goſpel doth declare the promiſe to Abraham more plainly, and our ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into Chriſt by baptiſme more diſtinctly, according to the nature of the ſacrament; and in a more rationall way, entitling us to the promiſe, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Miniſters of the Goſpel to baptize all nations, males and females: without any limitation of yeers or ſex, whereby the proffer of grace is made to all nations: the ſeal of this proffer is baptiſme, whereby we are ingrafted into Chriſt, the promiſed ſeed; the promiſe of the Goſpel is plainly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be the promiſe made to Abraham, enlarged not in it ſelf, but by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of more ample diſpenſation: the promiſe to Abraham was not only to Abraham and his ſeed, but to all nations of the earth, though by provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence before Chriſt, kept within the nation of the lewes. The ignorance, or not attendance on this different manner of adminiſtration have cauſed men ſorigorouſly to require ſuch expreſſe direction in point of adminiſtration of the ſacrament of baptiſme; and by this means brought themſelves into ſuch difficulty, that if they ſhould ſtand to their principles, they could not ſinde out any way to adminiſter the ſacrament of baptiſme at all, unto any perſon whatſoever, for want of more plaine and particular direction: And thus, while they go about to inſiſt upon the Letter, and require the regulation of the Ordinance of Chriſt, to their own fancy, they make the Goſpel more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure then the Law, contrary to the conſtant declaration of the Goſpel which proclaimeth it more plain and full, more diſtinct and cleer, then the cloudy, weak, and childiſh manifeſtations of the Law: The Law ſaith, circumciſe a childe at eight dayes old in the family of Abraham, or any other believer; baptize all nations, ſaith the Goſpel: circumciſe males, ſaith the Law; males and females ſaith the Goſpel: circumciſe, this is my Covenant, ſaith the Law moſt obſcurely; baptize into Chriſt, by whom we have acceſſe by faith into grace, <hi>Rom. 5.2.</hi> moſt plainly ſaith the Goſpel: The Law giveth the ceremony therein moſt obſcurely, wrapping up the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Chriſt; the Goſpel promiſeth Chriſt moſt plainly, and moſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally drawing after it the ſacrament of baptiſme; children are in Chriſt by election of grace, before they are born; this is plainly ſet down in the Goſpel, but obſcurely intimated in the Law. Now, ſacramentally men
<pb facs="tcp:113690:4"/>are ingrafted into Chriſt by baptiſme, but perſonally to judge men faithfull, and thereby in Chriſt, before they were ingrafted into him, were a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in <hi>adjecto;</hi> therefore are men appointed to baptize and preach the Word as being able to adminiſter externalls only. The ſecond deluſion is, in that they interpret the hiſtories of the Acts of the Apoſties, wherein hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically is related, that perſons baptized did believe, not that confeſsion, or profeſsion of faith was made to the Apoſtles; and that the perſons baptized had their faith approved by the Apoſtles; and that that was the ground up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they baptized them, which is a plain addition to the Scripture: But my earneſt requeſt to <hi>Mr. Thombes,</hi> and all other Anabaptiſts, is, to look on the doctrine of the Goſpel, in a more ſpirituall way, then to ſubject it to ſuch a groſſe and carnall apprehenſion, and finde out ſome means in a more ſatisfactory way to ſtate the promiſe of the Goſpel according to the Word of God, then heretofore.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours in the Lord,
William Huſſey.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <div type="note">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>July 1. 1646.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have peruſed this Anſwer to <hi>Mr. Tombes</hi> his Book againſt Pedobaptiſme, or the baptizing of children; and finding it to be, in my judgement, ſolid and judicious, I do allow it to be printed and publiſhed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iohn Downame.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="response">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113690:4"/>
            <head>SATISFACTION TO M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Tombes</hi> his ſcepticall Exercitation Concerning Infants-Baptiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Method that I ſhall take in the handling this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie ſhall be, firſt, to ſtate the Doctrine of Baptiſme, as it was delivered by Chriſt, and underſtood by the Apoſtles, as may appear by their practice; then anſwer the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes and fallcies of Anabaptiſts, and in particular, of Mr. <hi>Tombs;</hi> and laſtly, ſome arguments to prove the lawfulneſſe of childrens baptiſme: As for the baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> it was of God; God ſent him to baptize, but as the Miniſtry, ſo the Baptiſme of <hi>John</hi> was perſonall, began and ended in him; he was not a Miniſter of the Goſpel, he was the greateſt of the Prophets, but the leaſt in the kingdome of Heaven is greater then he; he was <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſer,</hi> the forerunner of Chriſt, of whoſe baptiſme the Scripture is ſo ſilent, (if you conſider the form and nature of it) that we may quickly affirm more of it then we can be able to prove: As for Chriſt making Diſciples, and his Diſciples bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, the Scripture likewiſe ſpeaketh little, only that Chriſt made Diſciples, and his Diſciples baptized them: during the time of Chriſts abode upon earth, he did all things well, but ſome things he did which he was not pleaſed to reveal to us, what is written, is written for our learning; and ſo much is written, as by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving we may have eternall life.</p>
            <p>In things that are liable to no difficultie, a greater liberty of words is uſed: as, <hi>Go preach the Goſpel to every creature;</hi> here men cannot eaſily miſtake, becauſe none are capaple of the Goſpel but reaſonable creatures: So in the Commiſſion, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Make Diſciples of all nations, baptiſing them in the name of the Father Son and holy Ghoſt.</hi> Here Chriſt giveth a Commiſſion to make all nations his ſchollers, baptizing them, and teaching them what he commands: Here our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113690:5"/>is plain in the manner and form of Baptiſine that was new and unknown: concerning the doctrine they ſhould teach, he telleth them, he will give ſpeciall command what they ſhould teach; and for the ſubject, that being before limited to Jews, is now extended to the Gentiles alſo: but what ſhould be the qualification of perſons to be baptized is not ſaid, neither doth the Apoſtles any where declare, or give any thing in charge to <hi>Timothy</hi> or <hi>Titus,</hi> (to whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Miniſters of the Goſpel, to acquaint them with their duty) as matter of any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty wherein they might eaſily fail: and in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. he by occaſion ſpeaking of Baptiſme, ſpeaketh of that, as of a thing conſiſting in form of words, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward rite of waſhing, (ſo as it is miniſterially to be performed) wherein no ſuch difficulty was, or danger of miſtake; and therefore he had little care thereof, men of meaner qualifications might do that; yet were the Corinthians baptized be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he wrote to them, and a Church; In all the dogmaticall parts of Scripture, not one word concerning any direction to the Miniſter whom he ſhould baptize, whereby it is plain, that Chriſt did not charge his Diſciples with any danger of miſtake in baptizing, they ſhould teach what Chriſt had or ſhould command, for matter of doctrine; and Chriſt doth referre the commiſſion to future direction; but in all the Scripture no farther explanation concerning the perſons that were to be baptized: The Churches were baptized no man knowes by whom. To Churches and Saints, men received into the Church, is all the doctrine of the Apoſtles directed, whereby it appears, that they had care to teach all that Chriſt by his Spirit did command; but ſo little is ſpoken concerning the perſons to be baptized, or the manner of adminiſtration, more then is in the commiſſion; that it may plainly appeare, no controverſies were raiſed concerning that: it was a plain caſe wherein they walked, without diſpute; or, it ſeemeth, ſuſpition of controverſie, though light enough be given to the truth; ſo that Antipedobap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, without offending againſt plain Scripture, can have no ground to oppoſe the baptiſme of Infants by thoſe inartificiall and groundleſſe arguments which they urge againſt it; and certainly, it was long ere much was ſaid, and the ſtrength of that which is ſaid, will appear. What is gathered out of the commiſſion, <hi>Go, make Diſciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, teaching them, &amp;c.</hi> we ſhall conſider:</p>
            <p>Nations is the ſubject, that is ſo cleer, that Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> confeſſeth it, though with this limitation, nations that are made Diſciples; which limitation can receive no colour without apparent alteration of the words. Firſt, make them Diſciples, and then baptize them, ſaith Mr. <hi>Tombes:</hi> three words are added, <hi>(firſt, and, then,)</hi> the words plainly import, make Diſciples by baptizing them and teaching. I have added nothing but the word <hi>by;</hi> and that is implied in the participiall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, as may appeare to all Engliſh men that underſtand their own tongue: as in the like phraſe; make, or build houſes, laying the foundations on the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113690:5"/>tock, and raiſing the walls and roof of laſting and durable matter, do not theſe participles expreſſe the manner of doing? or, may a man gather from hence that the houſe muſt be built before the foundation muſt be laid? Again, the word nations, is a Noune of multitude, and the very commiſſion ſeemeth to point at the nation of the Jewes for the pattern, that they ſhould call other nations into covenant with God even after the ſame manner as the Jews have been, by vertue of the ſame promiſe; and thus it is apparent, the Apoſtles all underſtood it. Paul, both to the Romans, <hi>Rom</hi> 4 11. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. doth argue, that the promiſe might ſtand the ſame to us, as was to <hi>Abraham,</hi> though circumciſion be taken away, for as much as the promiſe was before circumciſion, even to <hi>Abraham;</hi> and there might remain the circumciſion of the heart, though the outward circumciſion were taken away, and Baptiſme put in the place of it; and from this promiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. S. <hi>Peter</hi> argueth to Baptiſme, <hi>the promiſe belongeth to you,</hi> therefore be baptized. If then Baptiſme may be tendered to nations, nations may receive baptiſme, that is, it may be, nay, it muſt be received by a nationall covenant, the nation of the Jews were only in covenant with God before Chriſt; but all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after Chriſt hath broken down the partition wall. Now principally a nation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all covenant doth conſiſt in this, that the moſt principall of the nation do cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for the reſt, the more conſiderable part do receive for the reſt, and require performance of others their inferiours. God laid circumciſion upon the Jews un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a penalty, which is a nationall way of receiving; God commandeth all to be circumciſed by a Law, under a penalty, that perſon that was not circumciſed, muſt be cut off, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14. that the whole nation might be circumciſed. If any ſhall object, that the Jews were all to be circumcized under a penalty, but the penalty was appointed of God. I anſwer, that was an eſpeciall priviledge of the Jewes, that they had their civill Lawes from God, but what lieth upon a nation as a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it may require of all, and cut off them that refuſe; and this is implied in the commiſſion, when nations ſhall covenant to be Diſciples, which may be done by a part for the whole, then are ſuch as are in commiſſion from Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to baptize and teach the whole nation, ſuch as are in authority may co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in a nationall way for the inferiour ſort, and juſtly require all externall performances from them, ſuch as Baptiſme, and ſubmiſſion to be taught are; as for faith, and internall performance, no creature can judge of that, or require it of another in a judiciall way.</p>
            <p>If any object that the Apoſtles did not execute their commiſſion, but upon ſuch parties as did believe, and would be baptized.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, a commiſſion cannot be executed in full extent, untill opportunity be gotten; he that hath a commiſſion to hang up all the thieves in the kingdom, muſt execute it as he may; he muſt hang them as he can catch them: as ſoon as they could procure a nationall willingneſſe, they were ready to baptize them, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113690:6"/>by the many thouſands baptized by them the ſame day of their converſion may appear, taking them in by families, which act by a nationall way, the maſter of the family covenanting for his ſervants and children: So <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.15. <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord;</hi> he may not believe for his ſervant, but he may cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for externall worſhip for his ſon, under a penalty, and for his ſervant accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his condition, under penalty, or diſmiſſion of ſervice, that the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily or nation might come in: And that the Gentiles ſhould in ſuch a manner flow into the Church, the Prophets do fully teſtifie, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.2. <hi>All nations ſhall flow, &amp;c.</hi> See further what light the word Diſciple doth give to this ſenſe of the commiſſion. Diſciple is a relative, and is referred to maſter, to him that giveth precepts, which have ſanctions of reward, and puniſhment annexed; and this is the covenant that is between the maſter and the ſcholler, that he will teach and puniſh the negligence of the ſcholler, the ſcholler muſt be under the covenant of ſubmiſsion, or otherwiſe he can be no ſcholler.</p>
            <p>Now, note that two ways this covenant of a ſcholler may be put upon any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Firſt, it may be put on with the conſent of the ſcholler: or, ſecondly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, in caſe of a ſlave, his Lord may impoſe what covenants he pleaſeth, without his conſent, if he will live and enjoy his being, the father may, and that juſtly, by his intereſt that he hath over his ſon by nature, put him to ſchool, and make a ſcholler of him, even before he be willing to conſent; he may juſtly carry him, and correct him, if he refuſe to be put under the power of a Schoolmaſter, giving his Schoolmaſter power to correct him. Now, to ſend him to ſchool to Chriſt, and teach him the precepts of Chriſt, and this impoſed on the parent of Chriſt, by his Apoſtles, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. <hi>And ye fathers, provoke not your children to wrath: but bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.</hi> And what a parent can do over his child in matter of duty, that may the parents of the countrey, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, require of the nations. God requireth it of them, they may put all the nation to ſchool to Chriſt: Now, what if ſome of them be too young to learn, yet if they be under the diſcipline of the Maſter, they are ſchollers? as may appear in many little children that are ſet to ſchool, to keep them ſafe, and from wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, before they be of capacity to learn, many have a hornbook given, more for a play-game, then a book, yet are they ſchollers, becauſe under the diſcipline and correction of the Maſter; is it not therefore great reaſon, that a Chriſtian ſhould dedicate his childe to Chriſt, to be partaker of the bleſſing and diſcipline of Chriſt? ſurely godlineſſe hath the promiſe of this life, and that which is to come. What, is the Infant capable of no good from Chriſt? neither in ſoul nor body? hath Chriſt nothing to do with him? Chriſt did bleſſe ſucking Infants, and as he bleſſeth, cannot he likewiſe puniſh at pleaſure? Why then, if he hath power over all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and <hi>de jure,</hi> they are all under his diſcipline, may not Chriſtian parents put their children under the tuition of Chriſt, ſeeing, though they cannot learn, yet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113690:6"/>he can bleſſe, and hath right, and will puniſh, which we by baptizing our Infants do but acknowledge? nay, certainly he is an Infidell that doth not think that Chriſt can teach the Infant by his Spirit, though we cannot by means that we can uſe, or that he doth not qualifie the ſouls of the elect Infants, with gifts of grace, not given to reprobates, if they die in infancy, which though he can, and will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out baptiſme; yet this is ſufficient incouragement for a Chriſtian parent to put his ſon to ſchool to Chriſt, if Chriſt can teach him, this were a vain thing to think for any ignorant parent to refuſe to put his ſon to ſchool, becauſe he underſtandeth not Latine or Greek himſelf; it is ſufficient that the Maſter underſtandeth and knoweth how to teach. And certainly, words could not have been invented that could have required the Miniſters to baptize all the world, Infants and all, willing or unwilling; ſo that any would ſee they might be taught, and ſubmit to the precepts and diſcipline of Chriſt, then to expreſſe it by the word Nation, and Diſciple; and this was plain to them that underſtood what it was for a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be in covenant with God, whereof there was but one pattern at that time, and ſo it doth appear the Apoſtles did underſtand it as a plain thing: in that, though often they took occaſion to ſpeak of baptiſme, yet never did explain this point concerning childrens baptiſme, as thinking it plain enough in the pattern: what might juſtly raiſe a ſcruple concerning the baptizing of women, ſeeing they were not circumciſed, that is, declared in plain terms, both men and women were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. Baptiſme is in room of circumciſion, as in anſwering Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I hope to make appear. For the further underſtanding of this word Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, I ſhall endeavour to ſet forth the full latitude of the word: the formall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Diſciple, is <hi>in relatione ad Preceptorem,</hi> the foundation of which relation is a covenant between the Maſter and the ſcholler, whereby the Maſter is ingaged to deliver precepts, and the ſcholler is bound to hear and undergo the penalties of his errors and contempts.</p>
            <p>Now, this covenant is either impoſed, as in caſe of a ſlave, when a Lord doth lay any covenants upon his ſlave; here the benefits of the covenant be mercies, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, if leſſe then the greateſt, or under any conditions avoidable, are favors; ſo <hi>Naaſh,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2. tendered a covenant to put out every one of the Iſraelites right eyes, which if he had been able to have deſtroyed, as he conceived he was, had been a favour; in this caſe one party maketh the covenant without mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other but as patient; therefore, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.18. God is ſaid to make a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and 17.9. God calleth the covenant, his covenant, God made the promiſe and conditions, not <hi>Abraham;</hi> but in <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.27. there, when <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Abimeleck</hi> did covenant, the Text ſaith, <hi>they both made a covenant, Abraham</hi> his conditions, and <hi>Abimeleck</hi> his.</p>
            <p>If the word Diſciple be taken in this ſenſe, then it is no more, but tell all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I am that Prophet that was promiſed by <hi>Moſes, 'Deut.</hi> 18.18, 19. and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113690:7"/>thus Peter Acts 3. and Stephen Acts 7. did make diſciples, repeating thoſe words of Moſes, A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe to you like unto me, him ſhall you heare; and he that will not hear the voice of that Prophet ſhall dye the death; and then theſe words make diſciples, doe ſignifie no more then tell all Nations that I am ſent of my Father to teach them, and they that will not heare ſhall dye the death. Chriſt without any more adoe doth give Precepts, and threaten death to all the world that refuſe, and ſo make diſciples is no more but tell them they are diſciples, and under the Precepts of Chriſt; but if any acceptance be required of the diſciple, the naturall father or father of the Country, may covenant for their children as before.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a Diſciple may be underſtood in reference to the end, and that either actively for a man that is active or diligent to get learning, he is ſaid to be a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; or paſſively a man is ſaid to be a Diſciple or Scholer that is learned; and this <hi>inchoativè vel ad certum aut deſignatum gradum vel perfectivè:</hi> if this man that is to be baptiſed muſt be taught <hi>inchoativè,</hi> it will ſerve turne to have learned one leſſon in reference to that one leſſon he is learned, though he hath learned but an A the firſt letter of his Alphabet. In the ſecond ſenſe men are aſſigned a certaine meaſure of learning as ſufficient for one calling, another meaſure for another calling; what degree of knowledge men muſt attaine to before they be baptiſed, no man yet hath declared: and in ſo great a ſilence of Scripture were an arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie inexcuſable; for want whereof, all that is ſaid concerning a Diſciple to bee made before baptized, is without any regularity and certainty; if it bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>perfectivè,</hi> then a man muſt never be baptiſed, if not before he be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly learned; whereby it appeareth that we cannot be ſaid to be made learned in diſpoſition to Baptiſme, but as before made Schollers in relation to Chriſt our Maſter by Baptiſme in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, being taught the precepts of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> 127. p. falleth upon this as urged by ſome obſcure perſon, but ſaith it is ſo fooliſh, that no man will ſay ſo but he that is out of his wit, but hee in the meane time anſwereth it no better then by ſaying if this were true, the Apoſtles needed to have done nothing elſe then to baptiſe them: I thinke if ever a man were out of his wit, it was here; Chriſt ſaith, make Diſciples by baptiſing them and teaching them, if he meane ſo, need they only baptiſe them, and not teach them? or if they were made Schollers, muſt they not be taught when they are ſchollers? in what ſenſe doth this man take ſcholler? ſurely in ſuch a ſenſe that he need be taught no more: if he muſt be a Diſciple in ſuch a ſenſe before he bee baptiſed, it were a bold adventure for any Miniſter to baptiſe any man, or if hee did, the party baptiſed muſt be taught no more: if baptiſing would make Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, the Apoſtles need doe no more, this were a good excuſe for not preaching Prieſts. It is plaine Chriſt commands to baptiſe and teach; what if a man do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113690:7"/>part of his duty, is he diſcharged of the other part? the command is in conjunctive tearms both muſt be performed. But Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> fell on that obiter, and I have vindicated it for the true ſenſe of the words which he ſo ſcornfully rejected: but I further prove it.</p>
            <p>What doe not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being active participles, expreſſe the action of their verbes: and is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the end, is not every action to an end? yes certainly, and to make Diſciples is the end, inrolling them by Baptiſme, and after teaching them the meanes. I deſire that men may not be outfaced from principles and rules. But I haſten to try the ſtrength of Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>He confuteth this practice, that Infants borne of Beleevers are univerſally to be baptiſed; for my part I ſtate not the queſtion ſo, but Infants borne in a Nation that are the Diſciples of Chriſt, or have received the Goſpell, are to bee baptiſed: of Beleevers much more, if preſented by them; and they undertake to inſtruct them by themſelves or others in the precepts of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his ſophiſmes, That which hath no teſtimonies of Scripture that is doubtfull.</p>
            <p>Infants baptiſme hath no teſtimony of Scripture, <hi>ergo</hi> doubtfull.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minor</hi> Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> laboureth to prove by an induction, but it wanteth forme; he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>&amp; ſic de ceteris,</hi> none of all theſe places might prove this, and yet it might have teſtimony from ſome other place: but I will follow him in his exceptions, and ſee how juſt they are againſt the teſtimonies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
            <p>The firſt teſtimony which he pretendeth accurately to examin, Gen. 17.7. &amp;c. I paſſe by his jingle, he raiſeth 14 arguments raiſed out of ſeverall places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as urged in defence of Paedobaptiſme, which he anſwereth, whoſe anſwers I ſhall endeavour to examine, and ſee how the arguments are as he urgeth them, or as they may be urged from this place of Geneſis: to whom the Goſpell Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant agrees, to them the ſigne of the Goſpell Covenant agrees; but to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of Beleevers the Goſpell Covenant agrees, therefore the ſigne of the Goſpell Covenant, and conſequently Baptiſme. That Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for an anſwer, he ſheweth a great deale of his accurate skill, he examines foure <hi>ſuppoſita,</hi> things granted on the part of Pedobaptiſts, and converteth them into queſtions, ſtateth them apart, and ſo endeavoureth to take away the ſtrength of the argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Covenant made with Abraham, and the Goſpell Covenant be the ſame? Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> denieth with this difference, that the Covenant with Abraham was mixed, but (with reſpect to Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> his opinion of learning he hath gotten) he beginneth at the worng end to prove it: for a Goſpell Covenant between God and man, taketh in all the Covenants that now are, or ever were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113690:8"/>ſince the fall between God and man: God was never in covenant with any man or Nation, but in Chriſt: Chriſt is the adequate ſubject of the Goſpell: this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell was preached from heaven by the Angels, Luke 2.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I preach the Goſpell, which was in theſe words, Unto you is borne this day in the City of David a Saviour which is Chriſt the Lord: Certainly whatſoever the Saints enjoy upon earth, or ſhall enjoy in heaven, they enjoy it in and for Chriſt. Whereas Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> diſtinguiſheth the promiſes made to <hi>Abraham</hi> into Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, Domeſticall and Civill promiſes; what had <hi>Abraham</hi> ſome things in Chriſt and ſome things out of Chriſt? godlineſſe hath the promiſes of this life and that which is to come. Now to deny the promiſes of this life to belong to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> under Evangelicall promiſe, or to diſtinguiſh individualls by ſpecificall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, is ſtrange Divinity and ſtranger Logick, is reaſon of different nature in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> or is <hi>Pauls</hi> reaſon of another nature then <hi>Peters,</hi> becauſe he uſeth ſome particular arguments that <hi>Peter</hi> doth not? <hi>Abraham</hi> had the bleſſings of his houſe, and others have the bleſſings of their families: and Gal. 3.9. <hi>Paul</hi> telleth us, that they which beleeve are bleſſed with faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> they are not bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed only as the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but as <hi>Abraham</hi> they are fountaines of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to their ſeed through faith in Chriſt; and that doth that inference cleerly prove that <hi>Abraham</hi> was intituled to the bleſſing by his faith, <hi>tanquam medio,</hi> as by the meanes, and therefore is <hi>faithfull</hi> repeated in the argument with <hi>Abraham,</hi> that thoſe that beleeve are bleſſed not <hi>with Abraham,</hi> but <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Abraham;</hi> and further ſaith, not that the faithfull are bleſſed with the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but with <hi>Abraham,</hi> they that beleeve have as full a right to the promiſe as <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelfe: the ſame Covenant, the ſame bleſſing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines to us with <hi>Abraham:</hi> as for thoſe particular differences they are but nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericall, and make no difference in the promiſe, no more then the difference of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> doe in mankinde: <hi>Abraham</hi> had his family bleſſings, wee have ours: <hi>Logica non tractat aut definit particularia:</hi> if any ſhall ſay that his being father of Chriſt after the fleſh putteth a mixture of the Covenant, and maketh it of another nature: I deny that it doth any more vary the nature of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, then a badge of honor doth the nature of man, and this ſhall appear in that ſo much of the covenant as was ſealed to <hi>Abraham</hi> by circumciſion commeth down to us; and if <hi>Abraham</hi> had any bleſſing that came not to us, that was not ſealed to him by circumciſion, foraſmuch as all the benefit that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his naturall or faithfull ſeed had of circumciſion, that the Beleever hath without circumciſion. For though it be true that circumciſion was given to all indefinitly, yet the benefit of circumciſion came only to the faithfull both before and after Chriſt came: and this is ſo plainly ſet downe by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that nothing can be more plaine, that circumciſion was of force to <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, Rom. 4.9.10. Faith was recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Abraham</hi> when he was uncircumciſed, and that he received circumciſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113690:8"/>as a ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of faith: and in verſe 12. he ſaith, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was father of circumciſion to them that were uncircumciſed; where he implied that thoſe that were uncircumciſed were circumciſed in a ſenſe: and this is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affirmed of them who are in Chriſt Jeſus by faith, Col. 2.10. that they are circumciſed with circumciſion made without hands; and this circumciſion with hands is ſpecified, Eph. 2.11. Yee were uncircumciſed with circumciſion in the fleſh made with hands, implied that they were circumciſed in the heart: what other ſenſe can be rendred of this circumciſion of heart, but that that cleanneſſe of heart which was ſignified to our fathers by circumciſion, remaineth to us though the ſeale be altered? and this is that uſuall ſetting downe of Evangelicall duties and benefits by ceremoniall expreſſions: We under the Goſpel are circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in heart without hands. Now how could that be, unleſſe the internall part of circumciſion did remaine to us? And this Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> p. 33. doth confeſſe that the ſubſtance of the Covenant doth remaine; but ſtill helpeth himſelfe with his mixt covenant, which I have formerly denyed, and ſhall preſently evince: the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent manner of adminiſtration doth not alter the Covenant: God did ſet forth, his promiſes of Heaven by Canaan: was punctuall in the ceremonies; but the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies did lead thoſe that beleeved to better then the bare ceremony, without which, circumciſion and all their ſervice was utterly without uſe or benefit; God did in ſpeciall manner bleſſe thoſe outward duties to his elect, becauſe they were his owne Ordinances, cauſing them to ſee more in thoſe types, then they in their owne nature doe ſeem to manifeſt. And thus Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>that the promiſes that were Evangelicall in the more inner ſenſe of the Holy Ghoſt, doe point at the priviledges</hi> of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe in the outward face of the words: ſo that it may bee doubted whether this Covenant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> may be called ſimply Evangelicall: and this doubt is made the more juſt, becauſe Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> and ſome of his company doe not call the Covenant on Mount Sinai ſimply Evangelicall: what have you diſtinguiſhed between mixed and pure Goſpell Covenants, on purpoſe to make the Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> mixt, and is it now doubtfull? and therefore doubtfull, becauſe Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> and others doe call the Covenant on Mount Sinai mixt: What if they miſcall it? What ground then of the doubt? away with ſuch groundleſſe doubts: for wee call that Covenant, and all the Covenants that God made with man ſince the fall, purely Evangelicall, without any mixture at all; and let Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> or any of his company prove the contrary: in the mean time, let me intreat Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> and all other that meddle with controverſies, to make no more diſtinctions nor limitations, then lawes of diviſion and limitation will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: For, though at firſt they may win applauſe for their novelty, yet after ages will ſee their vainity, if any of them be taken up in a tract, yet times will come that will find them out: But all this while, Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> doth not tell us what part of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113690:9"/>the covenant was ſealed by circumciſion, or whether circumciſion did reſpect principally the domeſticall part or civill, or Evangelicall part, or equally all; nor ſhew any reaſon why the Goſpel covenant will not admit any ſuch mixture as he ſuppoſeth; but I do not love to inſult over a weak argument, or ſtrike an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary when he is dead.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> cometh to diſtinguiſh the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> I will not trouble my ſelf to repeat or take notice of what Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith well, but of ſuch paſſages as he layeth down, upon which he purpoſeth to raiſe ſomething againſt childrens baptiſme: He indeavoureth to prove, that the ſeed of believing Gentiles, were not the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the reaſon is, becauſe Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> doth not finde them ſo called: a man may not heare himſelf or his neighbour called a man in many yeers; nay, ſuppoſe they were never ſo called, were they therefore no men? But it is moſt plain, that the ſeed of believing Gentiles were the ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> for that is the knot of the queſtion, and God himſelf doth decide it. All that were by Gods appointment to be circumciſed, were in ſome ſenſe or other the ſeed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> or, otherwiſe there had been no need at all of calling the faithfull the ſeed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> But becauſe they are partakers of the benefit of the promiſe, made to the ſeed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> And this is made plain in the doctrine of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> he handleth this promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, not as the words do import, but as they carry the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> without reference to circumciſion or uncircumciſion, ſhewing that circumciſion was annexed to the promiſe but for a time, was but accidentall to the promiſe, and might be taken away, the promiſe remaining: This the Apoſtle doth moſt artificially prove, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to rules of art: For, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.10. his purpoſe was to prove, that now they were not to retain circumciſion, Chriſt being come, and baptiſme being ſet in the place and room of it; and that notwithſtanding the promiſe made to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did remain; now that he might prove that, he ſheweth that circumciſion was not a proper paſſion to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed flowing from the promiſe, as the cauſe, and therefore may be ſeparated from the promiſe; circumciſion belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather to the ceremoniall adminiſtration then the eſſence of the promiſe; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the externall part of the worſhip then the efficacy and vertue of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; and this he proveth: Firſt, becauſe the promiſe was of force to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> through faith, before circumciſion, and therefore, <hi>prior tempore,</hi> before, in time to circumciſion, which it could not have been, if it had flowed from the promiſe as the cauſe: For, though the immediate cauſe be before its effect in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet not in time; man is not <hi>rationalis</hi> before <hi>riſibilis,</hi> and therefore as the promiſe was before circumciſion, ſo it may continue after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But the promiſe was made to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, which we are not. To this I anſwer, the promiſe was made to one ſeed, not many, which is Chriſt, as <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> explain it, not of the perſon of Chriſt, but believers in Chriſt;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113690:9"/>implying, that though there were a diſtinction between Jews and Gentiles, yet by faith in Chriſt they were all one, and the argument in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. doth cleerly ſhew this; neither Jew nor Greek, bond nor free, all one in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had but one bleſſed ſeed to whom the promiſe was made, which is Chriſt, ſaith the Text, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. But I have proved the promiſe was not made to Chriſt in perſon as the ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> is reckoned in Chriſt, and the word Chriſt is taken for the myſticall body of Chriſt his Church of the elect, which in reference to the promiſe are but one ſeed, whether Jew or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, ſo are the bleſſings and ſufferings of the Church reckoned the ſufferings of Chriſt. So that this ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> in reference to the promiſe, was never underſtood of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, according to the fleſh, but by faith: And here note, that this is not an univocall diviſion; as if the members did not <hi>coincidere,</hi> or, that ſome were the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the fleſh, and none of them his ſeed by faith, and others by faith his ſeed that were none of them his ſeed in the fleſh; nay, but this diſtinction is in reference to the promiſe as diſtinct from cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion; all thoſe were not of the ſeed according to promiſe, that were the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the fleſh; no, not of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but the believers, theſe are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to promiſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>If ye be Chriſts, them are ye Abrahams ſeed, and heirs according to promiſe,</hi> elſe not: And this is not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh Jews from Gentiles, but believing Jews from infidels, and to draw the whole vertue of the promiſe on Believers: ſo the promiſe is belonging to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> through faith, and the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as the word ſeed is underſtood in the promiſe, and in the eſtimation of God is the Believer only; ſo that the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, and the ſeed unto whom the promiſe of God to <hi>Abraham</hi> did belong are the ſame, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Believer, whether Jew or Gentile, whether before or after Chriſt, are all one, in the eſtimation of God: So that the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> that were bleſſed were believers only, not all the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> nay, nor all the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that is, in Chriſt, that was the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> all that were in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that is in Chriſt, of whom <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac</hi> was a type, that is, believers only, not all the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> for the promiſe did not belong to <hi>Eſau</hi> that was the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> for that, though he were the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yet he was not in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that is, he was not inſerted into <hi>Iſaac</hi> as a type of Chriſt by faith; and therefore the ſeed muſt be ſo underſtood that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe might belong to all the ſeed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. not to that which is of the Law only, but that which is of the faith of <hi>Abraham;</hi> not to them only which were circumciſed according to Law, but to believers, though not circumciſed, (that is, after circumciſion was taken away by appointment of God: For, though circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was not ſo naturall and eſſentiall to the promiſe, that it was enough at any time to entitle any to the promiſe without faith; yet, <hi>virtute inſtitutionis divina,</hi> was not to be omitted untill God took it away;) for the promiſe was not to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113690:10"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> through the Law, therefore not through circumciſion, which was a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall right, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the righteouſneſſe of faith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. to let us know that it was not any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rite or ſacrament that can intitle to the promiſe, it doth but externally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the vertue of Chriſts blood, and by it the circumciſion of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſight of God is the only circumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29. He is a Jew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and circumciſion is of the heart, in the Spirit, not in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not of men, but of God. All this while the Scripture treateth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> in the eſtimation of God: God accounteth none the ſeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> but in Chriſt, none heirs of the promiſe but in Chriſt, none circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them that are in Chriſt, and therefore ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28. that is not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the fleſh, and this, <hi>ex regula de nullo.</hi> Again, <hi>ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> all that are in Chriſt Jeſus, that is believers, are the ſeed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> heirs of the promiſe, circumciſed in heart; but theſe have their eſtimation and praiſe not of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, but of God, and theſe are equally denied and affirmed to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d, and Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es according as they are believers, or not believers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> without any reſpect a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed according to the fleſh; ſo that <hi>Abrahams</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had no right at all to any part of the promiſe in the eſtimation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and therefore, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. they that are the children of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>Abrahams</hi> freſh, are not the children of God, the children of the promiſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accounted for the ſeed; and therefore, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. the Lord did make the promiſe not to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed only, but from <hi>Abraham</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived the bleſſing upon all the families of the earth; all the families of the earth were bleſſed in <hi>Abraham:</hi> Or, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.18. all nations are bleſſed in the ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and therefore do Interpreters interpret that former <hi>by [thee]</hi> that is, in thy ſeed, and all that are in Chriſt, are plainly the heirs of the promiſe, and none but they. <hi>Abraham</hi> in honour and title, was called the fountain of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but in de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and truth, not <hi>Abraham,</hi> but Chriſt; for <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf was bleſſed in Chriſt, not in himſelf, as Chriſt was; Chriſt was only bleſſed and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in and for his own holineſſe by the works of the Law inherent in himſelf; So that Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his diviſion of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Chriſts ſpirituall ſeed believers, naturall ſeed is moſt inartificiall, many of his naturall ſeed were ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall alſo: <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed muſt be divded into equivocall and univocall; equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocall ſeed Chriſt, for that he was not like <hi>Abraham</hi> he was of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but <hi>ex parte,</hi> according to the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3. He was <hi>Abrahams</hi> Lord, as well as his ſon; his Saviour, as well as his ſeed: he was the promiſed ſeed, not the ſeed unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>om the promiſe did belong, as the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but that ſeed that was the fountain of bleſſing to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all other his ſeed: and therefore Chriſt was the bleſſing it ſelf, the promiſe that was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, was through the righteouſneſſe of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. but the bleſſing came not on Chriſt through the righteouſneſſe of faith, ſeeing the righteouſneſſe of faith is derivative
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113690:10"/>from Chriſt to Abraham: Chriſts righteouſneſſe was primitive in himſelfe, and that very righteouſneſſe that became Abrahams by faith: and therefore is Chriſt the inheritance of Abraham and all the faithfull ſeed, <hi>Eſay</hi> 42.6. he is called the Covenant of the people, and a light to the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Abrahams</hi> univocall ſeed were like unto himſelfe in relation to the promiſe; the word ſeed in the promiſe, I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed, is only the faithfull, nothing belonging to the ſeed of <hi>Abrahams</hi> fleſh, but ſo as they are faithfull, nor excluding any Nation, or family, or perſon in the earth, ſo as faithfull: as for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed according to the fleſh, if not faithfull, <hi>non eſt noſtri inſtituti;</hi> it is not belonging to the doctrine of the Promiſe to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them at all, Rom. 2.29. they were not to be reckoned among the circumciſed by God. Now for the particular application of this promiſe to this Nation or that, in one age to the family of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the fleſh, in another age to the Gentiles; in one age under the ſeale of circumciſion, in another of Baptiſme; ſometimes to give a Nation the means of Grace, Word, and Sacraments, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to lead them away into captivity; theſe things were ordered according to the particular determination and purpoſe of God, though God did in a more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner bleſſe the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> then other Nations, with the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Word and Sacraments, and other bleſſings, yet they had them together with the land of Canaan, and the place of Gods worſhip; only on conditions of faith and obedience, as in Deut. 28. and 29. chapters, and by the many threatnings of removall of them by the Prophets, and their actuall captivities may appear; ſo that theſe graces of faith and obedience come on this or that Nation or perſon according to the purpoſe of Gods will, as likewiſe effectuall operation of the Word, and the particular effect of the Sacrament under the means of Word and Sacraments, wholly depend on the mercy of God according to the election of grace. Men are to adminiſter the outward rite and ſacrament according to the ordination of God: God by his Spirit beſtoweth his grace, and with-holdeth it from whom he pleaſeth: The Jewes were tyed to the eight day to ſigne the fleſh with circumciſion; but it was God that circumciſed the heart, without which, the circumciſion of the fleſh was no circumciſion in the eſtimation of God; as Rom. 2.28. which man cannot nor ought to take notice of, it is the way of God, no man knoweth it; it is God that giveth the new name that no man knoweth but he that hath it. Thoſe that have this inward grace of circumciſion, are called and accounted by God for the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but whom muſt <hi>Abraham</hi> for his part in reference to this promiſe, account for his ſeed? the covenant on Gods part is to be the God of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, which God knows how to extend to Jew and Gentile, and limit to beleevers even among <hi>Abrahams</hi> family. But <hi>Abraham</hi> had laid on him that hee ſhould circumciſe, but he cannot walke by Gods rules in the eſtimation of his ſeed, Gen. 17.10. This is my covenant that ye
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113690:11"/>keep between me and you, and thy ſeed after thee, every manchilde among you ſhall be circumciſed: the former part, I will be a God to thee and thy ſeed, might have ſerved <hi>Abrahams</hi> turn, if he had known how to eſtimate his ſeed, as God did by the beleever, but that was paſt <hi>Abrahams</hi> skill, therefore muſt <hi>Abraham</hi> have another rule ſet him to walke by; and leſt <hi>Abraham</hi> inſiſting on the word ſeed ſhould debarre many from circumciſion of the fleſh, whom God did intend to circumciſe in heart; he is charged with his duty in plaine tearmes, 12.13. verſe, Every manchilde in your generations, he that is borne in the houſe or bought with money of any ſtranger that is not of thy ſeed. And Exod. 12.48. When a ſtranger ſhall ſojourne with thee, and will keep the Paſſeover to the Lord, let all his males be circumciſed, and then let him come neare and keep the Paſſeover, for no uncircumciſed perſon ſhall eat thereof, one law ſhall be to him that is home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, and unto the ſtranger that ſojourneth among you: ſo you ſee how <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was to count his ſeed, not only thoſe that were indeed his ſeed, but thoſe that were of his family, not ſo only, but the ſeed of beleeving Gentiles, were to be the accounted ſeed of the promiſe: one law muſt be to the ſtranger that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journeth, and to the naturall ſeed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> the beleeving Gentile that would keep the Paſſeover, muſt be ſubject to the ſame law with <hi>Abraham:</hi> he muſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe not only himſelfe, but all his males, and the reaſon is, becauſe no uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed perſon may eat thereof: the maſter of the family might not be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a circumciſed perſon, unleſſe all his males were circumciſed, becauſe that was the law of circumciſion, that he that was circumciſed himſelf, muſt circumciſe all his males, becauſe the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> was a family bleſſing, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. In thee ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſſed; and that which is there ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by families, is in 18.18. rendred by Nations, All the nations of the earth ſhall be bleſſed in him: ſeeing all families, and all nations be of the ſame extent. Thus yee ſee plainly demonſtrated that <hi>Abraham</hi> and beleeving Gentiles were to underſtand the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> in reference to the promiſe of the ſeed of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Gentiles, which Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> doth not finde.</p>
            <p>You ſee the promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all families, and all nations perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in ſome families, even under the law of circumciſion, the families of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, the males that were borne in the houſe or bought with money, were recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as <hi>Abrahams</hi> males; but this ſtranger that would keep the Paſſeover, muſt circumciſe his males not under the name of <hi>Abrahams</hi> males, not as borne in <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe, nor bought with money, but under the name of the ſeed of ſuch a ſtranger that would keep the Paſſeover; they could have no right to circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but as the ſeed of beleeving Gentiles. Againe, you ſee this promiſe is made to all Nations in <hi>Abraham,</hi> which muſt have a time of performance in that ſenſe alſo: but this was never performed in any nationall capacity before Chriſts time; yet God never maketh a promiſe, but he taketh a time in ſome ſenſe or other to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113690:11"/>but we ſee notwithſtanding this promiſe, God had not any Nation bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but the Jewes, and therefore doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> plainly interpret that part of the promiſe concerning Nations in reference to Nations after Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. the Scripture foreſeeing that God would juſtifie the heathen through faith preached before the Goſpell to <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaying, In thee ſhall all the nations of the earth be bleſſed: ſee God made his promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all families, all nations; he began with Abraham and his, and ſome other few Gentiles families, and after referreth the performance of the promiſe as it concerneth all Nations to the times wherein he foreſaw that the Nations would beleeve.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Queſtion, whether there be the ſame reaſon of Circumciſion and Baptiſme in ſigning the Goſpell-covenant? To this Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> ſaith, that the ſubſtance of the Goſpell-covenant was the ſame in all ages, yet this covenant hath had divers formes and ſanctions, where after abundance of words to prove diverſity of formes and ſanctions, he endeavoureth to prove a diverſity of the forme and ſanction of the covenant with Abraham, and forme, ſanction, and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the new Teſtament covenant: and from thence he inferreth his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in theſe words. Whence I gather that there is not the ſame reaſon of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion and baptiſme in ſigning the Evangelicall covenant; nor may there be an argument drawne from the adminſtration of one, to the like manner of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the other. I have heard very much of Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> his learning, and now I ſee wherein it lyeth, in drawing that out of premiſes that no man elſe can draw, and making ſyllogiſms with two concluſions, <hi>toto coelo,</hi> divers, and yet make them ariſe from the ſame premiſes: this is the learning ſo much magnified.</p>
            <p>That which he principally gathereth is, that there is not the ſame reaſon of circumciſion and baptiſme in ſealing the Goſpell-covenant. For my part I know but two wayes of ſignations or ſealings, one naturall, the other <hi>ex inſtituto divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no vel humane.</hi> Now I conceive both circumciſion and baptiſme doe ſigne or ſeale ſacramentally, and by divine inſtitution; and therefore there is the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of both their ſealings. Now the different forme of the covenant maketh no difference in the ſeale: If it be an obligation for money, or a leaſe under large or ample covenants, or a conveyance of inheritance, wherein one parcell of land of an acre, or one free-hold, or more; one mannor, or more, maketh no difference in the ſeale or ſignature, neither doth it vary the reaſon of the ſeale, which are <hi>ex humano inſtituto obligatori:</hi> neither doth the difference of the covenant with Abraham, and the Evangelicall covenant if differing, as Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> would have, make any difference in the reaſon of the ſigning of the Goſpell-covenant by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion and baptiſme: for grant that circumciſion did ſeale both Evangelicall and Politicall, and baptiſme only Evangelicall covenants, yet they did both ſeale Evangelicall promiſes, and for the ſame reaſon, becauſe God had appointed them to be ſeals: neither doth the mixture of one promiſe with another alter the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113690:12"/>operation of the ſeale, ſeeing the ſeale doth worke as ſtrongly upon every part of the covenant, or every promiſe in the covenant, as if there were but one promiſe in all, or as if every covenant or promiſe had a ſingle deed and ſingle ſeale: but all this while what Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> hath here aſſigned as differences in forme and ſanction, are differences in matter, not in forme or ſanction: promiſes, the things granted in the covenant belong to the matter of the covenant, not to either forme or ſanction: things promiſed, whether Evangelicall or Politicall, paſt, preſent, or to come, belong only to the matter of the covenant, and do not vary the reaſon of their ſealing, which maketh the collection of Mr. Tombes ſeem to me very ſtrange; and ſo much the more, becauſe it hath the teſtimony among other things of a learned collection.</p>
            <p>But, leſt I might be anſwered, that this was affirmed but barely, I ſhall deſire that all learned men would conſider what be formall differences of covenants, and what maketh the differences of ſanctions.</p>
            <p>The formall differences of a covenant may be conſidered, either different <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> formis verborum,</hi> that is, when the ſame thing is granted in different formes of words: as when Chriſt is promiſed under the ſeed of the woman and the ſeed of Abraham. Secondly, covenants are ſaid to differ formally; if one covenant be abſolute, the other conditionall, one free, the other upon valuable conſideration; the one upon a condition already performed, the other upon a remaining condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſervice or rent; the one voluntary on both parties, the other voluntary on the one part only, and on the other impoſed: Theſe, or ſuch like, are formall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in the nature of a covenant; as for formality of words, difference in them will not make an abſolute covenant conditionall, or the like: And conſider, I pray you, what formall differencee is there in the covenant with Abraham, and the Evangelicall covenant in Mr. Tombes his own ſenſe? was not the covenant with Abraham and the Evangelicall promiſe upon the ſame condition in Chriſt through faith? were not both in Chriſt upon the ſame valuable conſideration in our ſelves equally free? Do not we all ſtand bound to faith and obedience under both covenants, as you diſtinguiſh them? Did not God equally impoſe on us all the means of our ſalvation? Where then is the formall difference in theſe cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants you talk of? unleſſe you mean <hi>verbis formalibus,</hi> which make no difference in law or equity. Your difference you talk of, is but in matter, which I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly proved to be but imaginarie; but grant there had been a formall difference in the covenant, what had that been to the difference of the ſeal that ſigneth only <hi>ex inſtituto,</hi> by the command of God, conditionall, abſolute, free, or impoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der covenant performed, or to be performed, all ſealed with the ſame ſeal, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the inſtitution put a difference.</p>
            <p>But now let us conſider what difference there is in the ſanction: Sanctions are the ratifications and confirmations of a covenant, upon which the verity and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113690:12"/>bounds of the covenant are eſtabliſhed: are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n oath: ſecondly, a ſeal: thirdly, a reward: fourthly, puniſhment: fifthly, earneſt, and perhaps, ſome other that my memory and skill will not reach to, but for all theſe they are the ſame to both covenants; for the oath that he ſwore to Abraham, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16. is performed in Chriſt, the ſubſtance of the Evangelicall promiſe in your ſenſe: and Zacharias<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 1.72, 73. doth challenge that ſanction as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elonging to him, and tell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th us plainly, that if Chriſt had not come to deliver us from the hands of our enemies, God had not performed his oath to Abraham. Now, if you look back to that oath, ye ſhall ſee that God promiſed in Abraham, to bleſſe all the nations of the earth, which was not performed, nay, not to my one nation beſides the Jews, not ſo much as by way of proſſer, untill Chriſt came under the notion of a nation; but worſhip was reſtrained to Jeruſalem, ordinances to the Jews, therefore Chriſt gave his firſt commiſſion unto the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael, but after his commiſſion was to all nations; and therefore Saint Paul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.10. entitles the Jews to honour, glory, and peace firſt, and alſo to the Gentiles: And in <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 6.18. raiſeth comfort after Chriſt, from the oath made to Abraham, and from thence I can gather (however it will ſound in Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his cares) that the covenant made with Abraham did remain after Chriſt, or elſe the conſolation is but by way of analogie: For, what comfort can we have from the ſanction, if the covenant be void, unleſſe by way of analogie, with which kind of argument Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> is much troubled, when he raiſeth them againſt himſelf, though many of his own arguments be nothing but analogies? Beſides, our Saviour doth uſe the ſame ſanction to the Goſpel-covenant in Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his ſenſe, even the covenant which he made with the believers in the new Teſtament, he doth confirm by an oath, <hi>John</hi> 5.24. Verily, he that hearth my Word, and believeth on him that ſent me, hath everlaſting life; as likewiſe, <hi>John</hi> 6.47. So that it is plain, this ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an oath was the ſame unto Abraham and under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſanction of the ſeal is to both the ſame; for the difference of the ſeal doth not make the difference in the ſanction, for the confirmation is the ſame, whether the ſeal be a Lion or a Lamb: If a Prince ſhould change his ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from his portrayture to his arms, which he may do, if the Law forbid not, or by act of Parliament, if it do, yet the ſanction would be the ſame: circumciſion and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, though different ſeals, not different ſanctions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for the rewards, they are the ſame, hell and heaven are the ſame; for that temporall bleſſing, and mixture of covenant, I have already ſpoken, to which I refer my Reader. But grant that there had been ſeverall ſanctions in reference to reward and puniſhment, what had that been to the difference of the reaſon, why circumciſion and baptiſme ſhould ſeal the Evangelicall covenant, ſeeing they are both but one ſanction, namely, ſeals? but the change of the ſeal doth not change that ſanction. Thus you ſee, how weakly this concluſion will follow from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113690:13"/>premiſes, and likewiſe, how falſe it is in it ſelf; they are both ſeals, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of being ſuch, is the ſame, namely, divine inſtitution. But for the ſecond concluſion he draweth out of the ſame premiſes, is, that baptiſme and circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are not to be adminiſtred after the ſame manner; did any man ever ſay that baptiſme and circumciſion ſhould be adminſtred after the ſame manner, that were a ſtrange and unpoſſible thing to imagine?</p>
            <p>His third queſtion, whether <hi>federate, and to be ſigned are convertible termes;</hi> and why <hi>many were circumciſed, to whom no promiſe in the covenant made with Abraham did belong: as Iſhmael, the ſame may be ſaid of Eſau.</hi> And why are theſe the only inſtances, I will grant Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> more then he deſireth, that half they that were circumciſed, were ſuch, unto whom no part of the covenant do belong: was Abraham able to know that Iſhmael was a reprobate, when he cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed him? circumciſion was adminiſtred by the appointment of God, and was not ſo intrinſecall to the covenant, that it muſt be, <hi>Proprium quart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, proprium tertio mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, omni ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li non ſemper,</hi> will ſerve: the time before Abraham, not liable to any ſeal, it had been ſin to uſe a ſeal before God gave it: and as for Job, Lot, and ſuch as lived in, and after Abrahams time, and were acquainted with this covenant with Abraham, they loſt the benefit of the bleſſing if they refuſed to be circumciſed, and what they did is not plain, the Scripture is ſilent.</p>
            <p>After God had given the ſeal of circumciſion, all that were in Abrahams houſe, and all believing Gentiles and their ſeed ought to be circumciſed: in Abrahams houſe, thoſe that were not circumciſed were to be cut off from among Gods people, and thoſe ſtrangers were not to be accounted believers, nor ſuffered to eat the Paſſeover; if they, and all their males were not circumciſed formerly proved out of <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. Then all that were in the covenant muſt be circumciſed; as for the perſons that were not eight dayes old, they were not to be circumciſed actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, nor yet women, and yet were not uncircumciſed; <hi>Privatio non dicitur de ſubjecto habili ante tempus ſtatutum: as catulus non dicitur caecus ante nonum diem, uec infans edentulus;</hi> if he die before the eighth day, it is all one, as if he were circumciſed, being in diſpoſition to circumciſion: and the female, ſhe was likewiſe circumciſed as a member of Abrahams houſe, in that ſhe was the ſeed of Abraham, partaker of the bleſſing of Abraham admitted to the ſervices, offering of ſacrifices, eating the Paſſeover, though in her perſon ſhe was not, yet in her pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, in her husband, in her male iſſue ſhe was, which priviledges no woman that was not the ſeed of Abraham, or the ſeed of a circumciſed perſon might enjoy. Now, ſee I pray you, how this woman came in to help Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> in his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that all that were in the covenant were not circumciſed, the bleſſing to the family were to all the family, but ſome aſſigned perſons were to be ſigned, but the whole bleſſed; if ye come neerer to all the perſons of Abrahams family that were males muſt be circumciſed; but what of that? not every member of the males,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113690:13"/>but their foreskins, yet every member of their bodies were partakers of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, ſo were the females partakers of the bleſſing of the family, the firſt fruits ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth the whole lumpe, the redemption of the firſtborne, Exod. 13.13. did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the whole iſſue: why may not the circumciſion of the male, ſerve for the female? that which commeth within our conſideration is only this, whether any were refuſed becauſe unbeleevers, not becauſe women, or ſuch as God exempted.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> for all his abandoning of arguments, from analogie bringeth an argument from the like, and perhaps a greater reaſon, children are baptized in their parents. But perhaps not ſo great a reaſon, perhaps no proportion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps no reaſon at all, perhaps ſuch a reaſon as Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> upon ſecond thoughts would not inſiſt on; what, when God ſhall accept of the women to ſervices, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, Paſſeover include her in the bleſſing, nor young, nor old, never require cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of her, appoint the males, ordaine it in ſuch a manner, as without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explanation could not be executed upon her: how can Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> think of proportionable reaſon from hence? that mayſuit with the baptiſing Infans in their parents which muſt afterwards be baptized in their perſons that are capable of Baptiſme in their perſons, by no colour of reaſon exempt: I pray Sir, let your next analogie have better proportion. Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> proceedeth, <hi>But it is manifeſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the Jewes comprehended in the Covenant made with Abraham, and circumoiſed, were nevertheleſſe not admitted to baptiſme by John Baptiſt and Chriſts diſciples, till they prefeſſed repentance and faith. Hence I gather that right to Evangelicall promiſes was not the adequate reaſon of circumciſion,</hi> but Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>gratis affirmat:</hi> he proveth nothing, only he ſaith, that John Baptiſt did not baptiſe circumciſed perſons before they profeſſed repentance and faith in Chriſt; notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> hath not proved, neither can he, nor any of his opinion, ever prove, that John did require that they ſhould profeſſe repentance and faith before they were baptized: it will not ſerve turne to prove that John requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red profeſſion of repentance to prove he required repentance: repentance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of repentance, be two things; neither will an hiſtoricall narration, that this or that perſon did beleeve, prove he profeſſed his faith. But we ſhall ſcan this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when we ſhall come to anſwer Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his other arguments. Hence that is from a thing not proved to a conſequence that will not follow if granted: grant John Baptiſt would not baptize circumciſed perſons untill they profeſſed they did beleeve that God did take away circumciſion in Chriſt, and appointed baptiſme in the ſtead; doth it therefore follow that circumciſion while it ſtood in force, was not dependent on the right to the Covenant, as the adequate reaſon why this or that perſon might be circumciſed, I ſhall put Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> in minde of this collection upon ſuch an occaſion as he will not deſire to heare.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee what aſſociate cauſe he will aſſigne, to ſhew that right to Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall promiſes was not the adequate cauſe; Gods precept and mans right bee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113690:14"/>aſſociate reaſons, cauſes ſubordinate in <hi>ſecundis cauſes,</hi> be not aſſociate, much leſſe any cauſe or reaſon immediately flowing from the firſt cauſe is aſſociate with any ſecond cauſe, <hi>cauſe principalis eti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in ſecundis cauſas non aſſociatur,</hi> for then it could not be principall, <hi>minus principalis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntum aſſociatur.</hi> Mans right is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Gods precept, or otherwiſe there can be no adequate reaſon taken from<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> topick place which is finite, nor any demonſtrative medium to prove them not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates, ſeeing they are all joyned with the operation of God, <hi>ſecunda canſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moventur niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otis primis;</hi> an adequate reaſon doth not exclude the ſubordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of cauſes, but only parity of ſociety; mans right to the Covenant doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Covenant it ſelfe, God commands that all that have right to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and none but they ſhall be circumciſed; is not here right to the Covenant <hi>in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere,</hi> the adequate reaſon when they and none but they muſt be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? the materialls of Gods commands are Covenants, and therefore in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture are the commandements of God called Covenants. And Deut. 29.1. Theſe are the covenants which the Lord commanded Moſes. From theſe grounds ſuch as they are, Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> denieth the major if univerſally taken, his meaning ought to be, if the propoſition be univerſall according to the limitation of the tearmes in the propoſition, the ſigne of the Goſpell-Covenant muſt agree to every perſon to whom the Covenant doth agree; not every ſigne of the Goſpell-covenant but ſome ſigne, it is ſufficient that notion ſigne in its ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall nature be attributed <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>i ſubject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> limitato,</hi> ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s it is limited in the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. No man can deny this to be an univerſall propoſition, though living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt be in a limited ſenſe, that every man is a living creature: though there be but ſome living creatures that be men; yet this is univerſally true, every man is a living creature: what ſhould a man talke of convertibility, no ſuch things found <hi>in directa ſerie,</hi> where are many univerſall propoſitions? If Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, he knew how eaſily it might be proved, and therefore is all this ſinffe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which I have cleared what chaffe it is prefixed, and you ſhall ſee what goodly limitations follow; but ſee firſt the proofe of this, if denyed.</p>
            <p>Thoſe relatives that are conſerved in the ſame ſubject, they are both or none in the ſame ſubject, but the Covenant and the ſeal of the Covenant are relatives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the ſame ſubject, <hi>ergo</hi> the Covenant and the ſeale of the Covenant are both or none in the ſame ſubject: or thus, That ſubject which is capable of two ſuch accidents as are alwayes in the ſame ſubject, that ſubject is capable of both or none; but that ſubject which is capable of the Covenant and the ſeale of the Covenant, is capable of two ſuch accidents as are alwayes in the ſame ſubject, <hi>erg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that ſubject as is capable of the Covenant and the feale of the covenant, is capable of both or none. I have not concluded the major which Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> hath denyed if univerſally ralten, becauſe it is not a propoſition; the termes are not in <hi>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> nor is <hi>eſt</hi> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> by means whereof a ſylogiſme cannot be made to make
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113690:14"/>that the concluſion; but from theſe concluſions, or any one of them, an Enthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neme will riſe, whoſe conſequence is not deniable. Thus the covenant and ſeal of the covenant are in the ſame ſubject; therefore, to whom the Goſpel-covenant agreeth, to them the ſigne of the Goſpel-covenant agrees alſo, which is the very ſame in terms which he calleth the Major. The argument is the Pedobaptiſts; but I conceive the form is Mr. <hi>Tousbes</hi> his; but why ſhould this be particularly true, and univerſally falſe, I cannot underſtand why one ſhould be capable of the figne of the covenant, becauſe he is capable of the covenant, and not another?</p>
            <p>Now, for the manifeſtation of the proof, that they are alwayes in the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the ſame inſtrument: if a covenant be written in one parchment, a ſeal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant upon another parchment will not ſeal that covenant, neither is that a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant formally ratified without a ſeal: Again, the truth of a ſigne doth depend on the connexion with the thing ſignified; ſo that if the buſh hang at one houſe, and the wine ſold at another, that is no ſigne, becauſe falſe, <hi>ens ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> be convertible: and if it be any mans duty to ſet up, or any wayes give de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative ſignes they muſt be ſet where the thing ſignified is, as neer as he can, or otherwiſe they be not ſignes; and this were a fooliſh thing in any mans apprehenſion, to ſay the land, and the deed for the land did belong to ſuch a man, but the ſeal of that deed did not belong to him, that was appendant on ſome other deed, and belonged to another perſon.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee upon what limitation he will grant the major, as he calleth it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e telleth it is true of that ſigne of the covenant which agrees univerſally in reſpect of form and ſinction to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that receive the Goſpel, but it is not true of ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are of particular form and ſanction. This is ſtrange logick, what can a Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be univerſally crue in reſpect of ſome particular? Again, Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the wrong term, what over man did deny a Propoſition to be univerſall by limitation of the predicate: the ſubject it ſelf doth limit the predicate: as if I ſhould deny this Propoſition to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> univerſall, every man is a living creature, with this limitation, that it is true of ſuch living creatures as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but of Lions and Bears it is not true, but ſee further into this limitation; he ſaith, it is not true of circumciſion; it is not affirmed of circumciſion, it is affirmed only of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall nature of a ſigne, and conſequently baptiſme; circumciſion is not a ſigne of the covenant, it was, and then it might be applied to them that were in the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but now baptiſme. A man taketh down an old ſign, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up a new, the old is no more a ſigne, it is carried into ſound back place of the houſe, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, it poſſeſſeth not the place no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> office of a ſigne; as for thoſe juggling terms of form and ſanction, I referre my Readed to what hath been ſaid of them. But the minor he denieth univerſally taken, and here is all the len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the queſtion, what labour is ſpent about the major is loſt; but that Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> is not willing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any thing true that is alled god by Pedobaptiſts, all the children of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113690:15"/>Gentiles are not ſuch as to whom the right of the covenant doth belong only ſuch as were his ſpirituall ſeed; the ground of this diſtinction is an opinion, that the covenant did belong to all that in any ſenſe were the ſeed of Abraham, but the Gentiles cannot be accounted the ſeed of Abraham after the fleſh, and therefore all the claim they have to the ſeed of Abraham is (as Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> ſtateth the matter) according to the election of grace by faith; and therefore Abtaham might circumciſe all his ſeed, becauſe the promiſe did belong to his ſeed. Now the ſeed of Abraham is to be eſteemed either by nature or by grace; they that have any way had right to be Abrahams ſeed, have right to the promiſe, but the ſeed of believing Gentiles have no right at all, the believers themſelves have a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall right. I have formerly ſhewed the falſhood of this diſtribution, and that the ſeed of believing Gentiles under the Law, were eſteemed as Abrahams ſeed in right to circumciſion: now he telleth us they have right by election, but, ſaith he, <hi>which is unknown to us but by profeſſion or revelation;</hi> implying, that thoſe that baptize muſt know the election of them they do baptize, and that they can do by profeſſion, theſe fancies I leave to their juſt occaſion to be confuted. In the mean time, I briefly ſay, if no children were under the covenant of grace, we might bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize none, for as much as ſome are, we may, we muſt baptize all, ſeeing the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of them that are, from them that are not, belongeth to God, and not to man: and this was the rule that Abraham walked by, and that we muſt all walk by, as ſhall, I hope, appear.</p>
            <p>But I come to the ſecond argument. I have the longer inſiſted upon the defence of this firſt, becauſe I conceive in anſwering what he hath ſaid againſt that I have anſwered all.</p>
            <p>The ſecond argument that Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> urgeth, as from the Pedobaptiſts from teſtimony of Scripture, is from 2 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 11.12. The argument he raiſeth thus:</p>
            <p>To whom circumciſion doth agree, to them baptiſme doth agree; but to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants circumciſion doth agree, <hi>ergo,</hi> alſo baptiſme. The major proved.</p>
            <p>If baptiſme ſucceed in the room of circumciſion, then baptiſme belongeth to them that circumciſion belonged, but the antebed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s true, <hi>ergo,</hi> the conſequent. The major of the Proſyllogiſme is apparently falſe, for to them that circumciſion did belong, to them ſacramentall baptiſme doth belong, the contradictory is true, but his meaning is, that men of ſuch condition, in reſpect of Infants, and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth, and cutteth, and divideth the major of the conditionall Syllogiſme into ſuch parts, that he may find out ſomething, that he may deny: that it doth ſucceed baptiſme he cannot deny, nor readily ſinde out a reaſon why a man of yeers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel ſhould not be able to bear as much as an Infant under the Law. I ſpeak this in reference to the diſpenſation (under the Law) of the promiſes, the condition of the Church is called infancy, the heir under age: now, how ſhould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> childe of eight dayes old, when the whole Church is under age, be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113690:15"/>circumciſion, and now the Church is at age, our Infants not able to receive baptiſme?</p>
            <p>He telleth us, that <hi>the argument ſuppoſeth baptiſme to ſucceed circumciſion;</hi> it doth not ſuppoſe it, but proveth it out of <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.11.12. but he prepareth for a deniall ſo to ſucced; that <hi>thoſe perſons to be baptized, that by Gods appointment were to be circumciſed,</hi> it ſhould be perſons of ſuch quality; but becauſe he taketh no advantage of that difference, let him alone with his own expreſſions. <hi>In this ſenſe it is falſe,</hi> ſaith he, females were not circumciſed, nor believers out of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams family, as for believers out of Abrahams family, if he underſtand it of ſuch believers out of Abrahams family, as lived before Abrahams time, or before the Law of circumciſion, ſuch a plea, to prove all believers under the Law, were not circumciſed, were vain: for to prove exemption from a poſitive Law by ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that lived before the Law was made were exempt; <hi>but for perſons that were out of Abrahams family;</hi> the promiſe was made to all families in Abraham, and they might be circumciſed, though neither bought with money, nor born in Abrahams family, but deſirous to eat the Paſſeover only, and ſo believers: they and all their males muſt be circumciſed, but for the females, circumciſion was given in terms, that did exempt females: baptiſme, to all nations, not males only, as circumciſion was, but females alſo: Beſides, the Scripture doth tell us, that the Apoſtles did underſtand all nations, male and female, and accordingly did bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. Now, becauſe God hath called in females, becauſe they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the ſigne of baptiſme, which in circumciſion they were not, may you without warrant thruſt out Infants? or, doth it any way follow, becauſe ſome perſons of ſome quality are added, therefore thoſe that were before capable are now uncapable, if God had declared infants uncapable, as he hath women capable, we muſt have been ſatisfied? baptiſme may ſucceed circumciſion, though with ſuch difference as God is pleaſed to make; but becauſe God maketh one diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in reference to the perſons, man may not take liberty to make another: As for Job, Lot, and Melchiſedeck, or whom ſoever elſe you can name, we know, if they lived after the Law of circumciſion was made, they might come, and be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, the extent of the promiſe made to Abraham did reach to them; and what thoſe perſons you name did, you cannot tell, if they had any particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption, that is nothing to the queſtion, we know none had priviledge to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance but circumciſed; and in plain terms, both in the old and new Teſtament, nouncircumciſed perſon ſhall eat thereof, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2. this is reckoned the profit of circumciſion, that they had the Oracles of God, here is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circumciſed perſon, for that it is properly aſſigned to circumciſion, as the profit of circumciſion, there it is no uncircumciſed perſon; yet Mr <hi>Tombes</hi> will tell us, all perſons in covenant were not circumciſed, this is the reverence that is given to the Scripture, when it croſſeth their opinion, though they would make the world
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113690:16"/>believe that they were the only men that did reſpect the Scriptures; he ſhould have made his perſonall difference by believers, and not believers: by Infants and men of yeers: and not by male and female, in or out of Abrahams houſe. Two ſorts of ſucceſſion (which he denieth) of baptiſme to circumciſion, is of time; becauſe baptiſme began before circumciſion ended. What if circumciſion did overlap a little, and baptiſme did begin a while before circumciſion ended? the ſame Goſpel Chriſt in his perſon, and by his Spirit in his Apoſtles, did put down one and ſet up another, that is all I ſay to that; and ſurely it is ſo frivolous, I needed not to have ſaid ſo much.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of ſignification, here Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> is put to his ſhifts, in ſome ſignif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations he confeſſeth, but not in others. Firſt, I will conſider the ſignifications he alloweth, and obſerve, that wherein they agree, cannot hinder their ſucceſſion, <hi>they both ſignifie the righteouſneſſe of faith,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Tombes;</hi> but he muſt mean it doth ſacramentally confirm or ſeal, not demonſtratively ſignifie, but how ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, he doth agree that baptiſme and circumciſion have the ſame reſpect to the righteouſneſſe of faith; and yet the hinge of all Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his work is on this, that Abrahams ſeed were circumciſed, whether they believed or no, none muſt be baptized but actuall believers, and yet circumciſion and baptiſme have the ſame reſpect to faith. Me thinks the bare acknowledgement of this is enough to daſh all that any Anabaptiſt can ſay, the controverſie is at an end, if there be no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in reſpect of faith, why ſhould faith be required more to the baptized, then the circumciſed? certainly, I would have found out ſome difference, or found ſome other reaſon why Infants ſhould not be baptized, then want of faith, or I would never have opened my mouth in ſuch a caſe. I would never have confeſſed them both ſeals of the righteouſneſſe of faith, and yet the whole weight of the buſmeſſe depend on this; that one might be given in infancy to them that have not actuall faith, the other may not be given in infancy; for no other reaſon, but becauſe they want faith. What is the reaſon, why circumciſion, the ſeal, may be given where there is no faith, but baptiſme the ſeal of faith may not; and that for no other reaſon, but becauſe faith is wanting? What? may a man make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a common accident? or make a genericall form a ſpecificall difference, or a ſpecificall form a numericall difference? this is all one, as if a man ſhould ſay, that a Bear were not a man, becauſe he can ſee, or not a Lion, becauſe he can hear; and yet after confeſſe, that both men, and Bears, and Lions, can both heare and ſee: juſt ſo doth Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> baptiſme doth not ſucceed circumciſion, becauſe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme muſt be given to believers only, yet confeſſeth, that both baptiſme and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion have a like reſpect to faith; it is true, he aſſigneth other differences, but none of them will more diſable from baptiſme, then from circumciſion: The firſt difference is, that circumciſion doth ſignifie Chriſt to come of Iſaac, according to the fleſh, but baptiſme doth ſignifie incarnation, death and reſurrection of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113690:16"/>Chriſts: doth this make the difference? can children better underſtand that Chriſt ſhall come of Iſaac after the fleſh, then that Chriſt is incamate, dead, and riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n again? Secondly, can Infants better underſtand that the Iſraelites were people, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from all nations, then they can underſtand that all are one in Chriſt? can they better underſtand that the Law of Moſes muſt be kept, then that it is voyd, or the promiſe of the Land of Canaan, then of eternall life? The difference that Mr. Tombes putteth between circumciſion and baptiſme, cannot make Infants differ under the Law, and under the Goſpel, and do they differ by that which doth agree to circumciſion and baptiſme?</p>
            <p>As for the place out of which this argument is drawn, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. Mr. Tombes ſaith, that the Text doth not ſay we are circumciſed, becauſe we are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, but we are compleat in him, becauſe we are circumciſed in him, and buried with him in baptiſme; I muſt needs ſuſpect this mans learning, or his honeſty, elſe he would never abuſe his ignorant Reader thus: what, Mr. Tombes, doth the Text ſay, ye are compleat, becauſe circumciſed? Let men that can examine the Text ſee, and they ſhall find, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> our tranſlators have dealt more faithfully with us then ſo, that have tranſlated it, in whom alſo that is, we are not only compleat in him, but we are alſo circumciſed with the circumciſion of the heart: we have that mercy ſealed unto us, though circumciſion be taken away, and we might ſeem to be without that confirmation or ſigne of the purity of heart, which our Fathers had. Why ſaith S. Paul? Chriſt was circumciſed, and that gave an efficacy to the circumciſion of our: Fathers circumciſion ended in Chriſt, and is not deſcended to us, but the effect of circumciſion is in the circumciſion of Chriſt, part of the body was put off, in circumciſion, but the body of ſin was ſignified: now this Chriſt did in circumciſion, not only ſo, but by buriall he put off that body, that became ſin for us, of both which ye are partakers, being buried with him in baptiſme; ſo that baptiſme doth entitle us to circumciſion of the heart, by the circumciſion and buriall of Chriſt, as the circumciſion of the Jewes was made effectuall by the circumciſion of Chriſt; ſo we have the ſame grace expreſſed by cicumciſion of the heart, in baptiſme: it could not be plainer expreſſed, if it had been ſaid, that the benefit of circumciſion by Chriſt is made yours by baptiſme; Circumciſion was the ſeal of circumciſion of the heart to the Jews: circumciſion of the heart is ſealed by baptiſme to you; For it ſaith plainly, in whom alſo ye are circumciſed with circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the ſins of the fleſh by the circumciſion of Chriſt, the means of all this conveyed unto you by baptiſme; no man can deny that circumciſion in the fleſh, did ſignifie, and ſacramentally ſeal the circumciſion of the heart which the Apoſtle here affirmeth of Baptiſme. After all this incongruous ſtuffe, Mr. Tombes denieth that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme doth ſucceed circumciſion, and therefore Infants are not as capable of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme as of circumciſion; he hath confeſſed that faith is as requiſite for one as the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113690:17"/>other, in regard they ſtand both in the ſame relation to faith, and thereby confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth what he doth deny, and yet no more then the Scripture doth affirm.</p>
            <p>Mr. Tombes falleth out with this argument, and in a metaphoricall way talketh of an Egge, out of which, if not reſtrainedly taken, nothing can be gathered: but that baptiſme and circumciſion in ſome things ſignifie the ſame; and do ſo Noahs flood, and the red ſea, yet do we not ſay that baptiſme ſucceeded into their place, much leſſe do we inferre any right to be inſtituted in their ſteed, reſpecting the ſame perſons; I do profeſſe I was troubled to parallel this non-ſenſe with any thing that might equall it: if we could get theſe Anabaptiſts to ſpeak ſenſe, a man might the better deal with them. Can any man make any thing of this after Mr. Tombes hath allowed that they both ſignifie the righeouſneſſe of faith? that both ſignifie the ſanctification of the heart; are they again turned into <hi>materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am primam,</hi> that Noahs flood might be parallelled with baptiſme, as well as circumciſion. You bid us take heed of ſuch argumentation; you might ſay bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and ſpeaking, in ſome things, do agree <hi>(in prolatione verborum;)</hi> and waſhing pots in ſome thing, in waſhing, in action with whatſoever we can do. Your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to Noahs Ark, is <hi>fallacia conſequentiae à genere ad ſpeciem affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mativè,</hi> thus Noahs Ark agreeth with baptiſme in ſomething, therefore in ſacramentall nature; as if a man ſhould ſay, <hi>eſt animal, ergo equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> it is a living creature, <hi>ergo,</hi> an horſe.</p>
            <p>The collection that nothing can be gathered in a reſtrained ſenſe, but that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in ſome things ſignifie the ſame; yes, more then that, they agree in ſome things, we may gather in what they agree; they agree in the nature of a ſacrament; in divine inſtitution; in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eal of faith: they muſt be adminiſtred to all to whom the tender of grace is made, not only to all that are partakers of grace. The firſt, in reſpect of providence limited to a narrow compaſſe, and by the ordinance bounded within the nation of Jews, though not to the perſons of the Jews: all nations might come in and be circumciſed, and offer ſacrifice, and eat the Paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, but they might ſacrifice no where but at Ieruſalem; but now the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are tendered to all nations, and baptiſme muſt be adminiſtred to all nations, no aſſignation of perſons by the commiſſion, ſurely the commiſſion was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by man: Chriſt commandeth his Diſciples to baptize all nations; here is not men, women, nor children, we muſt baptize ſome body; it muſt then be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined who they are that muſt be baptized? it is no wil-worſhip to baptize, it is no will-worſhip to baptize all nations, to baptize whom we pleaſe, and refuſe others without ground out of Scripture, that is will-worſhip. Now, theſe perſons muſt be found <hi>à ſubjecto capaci</hi> from the capacity of the ſubject, or from the judgement of the perſons in commiſſion to baptize. Your part requireth, that you prove In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are unfits ſubjects, and I will prove in due time, that Miniſters are unfit jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: For, arguments drawn from analogies, I willingly grant to be invalid, if you mind analogies of proportion, to invent any part of Gods worſhip by; as if we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113690:17"/>had invented baptiſme by rules of proportion, but being commanded to baptize all Nations, and told that it ſhould ſtand us in the ſame ſtead that circumciſion, in reference to ſuch principles as concerne us moſt, and did equally concerne the Iewes in the ſame reſpects, and telling us now the particular priviledge of the Iewes ſhould ceaſe, and the ordinances ſhould freely be communicated to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; never ſpeaketh one word of the particular qualification of the perſon of them that are to be baptized, he leaveth that to be underſtood <hi>ex natura rei</hi> under the Goſpell; God dealeth with the Church as fathers with their children; when they come of years tell them the ground and reaſon of things, leaving circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which neceſſity will drive them upon unto their own diſcretion; whereas when they are children the father directeth them to the ſenſitive part not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with the reaſon, but ſupplieth the defect of the infant with the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar direction of the fact to be done, having a care that he take not more upon him then he is able to beare; but when he becommeth a man if he ſhould ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſuch ſimplicity as inſiſt upon the ſame rule, and take no notice of any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable inſtruction; nor by comparing his ſtrength with infancie judge nothing of his owne power, but ſtill looke for the ſame direction as he had when he was a childe, when the father chooſeth rather to inſtruct him by reaſon, then by ſenſe, he could not eſcape the juſt cenſure of a foole. God our Father telleth us that baptiſme doth circumciſe the heart, ſealeth faith as circumciſion did, Go baptize all Nations; this is enough for a man when he is told the nature of baptiſme by compariſon with circumciſion; and ſhewed the difference in caſe of women and appropriation to the Jewes, to direct them by a rationall proportion with what God did direct his Church in infancie: ye ſhall circumciſe no more, but ye ſhall baptize; that ſhall have the ſame operation upon the heart, and you ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine my worſhip to Jeruſalem as of old, but goe to all Nations: If any ſhall further object, But what ſay you to Infants? I ſay nothing, but that baptiſme in reſpect of my worſhip, and the operation it hath upon the heart, is the ſame with circumciſion; and you know what direction I gave to my Church when ſhee was in infancie concerning circumciſion; you are capable of as much purity of heart as they were then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is all I ſay; you are now of yeares, whilſt you were children I taught your ſenſe, now I teach your underſtanding; as for argument from analogie, though it doth come farre ſhort of an argument from precept; yet it is equall with an argument from example; for indeed all that can be drawne from an example is by analogie, and among analogies thoſe are more certain that are drawne from a precept, then thoſe that are drawne barely from an example, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſhadow of a precept, when the analogie is made by God, and we are led to the thing ſignified by Gods-owne direction, and told that circumciſion of the heart is the ſame under baptiſme, as under circumciſion of the fleſh: how dare we ſay that infancie maketh men uncapable of circumciſion of the heart? when
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113690:18"/>God ſometime did declare, that that ſhould be no obſtacle to the adminiſtration of the ſigne, ſeeing we are truſted with adminiſtration of the ſigne not with the judgement of the heart; but as for that rabblement of analogies which he talketh of out of Durands <hi>Irrationale,</hi> they are things of no analogie with this. I further ſay, that it is not the proportion of the ſigne with the thing ſignified, that maketh a Sacrament but inſtitution; I hope no man will affirme that baptiſme wanteth inſtitution: and as for the perſon, if you will have him <hi>adultus,</hi> I make no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you ſhall runne upon a greater neceſſity of will-worſhip, then by adminiſtring of it to Infants, as I hope upon further occaſion to make appeare.</p>
            <p>Your third argument is out of the verge of your owne method, as not being drawne from any place of Scripture, and therefore I omit that, and come to your fourth Argument from the Acts 2.38, 39.</p>
            <p>He frameth the Argument well, if the Propoſition wanted not forme, it ſhould be they to whom the promiſe belongeth are to be baptized; but Infants of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are they to whom the promiſe belongeth, therefore Infants of beleevers are to be baptized.</p>
            <p>Mr. Tombes before he can make any anſwer to the argument, hee muſt fit his anſwer, that is, he muſt miſquote and miſapply two or three places of Scripture to the intent his Reader may conceive, that the promiſe that was there meant was not the promiſe made to Abraham, but the promiſe of ſending Jeſus Chriſt: others ſay ſending the Holy Ghoſt, all is one, if Chriſt had not been ſent, the Holy Ghoſt had not beene ſent; and the ſending Chriſt was the promiſe made to Abraham, as I have proved before out of Luke 1.73. But Mr. Tombes quoteth ſome places of Scriptures, as if a man in them ſhould finde ſo plaine a difference from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to Abraham, and there ſpoken of by St. Peter, as muſt needs give full ſatisfaction to all that doubt of that: but let us view thoſe places, Acts 3.25. Yee are the children of the Prophets and of the Covenant which God made with our Fathers, ſaying unto Abraham, And in thy ſeed ſhall all the kindreds of the earth bee bleſſed; that is plaine enough of the promiſe to Abraham, Act. 13.32, 33. And we declare unto you glad tydings, how that the promiſe that was made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fathers, God hath fulfilled the ſame unto us, Rom. 15.8, 9. Now I ſay that Jeſus Chriſt was the Miniſter of circumciſion for the truth of God to confirme the promiſes made unto the Fathers: read and judge, and judge what Mr. Tombes hath gotten by theſe places to prove any difference from this promiſe here ſpoken of, and the promiſe made to Abraham: But ſaid Mr. Tombes, the promiſe was made to them he ſpoke to and their children, &amp; to them that are afar off, whether they be Gentiles who are ſaid to be afarre off, Eph. 2.17. or Iews in future ages, as Beza is doubtfull: indeed Beza doth argue that Peter did not then know the call of the Gentiles, or if he had, it is not likely that he would have told the Iewes of it; it might be, Peter did not at that time know the Nationall calling of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113690:18"/>Gentiles that was afterward made knowne to him; for then he could not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſaid of them that they were afarre off in reſpect of the Iewes, but Peter was not ignorant that as many of the Gentiles as the Lord ſhould call had right to the promiſe, and this was in no age offenſive to the Iewes: they alwayes knew that one law was to the homeborne and the ſtranger that ſojourneth among them, Exod. 12, 48, that is, when and after they were called; they were put into the ſame condition with the Iewes in reference to the promiſe; it is plaine that the promiſe in reference to Baptiſme is the ſame that it was in reference to circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: now it is true he further teacheth the inner power and effect of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which was the turning men away from their iniquity: this is the doctrine both of circumciſion and baptiſme, that neither circumciſion which is outward in the fleſh is circumciſion, Rom. 2.28. neither is that baptiſme which is outward, but that is circumciſion which is of the heart, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God. Thus baptiſme muſt be taught, it muſt be taught as from God, it muſt bee adminiſtred as by men; therefore ſaith Mr. Tombes, the promiſe is not made but on conditions of calling, and faith which may be confirmed abundantly, Rom. 4.13, 14, 16. let the proofe be examined, St. Paul doth handle the promiſe made to Abraham in reference to the fruit and effect of it, and ſo to entitle the Gentiles to the comfort and fruit of the promiſe, foraſmuch as the promiſe did alwayes beare that ſenſe, that never any of Abrahams poſterity had any benefit from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe unleſſe they were beleevers, and that benefit the Gentiles alwayes had if proſelites, and now in a more free way; and this was ground to the Romans to ſeeke for juſtification by faith, becauſe that was alwayes the ſence and meaning of the Covenant made with Abraham; but this was the uſe that the faithfull ought to make of the Covenant: Abraham was juſtified by faith as we are; Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham was not juſtified by circumciſion, nor we by baptiſme; circumciſion was adminiſtred in <hi>facie Eccleſiae,</hi> according to the appointment of God, men had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe to examin faith, the praiſe of that was not of men, but of God: it is confeſſed that Abraham did circumciſe without any judgement of faith, yet had as much need of faith for benefit by the Covenant as we, his juſtification and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation the ſame with ours by faith in Chriſt, Gal. 3.9. They which be of faith are bleſſed with faithfull Abraham: ye ſee Abraham himſelfe had his bleſſing by faith, God preached the Goſpell to Abraham, the ſeed of Abraham had the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the covenant by faith: whereby it plainly appears that circumciſion was not given by the eſtimation of faith, though it had its effect by faith; but every male of Abraham muſt be circumciſed, and that becauſe of the promiſe, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of faith and repentance were not new conditions put on us which Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his poſterity had not, though they are more plainly preached to us then to Abraham, God was the judge of faith in Abrahams time, and is ſo now, but the promiſe of the land of Canaan ſtood upon conditions of obedience the effect
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113690:19"/>of faith, notwithſtanding circumciſion: but, ſaith Mr. Tombes, the promiſe was not belonging to them ſimply as Jews, but as called, the promiſe did belong to all men, <hi>quatenus</hi> called, but it belonged to Jews, though not <hi>quatenus ipſum,</hi> yet it doth belong to Jews to be <hi>foederati,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, every Jew had an intereſt to the promiſe, though not <hi>quatenus,</hi> a Jew, becauſe Gentiles alſo had this right, <hi>per ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens,</hi> as called, but it was accidentall to the Gentiles, ſome were called, and ſome were not; all Iews before Chriſt were called, but note, that called is to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into outward calling, and inward or effectuall calling: by an outward calling, All the Iews were called: by an effectuall, only the elect were called; whether Iew or Gentile, both theſe callings had their ſeverall reſpects unto the promiſe, and the ſeal of the promiſe: The outward call had a right to the Oracles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1. the means of faith, and accordingly many had faith by that means, though ſome did not believe, that doth not make the faith of God of none effect; the promiſe of God ſignified by the word faith, in that place, is effectuall, though ſome do not believe, though it be without effect to them that believe not, yet it is effectuall to them that believe; and though he doth not believe, yet the Holy Ghoſt maketh circumciſion an inſeparable accident to a Iew, ſhewing, that the advantage of the Iew, and the profit of circumciſion were the ſame, and the chief priviledge is, that unto them were committed the Oracles of God. Now, this outward call had the promiſe of God being their God, and the God of their ſeed, and accordingly had the ſeal given to them and their ſeed: this is plain in caſe of the Iews, they had circumciſion, and the Oracles, and the promiſe, but all theſe are ineffectuall, without faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1, 2. Let us therefore fear, leſt a promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left us of entring into his reſt, any one of us come ſhort of it: For, unto us was the Goſpel preached, as well as unto them, but the Word preached did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit them, not being mixed with faith in them that heard it. You ſee, many have the promiſe left them that may come ſhort of it, they may have the Word without profit, the promiſe of God, circumciſion without effect, all for want of faith, all theſe externall, have an externall dependance one upon another: thoſe that were born in a believing family, had an externall promiſe left them, had cirumciſion, had the word, though they might come ſhort of the effect of all for want of faith; yet the externall adminiſtration muſt go by this outward rule; the promiſe in this place is underſtood in this ſenſe of outward promiſe that belongeth to you and your children, you are called already; and that is implied in the oppoſition to theſe words afar off, ſuch as are afar off is oppoſed to them that are nigh. Now, they that are nigh need no calling, but they that are afarre off, them we call; ſo that it is plain, calling is in reference to them that are afar off; and then the ſenſe of the words is as plain the promiſe belongeth to you and your children, therefore be baptized: and the promiſe likewiſe belongeth to them that are afarre off, not yet called, as many of them as the Lord ſhall call: and this appears, in that the Apoſtle
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113690:19"/>ſpeaks unto theſe Iews, &amp; exhorts them to amend their lives, and be baptized, for the promiſe belongeth to them, ſo that the Propoſition is immediatly true, they ſhall be baptized, becauſe the promiſe did belong to them, calling of them that are afarre off, is not at all immediately referred to baptiſme, but to the promiſe, and therefore cannot by any means be a limitation of ſuch perſons, unto whom the promiſe did belong, to make fit for baptiſme, as if there were ſome perſons unto whom the promiſe did belong, that were not called, and ſome called; thoſe that are called might be baptized, but unto whom the promiſe doth belong, and are not called, they may not be baptized: but this is to alter the form and ſenſe of the Apoſtles words, though they might have a truth in them, yet they are not the words of the Text, nor ſignifie what is there ſaid: Amendment of life hath not relation to baptiſme, but to that ſin they ſtood guilty of, and that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict that they had crucified the Lord of glory: the immediate argument that he uſeth to perſwade them to baptiſme, is, that the promiſe belongeth to them, it is no argument at all why they ſhould be baptized, becauſe the promiſe belonged to their children, nor becauſe the promiſe belonged to them that are afarre off, but becauſe it belonged to them, that only was ground, why the Apoſtle ſhould perſwade to be baptized: what is further added, is to note the amplitude of the promiſe, to raiſe up their faith, to lay hold on the promiſe of ſo bountifull a God, that extendeth his promiſes ſo largely, not to them only, but to their children, nor ſtayeth his bounty there, but reacheth it out alſo to them that are not called, to wit, ſuch of them as he ſhall call; you and your children, <hi>ſenſu determinate,</hi> them them that are afarre off, <hi>ſenſu indeterminate;</hi> but if all had been limited by as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as the Lord ſhall call, S. <hi>Peter</hi> had drawn an univerſall concluſion out of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular premiſes: For, if that part of the verſe alledged, out of which the Apoſtle doth inferre this concluſion, or inference be limited, then the propoſition is particular, as thus: If the ſenſe of the words be, the promiſe belongeth to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you as the Lord ſhall call, then it is no more but the promiſe belongeth to ſome of you, a few of you, therefore be baptized every one, had been a very ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationall argument; nay, if you reſtrain promiſe to its ſtrict ſenſe, for promiſe with effect to the effectually called, then it can belong to a very few of them; therefore every one of you be baptized, were very ſtrange: The promiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be underſtood in ſuch a ſenſe, as it was when applied to Abrahams ſeed, according to the fleſh; as the faith of God in his promiſe, is not of none effect, though ſome do not believe, the promiſe muſt be underſtood by us, as left for all, though all attain not to it, and this not in reference to univerſall grace, but univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall diſpenſation of means by us men; and herein God did go before us by his owne direction in the infancy of his Church, leaving us to walk by the ſame rule; when we have a more ample diſpenſation of the means of grace committed to us. God did command all Abrahams ſeed to be circumciſed, and all circumciſed to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113690:20"/>eat the Paſſeover, though they were taught alwayes they ſhould not poſſeſſe the land of Canaan unleſſe they obeyed the voice of the Lord, Deut. 28. and 29. Chapters: and all along, Moſes and the Prophets preach the bleſſing to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, and though under the forme of works, not the covenant of works; it was faith that God looked, as in Heb. 11. all the workes of the Patriachs are aſcribed to faith, and Abrahams obedience is commended by his faith; and he and they juſtified by faith, and not by workes: faith grounded on the ſame truth of God, and the ſame Chriſt; God uſeth the ſame liberty of his will, Rom. 9.15. in the diſpenſation of his grace, 13. An inſtance out of the old Teſtament in Eſau and Jacob will ſerve as well as in Peter and Judas; the grace of God did no more nor leſſe depend on Sacraments then now. God did not account any man cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed but a beleever, no more doth he now baptized; Moſes and the Prophets did teach faith and obedience, ſo do the Apoſtles, and that notwithſtanding the promiſe; yet the unbeleever and murmurer ſhall not enter into the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan: thus went the doctrine, thus the eſtimation of God in all ages, the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Word and Sacraments to the Iewes, and them that were afarre off as many as the Lord ſhall call under the Law; but now to all Nations all are now called, God doth command all men every where to repent; in the ſence of theſe words all the world have an outward calling. St. Peter doth argue with the Jewes to perſwade them to Baptiſme, <hi>à notioribus,</hi> they knew right well the bounds and extent of the promiſe; it was no new thing to them that the Gentiles called, ſhould be accounted among theſe to whom the promiſe did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long: nor that baptiſme did legally waſh away ſinne, nor that ſinners muſt repent, but that the promiſe ſhould be ſealed by baptiſme, that only was new: as for that Peter did teach repentance with baptiſme both together, as ſaith Mr. Tombs, that is not the queſtion; repentance and faith ought to be taught at all times, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch things as God doth only look on moſt ſeaſonably at all times to all men, Luke 13.3. Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh: but out of this place it doth no way follow that repentance muſt goe before, or is required as a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to baptiſme, verſe 38. is an anſwer to this queſtion, what ſhall we doe? we, that have crucified the Lord of glory? if to this generall queſtion, what ſhall we doe? Peter had failed to inſtruct them to repent, he had been wanting to his duty, but preſently to argue from the promiſe to move them to baptiſme, and baptiſe them preſently will ſcarce ſtand with any Anabaptiſticall diſcipline; you would hardly have any great company of Catechumen's if you follow the example of the Apoſtle, which you ſo much ſtand upon, nay the keeping men of years, many yeares under the diſcipline of Catechumen's directly contrary to the Apoſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. But of preparation to baptiſme we ſhall have further occaſion to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in other arguments. Mr. Tombes telleth us, that the promiſe doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to all Infants of beleevers, which is the minor univerſally taken: he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113690:20"/>told us of women, and believers before Abraham. I have formerly given ſatisfaction to thoſe exceptions, but the promiſe is to be underſtood three wayes, as before may appear: Either firſt, in eſtimation of God, or, ſecondly, in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the inward grace of the Sacraments, and effectuall operation of the means, or, thirdly, in the outward diſpenſation of the means of grace: The two former are diſtributed according to the election of grace to the believer only, but the laſt, under the Law, to Abraham and his ſeed, and in Abrahams ſeed, which is Chriſt, to all the families of the earth: But now in a more explicit and plain way to all the nations of the earth; and that not only in <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tentia,</hi> but by particular diſpenſation, and providence unto many nations in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> actually many nations have the Word and Sacraments, and God grant more may have: But it ſeemeth, he granteth the promiſe doth belong to ſome of the Infants of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, but which they are, he cannot tell, and therefore will baptize none: The way of God was to Abraham, that becauſe he could not diſtinguiſh, he ſhould circumciſe all: God commandeth baptiſme to be adminiſtred to all nations; it will not ſerve our turns in the day of the Lord, to ſay, we did not know who did believe, and who did not: it may, and will be anſwered again, who made thee a judge of faith? thou art a Miniſter of baptiſme, not a judge of faith, that is flatly denied thee: he that is a judge, is a Lord over them whom they judge, which thou art not: it were indeed great impiety, to adminiſter baptiſme to any whom we knew God had deſtinated to everlaſting damnation, but to take upon us to paſſe that ſentence on any perſon, were moſt high preſumption, much more on any Infant: we have commiſſion to baptize all nations, but without conſent we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not baptize any nation, and this is a good excuſe: he, ſaith the Text, ſpeaketh not of Infants, but children indefinitely: but it ſpeaketh of children in reference to the promiſe made to Abraham, which was extended not to Abrahams children only, but the Infants of beliving Gentiles, as before: thus of the Argument from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt argument, taken from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. that the Infants of a believer are holy, I have already proved: that Infants of a believer, though not of the ſeed of Abraham, are federally holy, and that in the words of the promiſe made to Abraham doth appear: As for that the words in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Elſe were your children unholy: I ſay, it may well be an alluſion to that federall holineſſe, as I conceive, though the argument be not ſo cleer, that among others more plain I ſhall inſiſt upon; yet not ſo improbable, that much may not be ſaid: for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thing I affirm, that the children of believing Gentiles are federally holy, for the argument, I neither aſſert it, nor diſclame it, but refer my Reader to that that hath been ſpoken of that matter, by other men, whoſe learning and judgements I honour, and come to the ſixth argument.</p>
            <p>The ſixt argument is taken from <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. which is repeated in <hi>Mark</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113690:21"/>
               <hi>Luke:</hi> ſuffer little children to come to me, for of ſuch is the kingdome of God. The argument is, that thoſe of whom the kingdome of heaven is, are to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, but Infants are ſuch of whom the kingdome of heaven is; therefore In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are to be baptized: For, that of coming to Chriſt, though the reaſon doth plainly convince that in this place, more is meant then a corporall coming, ſeeing many come to Chriſt corporally, of whom nothing is affirmed concerning the kingdome of God: as for his eight circumſtances, he hath gathered nothing for, or againſt the argument: they ſerve for nothing but to make a noiſe of Mr. Tombes his learning, that he can obſerve eight circumſtances, of which he rejected divers as not pertaining to the argument: the other he maketh nothing of, but that Chriſt did not baptize theſe children, which no man that I know, ever affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: but doth it follow, becauſe they were not baptized, therefore children may not be baptized? after Chriſt had given direction to his Apoſtles and Miniſters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of the world to baptize all nations, and now telleth his Diſciples that to ſuch belongeth the kingdome of heaven: which kingdome of heaven in other places is underſtood of the ſtate of the Church, after the publication of the Goſpel, which began after that Chriſt roſe from the dead, into which kingdome, Iohn the Baptiſt never entred. Now, theſe little children, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.16. were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> little, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>recens nati,</hi> young ones: Secondly, they were ſuch, unto whom the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God did belong: Thirdly, they were ſuch in their viſible condition they were in, and theſe things do all plainly appear, 1. that they were little ones, by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the derivation, doth ſignifie, or ſhew it: but Mr. Tombes ſaith, words are not be expounded by their derivation, but by their uſe: But how can he know how a word is uſed, but by its ſignification: Suppoſe a man ſhould call a man that is grown a babe, for ſome childiſh condition that he perceiveth in him; doth it follow that a bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e doth ſignifie a man of twenty or thirty yeers old? I conceive Authors do uſe liberty of words, but where infirmity cannot be laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Auhour, nor penury of words upon the language, much muſt be aſcribed to the choyce of words, with conſideration of their derivation; but ſee what confutation, that they were not Infants, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith Mr. Tombes, ſignifies no more but embrace, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth ſo much; the Propoſition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, may adde ſomething more then to embrace: but why muſt it ſignifie to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a grown perſon? becauſe <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.36. he places them in the midſt, as though a child that can ſtand alone, might not be taken up in arms: yea, but he warneth not to ſcandalize them, as though a childe might not be taken up in arms, that may be taught to ſwear and lie, and by many evill examples, led out of the way of God, or cauſe to ſtumble, but the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, ſignifieth a childe capable of teaching: it is apparent that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, doth ſignifie an Infant in his mothers belly, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.44. Now, how long it doth continue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the queſtion. Mr. Tombes ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth a childe capable of teaching: but ſee how he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113690:21"/>proveth it from the 2 Tim. 3.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whence hee gathereth that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth ſignifie a childe capable of teaching: Mr. Tombes will put no difference between from his childhood and in his childhood: from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timateth that whilſt he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then he knew not, but when he ceaſed to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then he knew: that is ſaith he, ever ſince he was a boy, then not when hee was a boy; but when doth a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſe to be an infant, and begin to become a boy? For my part I underſtand not by what rules he walketh ſeeing they were infants in Chriſts armes, for ought Mr. Tombs hath or can ſay to the contrary: But ſaith he, they were capable of teaching, ſuch they might be though in armes; but how doth or can hee prove theſe children were ſuch? he will ſay the proofe lyeth on our part, that they were not capable of inſtruction: true, it doth if we will have any benefit by the argument, a demonſtration that they were not, I cannot give, but probably I can, and far before any you can give to the contrary: Firſt thoſe that brought them brought them not to that end that they ſhould bee inſtructed, but that he ſhould touch them and bieſſe them; neither doth our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our at all teach them, or ſay any thing to the children: certainly if they had been capable of inſtruction, he would not have omitted to have given them ſome ſmall directions, ſuch as they were capable of, and not have bleſſed them, and taught them nothing; for that derivation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>madidus,</hi> that cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the moiſture of temperature, which in ſome ſenſe is given to young perſons till they ceaſe to grow, till a naturall drith falleth upon their bones that hindereth their further augmentation, but that moiſture is ſuch as is on children new borne: what Mr. Goodwin ſaith of it, I have not ſeen.</p>
            <p>But Mr. Tombes ſaith, that it is doubtfull whether our Saviour ſaith of them is the Kingdome of heaven, becauſe the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of ſuch, not of them. It is plaine our Saviour urgeth the relation they had to the Kingdome of heaven to move his diſciples to ſuffer them to come to him: now it could not have been any reaſon why theſe ſhould be admitted into the preſence of Chriſt, becauſe others had relation to the Kingdome of God, but the truth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hath a further emphaſis; for the words are not urged to ſhew a reaſon why the children ſhould come to Chriſt, but why the diſciples ſhould ſuffer them, and therefore Chriſt doth repreſent theſe children to his diſciples, not under ſuch a character as they did appear to him by his omniſcience, but ſuch as they were able to judge of, and therefore he ſaith, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if he ſhould ſay, well ye have forbidden children to come unto me, but it was out of ignorance; now I tell you if any ſuch as theſe are ſhall come hereafter, forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdome of heaven: The precept is given to the Diſciples <hi>in terminis intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligibilibus,</hi> in words, and in a ſenſe that may be underſtood by them: as if Chriſt ſhould have ſaid, To many of theſe little ones the Kindome of heaven doth not belong, but you are excuſed for that, inſomuch as the Kingdome of heaven doth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113690:22"/>belong to ſuch, you are not able to diſcerne the difference, and therefore it cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaid to your charge that you did ſuffer any wilfully to enter into the Kingdome of God, that the Kingdome of God did not belong unto. But the Apoſtles might have anſwered, nay Sir, but we can diſcerne theſe unfit for the Kingdome of heaven, they have not actuall faith and repentance, and therefore we may not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them into the Kingdome of heaven: to this our Saviours anſwer is plaine; the Kingdome of heaven doth belong to ſuch as theſe, therefore ſuffer them to come to me: Now for the further manifeſtation of the ſenſe of theſe words, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is underſtood, either of the Kingdome of grace, or the Kingdome of glory belonging to the elect only, or of the Kingdome of the viſible Church where men walke under the meanes of grace. 2. The comming unto Chriſt may be underſtood of comming to Chriſt <hi>motu locali,</hi> or comming to him by faith as he ſitteth in his Kingdome of grace and glory: or laſt of all comming to him as he ſitteth in the Kingdome of the viſible Church: Chriſt hath a reſidence in the Kingdom of glory and in the Kingdom of grace. Now no man can come to Chriſt as he ſitteth in the ſtate of grace or glory, but by faith agreed on by all parties; but Chriſt likewiſe ſitteth in the Kingdome of his viſible Church, and teacheth them as the Prophet promiſed by Moſes, and there inviteth all nations to the uſe of the meanes, and commandeth his Miniſters to baptize all nations, and ſuffer little children, not thoſe onely that Chriſt bleſſed and gave eſpeciall teſtimony unto; but thoſe that were but like unto them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they muſt be permitted to come to Chriſt. Now the queſtion is, whether this comming to Chriſt is underſtood only of corporall comming to Chriſt or any, or in which of thoſe reſpects this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Chriſt is here underſtood; though I dare not deny a corporall comming to Chriſt is there intimated, yet this is not all that is meant in the direction, Suffer little children to come to me; for the bare comming to Chriſts perſon could not have beene inferred from this aſſertion, for to them belongeth the Kingdome of God. I ſit in the kingdome of the viſible Church to diſpence ordinances to all the world which I doe by my Miniſters: A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up to you, like me, ſaith Moſes, and him ſhall you heare: according to which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, I ſit alwayes in the viſible Church teaching the minde of God; as I thus ſit ready to teach, Suffer little children to come to me, for to ſuch belogeth the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church: if thus you underſtand the Kingdome of God, and the belonging of Infants thereto, to ſignifie their intereſt to the viſible Church, then, come to me, ſignifieth no more in the direction then ſuffer them to bee received into the viſible Church, which is no more then ſuffer them to be baptized, or hereafter when ye ſhall have commiſſion to baptize all Nations, baptize them: Neither will Mr. Tombes his diſtinction ſerve turne, that thoſe whoſe is the Kingdome of heaven may be baptized, when it appears that the kingdome of heaven belongeth to them, the text is not of theſe but ſuch, that is of ſuch as have no difference
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113690:22"/>from theſe as far as you can judge in reference to the Kingdome of God, theſe are to be permitted to come to me. Now whereas Mr. Tombes ſaith ſuch, that is ſuch in meekneſſe, that is a liberty not to be allowed in interpreting of Scripture to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, or rather reſtraine the likeneſſe to humility, whereas our Saviour applieth the likeneſſe only in this, that they were little children, it was not <hi>ſimilitudo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatum,</hi> but <hi>ſubjecti ob omnes qualitates,</hi> for a ſubject cannot be ſaid to be like another, if any notable diſparity can be found: it is true if a quality be aſſigned wherein they doe agree, that one quality is enough to make them alike though they differ in all other things; but for a man barely to ſay ſuch as he is fit for this or that employment, he that is fit muſt be ſuch with reſpect to his skill, fidelity, and all other conditions requiſite for that employment. Now if any thing were named wherein they were like, it was in that they were little children, now that which they were a like fit for was the Kingdome of God: and if any children can be fit for the Kingdome of God, what unfitneſſe can be found in one more then another by any mortall man? therefore Chriſt ſaith, Suffer all children to come to me, for they are all alike fit for the Kingdome of God, the viſible Church and the inviſible too for ought you know: neither doe I know that the unfitnes of the Infidells childe is in the childe, but in the parent that will not bring it, nor covenant for it that it ſhall be a diſciple of Chriſt, nor undertake to bring it up in the doctrine of the Goſpell; nor is that man that is an Infidell himſelfe <hi>fide dignus</hi> to be beleeved in that point, but if he will ſell the intereſt of his child to a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, I doe not know but that Chriſtian might bring that childe to be baptized as his upon that promiſe, that he will bring him up in the feare of God; I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, notwithſtanding the promiſe was made to Abraham and his ſeed, yet hee that was bought with money might be circumciſed: all children therefore that are brought may be baptized, ſo as they be brought by perſons that have intereſt in them, and in any charitable conſtruction may be credited that they will bring them up Chriſtians: it is ſufficient for us if they be ſuch as unto whom the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven doth belong, though the Kingdome of God belong not to them, neither can that any way belong to this argument, that Chriſt doth teach men that are of yeares humility from the emblem of a childe, yet one childe cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from another (as more or leſſe fit to come to Chriſt) by their humility: for that Mr. Tombes ſaith Baptiſme doth not bring to Chriſt: I ſay, it doth as Chriſt ſitteth in the viſible Church, into which preſence the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell have commiſſion from Chriſt to admit all Nations, baptize all Nations; as for the kingdome of grace or glory, Miniſters certainly have no power or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to keepe any out of them, or hinder any from comming to Chriſt by faith.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh argument is from Acts 15 32, 33. Acts 18.8. 1 Cor. 1.16.</p>
            <p>If the Apoſtles baptized whole houſholds, then Infants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but <hi>&amp;c. ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113690:23"/>
            <p>This argument, ſaith Mr. Tombes, reſts on a ſleight conjecture, that there were Infants in thoſe houſes, and that theſe Infants were baptized: but ſaith he, the words plainly prove under the name of the whole houſe, are underſtood thoſe only that heard the Word and believed. Hence he denieth the conſequence, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that many whole houſes may be baptized, yet no Infants, becauſe it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they may be without children: And he further affirmeth, either theſe were without children, or elſe the children were not comprehended under the whole houſe, which he laboureth to prove out of the ſeverall circumſtances of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Texts which I ſhall endeavour to examine along with Mr. Tombes, not only as he mentioneth them here in this <hi>pag.</hi> 20. of his Exercitation, but as in his Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Mr. Marſhals Sermon, from <hi>p.</hi> 137. to 142. Mr. Marſhall ſaith, that the Goſpel took place, as the old adminiſtration by taking in thoſe families together. This Mr. Tombes ſtrongly endeavoureth to oppoſe, and endeavours to ſet up an aſſertion oppoſite to that for true: ſaith he, the adminiſtration is quite oppoſite to that of circumciſion: the oppoſition which he fancieth, he feigneth to conſiſt in ſeverall differences: Firſt, that Abrahams family was ſingled out: the males only: whether in the covenant of grace, or not: children, or ſervants: elder or younger: at eight dayes old in the houſe, by the Maſter, or others in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>For, his firſt difference was, Abrahams family only ſingled out for circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that is boldly affirmed, it is plain the promiſe in the ſeed of Abraham was to all the families of the earth: <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. which is rendered by nations, 18.18.22.18. there promiſe is made in the ſeed of Abraham, which in the 3. of <hi>Galat.</hi> is applied to Chriſt: ſo that Abrahams family is not ſingled out for the bleſſing, it is true, Abrahams family is ſingled out to be the line of Chriſt, according to the fleſh; many families could not have that priviledge, but the priviledge of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was not reſtrained to Abrahams family, but extended to all the nations of the earth, and was actually afforded to ſo many families as would dwell among them, or deſired to eat the Paſſeover, as I have formerly proved it: it is plain as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as would be, or were partakers of the bleſſing, muſt be circumciſed: but the bleſſing was promiſed <hi>in actu ſignato,</hi> to all the nations of the earth, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt it was <hi>in actu exercito</hi> performed to no nation but the Jewes, yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other families beſides Abraham were circumciſed; therefore that difference is not between baptiſme and circumciſion, that circumciſion did belong to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams family alone.</p>
            <p>For his ſecond diffence, that males only were circumciſed, I have already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to that: and the third, wherein all the knot of the queſtion doth conſiſt, what is here affirmed by Mr. Tombes, is but <hi>petitio principii:</hi> as circumciſion was to be adminiſtred in all the families that would eat the Paſſeover, whether perſons that were circumciſed did belong to the covenant of grace, or not; ſo is baptiſme, there being no man on earth, that can judge of any but himſelf, whether he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113690:23"/>to the covenant of grace or no: As for the circumciſion of children, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, elder, younger, I know not baptiſme doth make any more difference then circumciſion doth; for that in the houſe, and by the Maſter of the family, or ſome in his ſtead; I ſay, that in Abrahams time, all the publike offices of King and Prieſt, were in Abrahams perſon; Levi was in the loines of Abraham, what hand the Prieſt or the Judge had in the act of circumciſion, the Scripture is ſilent: but certainly, whether it were to be adminiſtred privately or publikely, there muſt be a publike account given of it, for as much as the perſon that was not circumciſed muſt be cut off, which could not be done, but by a publike act; neither do I know a more publike diſpenſation under the Goſpel ſhould inforce a more particular adminiſtration: but the agreement in the laſt circumſtance, is that whereon the argument doth reſt: that is, that whole families were brought to baptiſme un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel: To which Mr. Tombes ſaith, that it was but contingent to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; that they were baptized, no precept, no propheſie for it: contingent it is, I confeſſe, in reſpect of any cauſes, that any nation, family, or perſon in the world ſhould be baptized, but that nations ſhould be baptized, is not without either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or propheſie: the Apoſtles are commanded to baptize all nations, the bleſſing is promiſed to all nations in Abraham, and all nations are propheſied to flow to the mountain of Gods Church, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2. but we find not infants baptized, nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies baptized in conformity to circumciſion: Mr. Tombes ſaith, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity is not intimated: I ſay, that families were baptized, the conformity ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of it ſelf; But Mr. Tombes deſireth to elude this argument, by ſhewing that actuall faith was firſt required in every perſon before he were baptized; and therefore the Apoſtles did not baptize any, but ſuch as actually did believe, and make profeſſion of their faith; ſo that they did not baptize any family, unleſſe upon particular cognizance of every particular mans faith; this you ſhall ſee how fairly he will prove: as for the examples from John, and before the commiſſion, I know they walked by ſpeciall light, but what, we cannot tell, after they had their commiſſion, certainly they walked by it: The firſt inſtance after the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, is <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. they that gladly received the Word of God were baptized, and why ſhould they not? did ever any deny, that ſuch as received the Word of God ſhould be baptized? and theſe are they, ſaith Mr. Tombes, to whom he ſaid, <hi>verſ.</hi> 39. the promiſe belongeth to you and to your children, added three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſouls, yet never a child baptized; men may as well ſay, never a man, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a woman: from the word ſouls, an Infant may be called a ſoul, as well as men or women; but, ſaith Mr. Tombes, the Text ſaith, thoſe that received the Word were baptized; doth it ſay, their children were not? but Mr. Tombes confeſſeth they were the ſame perſons that gladly received the Word of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom Peter had ſaid, the promiſe did belong to them and their children, that was the Word they gladly received: And Saint Peter inferreth from this, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113690:24"/>the promiſe did belong to them, that they ſhould therefore be baptized, becauſe the promiſe did belong to them.</p>
            <p>Now if this argument from the promiſe was good concerning them, why is it not as good for their children? and if they received the word of the promiſe gladly for themſelves, it is likely if it had been denied them in reſpect of their children, they would ſome of them have had the boldneſſe to have asked it for their children; and ſaid, Peter, you told us of the promiſe, that it belonged to our children to as well as us; and you told us that that was a good reaſon why wee ſhould be baptized, and accordingly we are baptiſed: why ſhould not that be a ground for our children to be baptized alſo? we know no reaſon why that ſhould be a reaſon for us to be baptized and not for them: You tell us the promiſe doth belong to them as well as to us; as for the limitation of as many as the Lord ſhall call, that is to be referred to them that are afarre off, not to us: afarre off, is oppoſed to them that are neare, Epheſians 2, 13. You that were farre off are made nigh by the bloud of Chriſt: farre off, ſignifieth them that are not yet called, nigh, them that are called; to looke on the words in their originall ſenſe, we do not uſe to call them that are nigh already, but them that are afarre off, that they may come nigh: and this appeareth plainly to be the ſenſe; by that here are ſeverall ſubjects of the promiſe, you are the ſubject of the promiſe, and your children and they that are farre off: You are not your children, your children are not you, you nor your children are not afarre off, they that are afarre off muſt be called, that they may be nigh, that ſo the promiſe may belong to you all, that ſo ye may all be baptized. What Mr. Goodwins fancie is, Mr. T. doth not tell us, nor have I ſeen or heard, but cannot be denied that the word ſoules doe comprehend men, women and children; for though there be ſome difference in their bodies, yet they agree all in this that they be ſoules taken for perſons; though for my part, I will not argue from hence, that children were baptized; yet I ſay from hence is clearly evinced, that children have a right and intereſt to baptiſme, becauſe to the promiſe, and that as clearly as any thing can be: for that which is a cauſe produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing an effect in one ſubject, will produce the ſame effect in another, <hi>poſita cauſa ponitur effectus rationale eſt riſible,</hi> is as true in children, as in men; he to whom the promiſe doth belong, may be baptized, is as true in children as in men, if the promiſe doth belong to them both, as the text plainly ſaith it doth; and the poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Greeke text doth plainly declare this to be the meaning of the words: for there is no point between you and your children, but between children and them that are afarre off, to ſhew the promiſe belonged to them and their children in their preſent condition to them that are afarre off after their call: where note that the promiſe is to bee underſtood in the externall or internall conſideration: according to the externall Sacraments have their adminiſtration amongſt men; which tearmes ye have applyed to Jews and circumciſion, Rom. 2.29. He is a Jew
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113690:24"/>which is one inwardly, and circumciſion is that of the heart in Spirit, and not the Letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God; the Letter ſaith, God will be the God of Abraham and his ſeed, but the ſpirit ſaith, that he will be ſo to the elect and faithfull: The Letter ſaith, every male ſhall be circumciſed; the Spirit ſaith, that circumciſion is no circumciſion which is outward, but that which is of the heart: the Letter looketh on the family of Abraham, either by generation or by communion; the Spirit on a remnant only, according to the election of grace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Letter requireth circumciſion or cutteth off, ſome ſay [Goodwins antiq. Ainſworth <hi>in locum;</hi>] the parent, ſome ſay, the child for the neglect; thus exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall performance hath its praiſe or diſpraiſe of men, but that of the Spirit hath its praiſe not of men, but of God: To this latter, only faith and repentance is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or rather both; circumciſion of the heart, and baptiſme of the heart, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but faith and repentance which God can judge, and praiſe not man; and thus the promiſe, according to the Letter, did belong to thoſe Jews, to whom Peter ſpake, even before their effectuall call; and this Peter urgeth to them as a motive to move them to be baptized: as if he ſhould have ſaid, upon this ground ye were circumciſed, and now upon the ſame ground ye may be baptized; it is true, we are not only Miniſters of the Letter, but of the Spirit, and therefore we preach faith and repentance as requiſite to your baptiſme of the Spirit; but you muſt give account of that to God, and not to us, we can take no account of it, we are not Lords and Judges of your faith, we preach all the duties that belong to the inward man, but adminiſter ſacraments and guide our charity towards our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by outward rules, it muſt ſatisfie us: if you will come and claim your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to the promiſe, both for your ſelves and your children, we muſt baptize you and your children; we will teach what account ye muſt make to God of your faith and repentance, how you muſt bring up your children in the feare of God, but we can take account of none of theſe things. The next place of Scripture which he taketh in to this confutation, is <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. by which he proveth that the Apoſtles did not take in whole families at once, becauſe the whole City of Samaria: we prove a perſonall account of all to be baptized, was not required, becauſe they were taken in by whole families in the Apoſtles time, and Mr. Tombes confuſeth this, by ſaying, they were taken in by whole cities; I like ſuch confutations. Next, out of <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. and 9.18. he proveth that the Eunuch and Paul; ſingle perſons were baptized; brave arguments, therefore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies were not baptized, the Apoſtles had a commiſſion to baptize all nations, and accordingly they performed their commiſſion with all expedition, taking in families, cities, nations, ſingle perſons, refuſing none that would enter themſelves in the School of Chriſt: Chriſt is not like a Grammar-ſchool-maſter, that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no ſchollers, unleſſe they be entred before; he teacheth from the teat to the grave, from the ABC, to perfection; the next is of Cornelius, his houſhold was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113690:25"/>baptized, as may be gathered out of Acts 11.14. ſaith Mr. Tombes, though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he miſtaketh the place: the baptiſme of Cornelius family is 10.48. But this houſhold was not an ordinary houſhold, but a garriſon of Souldiers, what mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is there in that; what did Peter cauſe them to be baptized, for feare, becauſe they were Souldiers, God told Cornelius before Peter came, that he ſhould tell them words by which he and all his houſhold ſhall be ſaved? Mr. Tombes infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that all Cornelius houſhold were ſaved: good Charity, but bad Logick; that becauſe there was vertue in the word to ſave him and all his houſhold, therefore all his houſhold were ſaved: in the 1 Cor. 1.16. Paul baptized the houſhold of Stephanus, but ſaith Mr. Tombs in 16.15. the houſhold of Stephanus is addicted to the Miniſtery of the Saints; what is this to the purpoſe? did ever any man ſay that thoſe that were baptized ſhould never after be good for any thing? he ſaith, ſome things of Criſpus and others, that the houſhold is underſtood for them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in the houſe; but comming to Lydia, he hath nothing to ſay from any cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of that text, to prove that any of Lydias houſe did beleeve but herſelfe, but ſaith it muſt be interpreted by other places where they expreſſe baptizing whole houſholds, they expreſſe beleeving and receiving the word by the whole houſhold: ſtrange that one hiſtory ſhall be expounded by another, becauſe one houſhold received the word and beleeved, therefore another houſhold that was baptized, did likewiſe beleeve: an hiſtory can but inferre that ſome that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve were baptized: but ſaith Mr. Tombes, the frequent uſe of the word houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold for growne men in the houſe, Mat. 10.13. if the houſe be worthy, certainly what portion may be aimed at, as for whoſe ſake the houſe is ſaid to bee worthy of the Apoſtles abode in it is uncertaine; the houſe there is underſtood of all, little and great, your peace is no more, but your prayers: now firſt the worthineſſe may be found in the Maſter of the family alone, and the Apoſtles may pray for the whole family little and great.</p>
            <p>But now Mr. Tombes will fall upon ſome argument, to prove that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did not take in familes, for then ſaith he, if it be true that the preſident bee an houſhold, I demand whether we muſt baptize wife and ſervants becauſe they profeſſe the faith, or becauſe they be of the houſhold? if becauſe of the houſhold whether profeſſing faith or not, then an unbeleeving wife or ſervant ſhould bee baptized becauſe they are of the houſhold; unleſſe it be ſuppoſed that the husband or maſter being a beleever, the wife or ſervant cannot be an unbeleever; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſaith he appeareth: and thus Mr. Tombs hath done his doe, and then cryeth abſurd: but where lyeth the force of his inferences, and the abſurdity I cannot tell; Mr. Marſhall and Mr. Blake ſay, whole houſholds were taken in; but it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows all houſholds muſt come in; all or none, all that is inferred out of that, is, that the Goſpell may be received by a family: and maſter of the family may tender all his family to baptiſme, &amp; the commiſſioner to baptize all the world, need enquire
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113690:25"/>no further into the profeſſion of the family, but may take the teſtimony of the Maſter for the whole family; for you change a terme, and ſay, if a wife or a ſervant, make not profeſſion of faith (you minde to the Miniſter) then an unbeleever may be baptized, and ſo he may, though they ſhould make profeſſion of faith: but you throughout your whole Diſcourſe, make faith, and profeſſion of faith all one, <hi>more Anabaptiſtico,</hi> for lay that miſtake aſide which you muſt doe, and all Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts mouthes are ſtopt; for it is one thing to beleeve, and another to make profeſſion of faith: you much talke of this houſhold, and that houſhold belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; but ſhew me any but the Eunuch that made any profeſſion of faith before baptiſme, in which caſe Philip did not teach him to confeſſe his faith, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve only: it cannot be denyed, that the doctrin of faith ought to be taught to men of yeares, and that not as a preparation to baptiſme only, but for that the doctrine of faith is neceſſary to all actions; whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne: that which we argue from receiving of families, and from the Apoſtles commiſſion to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Nations, is that Nations may make Lawes for their whole Nations to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; and if the major part of a Nation doe according to their duty receive baptiſme, and undertake for the whole Nation to ſubmit themſelves to become ſchollers of Chriſt, they may juſtly compell by any penalty to joyne with them in the externall worſhip of God, <hi>Deum eſſe &amp; colendum,</hi> is the Law of Nature: all Nations have ever agreed to ſerve ſome God, without which no humane ſociety can be preſerved: all ſocieties are united by a Covenant confirmed by an oath in the name of ſome God, and doe agree upon ſome publike worſhip of their God: but may not a Chriſtian Nation agree upon the ſervice of God in Chriſt? may they not enrole themſelves the Diſciples of Chriſt, and ſubmit to the publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, of which baptiſme is the firſt? this therefore is it which is drawne from the commiſſion directed to the Diſciples for the baptizing of Nations, that Nations may act as Nations, and families as families; that is, that the more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganicall parts muſt act for the reſidue, the Magiſtrates for the Nation, the Maſter of the family for the family; otherwiſe it cannot be ſaid to be the act of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or of the family, though a <hi>poſt factum</hi> may be hiſtorically related to overſpread a Nation that is done without any Nationall conſent to ſhew the univerſality of a ſpreading evill: yet where a duty is charged upon a Nation, it cannot be orderly received without a Nationall conſent: and that of the Gaolers houſhold doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be acted by his conſent, as the text is plaine, Act. 16.32. Paul preached to all in the houſe, but in 33. it is ſaid the the Gaoler was baptized and all his: as if the text ſhould have ſaid, there were divers in the houſe that heard the word that the Gaoler had nothing to doe with, but thoſe that were his he would preſent to Paul to be baptized. Now whereas in 34. verſe it is urged by Mr. Tombes that he rejoyced beleeving in God with all his houſe: I confeſſe Paſſor and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers render <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo; yet it is an adverbe of place, and can reaſonably ſignifie no
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113690:26"/>more but the place where he rejoyced; beſides if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould ſignifie with all in the houſe, it muſt ſignifie more then were baptized, becauſe none were baptized but his, and if under the name of his, then he had an intereſt in preſenting them. Now man can have no more intereſt in any then in his children, they are his in a more eſpeciall manner; ſo that if he had any children, it is apparent they were baptized, or elſe they were none of his, all his were baptized: And whereas Mr. Tombes ſaith, all the houſhold beleeved, or all that were baptized beleeved; it is plaine that the Maſter of the houſe onely is ſaid to beleeve, for the participle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is referred to the nominative caſe, the adverbe that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> though it ſhould be tranſlated with all his houſe, is to be referred to the verbe, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> rejoyced, they rejoyced to ſee their maſter or father ſo merry: if belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had been referred to all the houſe, it muſt have been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>domo credente</hi> with his houſe beleeving; whereas it is now to be rendred, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving rejoyced with all his houſhold, none is ſaid to beleeye but himſelfe as in Lydias caſe, is likewiſe plaine: from whence it will appeare that a beleeving ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may preſent his ſervant and children to baptiſme, though it doth not follow that a beleeving maſter may or will preſent thoſe of his ſervants or children, that are adult or of yeares without their conſent, yet he may be his authority require them to it as an externall duty; he cannot compell them to any duty, or reſtraine them from any vice without their conſent, yet he may correct them, and incline their will to any outward duty by his authority, and having wrought upon them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o conſent and ſubmit, the commiſſioner may baptize them that come ſo preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: the maſter of a family is a King, a Prophet, and a Prieſt, if by any of theſe offices he can prevaile with his houſhold, he may bring them to the performance of their duties: Now baptizing as a duty and precept lyeth on the Miniſter <hi>ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedenter</hi> to the faith of the baptized; and is at leaſt annexed to doctrine, and not to faith, they muſt teach and baptize all Nations: now it is plaine they muſt teach as well them that beleeve not, as them that beleeve; againe baptizing is <hi>modus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi,</hi> a manner of teaching; as I have ſaid, and ſhall further be made appeare up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion. Now whereas Mr. Tombes further ſaith, that then it will follow that the whole houſhold muſt neceſſarily beleeve if the Maſter doth, and proveth that ſome time it falleth out otherwiſe: I ſay, that though it bee the maſter or husbands duty to move his family, yet he cannot alwaies prevaile; and ſpeciall direction concerning the wife is given to ſuffer her in regard of the bond of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony and that under ſome limited and reſtrained tearms in hope of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; yet nothing is ſaid concerning ſervants but that he may either force them or be rid of them if they continue Infidels in that ſenſe, that is refuſe to liſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves among Diſciples; the publike worſhip of ſome God being the bound of all humane ſociety, 101. Pſ. 6. He that walketh in a perfect way, he ſhall ſerve me: he that keepeth any ſervant that will not be baptized, is not a good Chriſtian;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113690:26"/>it is true, all men of diſcretion ought to conſent to every duty; but baptiſme is a duty without conſent, as all other precepts are, it is <hi>pactum impoſitum,</hi> as before; and ſo I come to follow his arguments, lapping up two or three of them, becauſe he maketh ſleight of the arguments, we ſhall take occaſion to ſhew the weakneſſe of ſome of his anſwers, and where the arguments be weak, the weakneſſe is his, to bring them in.</p>
            <p>The firſt argument of this ſort, is taken from the generall promiſes to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and their ſeed, this hath already been handled how they conclude for baptiſme he citeth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.2. he ſaith they are for the moſt part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning temporall things, then ſpirituall alſo, as confeſſed, generall and indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; if generall and indefinite it muſt be ſo by reaſon of the neceſſity of the matter, otherwiſe indefinite would be particular; election doth not ſtop chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, they are elect when children, or never; theſe promiſes are with condition of faith and repentance, therefore not belonging to this place, ſaith Mr. Tombes. Well, then he was too blame to bring it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.22. it is foretold, that Gentiles ſhould bring their children in their armes, therefore the Prophets foreſaw the baptiſme of Infants: It is the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the beſt arguments to have the weakeſt anſwers; they might be brought to other ends, which he proveth from <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.15. but were thoſe in that place brought to the Church according to the propheſie? then Chriſt muſt needs be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as ſitting in the Church, and ſuffer them to come to me, muſt be; admit them into the Church, as I have ſaid: it is true, that men which come to the Church, come for other ends then to be baptized, but if baptiſme be the door of the Church, as it is the ſacramentall door of the viſible Church, <hi>nemine contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ente,</hi> beſides Independents, then whatſoever be their buſineſſe, they did come in by the door of baptiſme: And whereas Mr. Tombes ſaith, that was an analogie and was performed by the perſwaſions in which the Gentiles did perſwade their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to imbrace Chriſt: he formerly affirmeth little ones in armes are not to be baptized, becauſe not capable of inſtructions, and muſt bringing of little ones in armes, be interpreted by inſtructions? it is true that Junius doth ſay, <hi>cum vexill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Evangelii quod eſt potentia Dei ad ſalutem, haec omnia alleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dicuntur de am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitudine regni Chriſti ſpiritualis;</hi> but he doth not ſay, that bringing of children in armes ſhould be underſtood of grown children, capable of inſtruction, when it may be literally underſtood.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall only mention that argument, taken out of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. where it is ſaid, Chriſt cleanſed his Church with waſhing of water through the Word: from whence it is argued, that the Church is waſhed with water of baptiſme, or not partaker of the waſhing by the blood of Chriſt. To which Mr. Tombes maketh this anſwer: that if this argument be of force, the thief repenting on the croſſe, Infants, catechumeni, martyrs, and others, dying without baptiſme,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113690:27"/>are excluded out of the Church, and the benefit of Chriſt; he ſhould have ſaid, if none of theſe were capable of baptiſme, then were they excluded from the benefit of Chriſts death, where God doth prevent any by death, the party ſo taken away by God, is not deprived of the benefit of Chriſts death; God is not tied to ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo, as that he cannot fave without them, though contempt of ſacraments be ſinfull and damnable.</p>
            <p>Mr. Tombes his ſecond argument is, That which agreeth not with the Lords inſtitution of baptiſme, is deſervedly doubtfull, but the right of Infants baptiſme agreeth not with the Lords inſtitution of baptiſme, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deny the minor, Mr. Tombes proveth, becauſe Infants cannot be Diſciples of Chriſt; I ſay they may. Mr. Tombes confeſſeth Infants may be ſanctified, but it cannot be made known to us, that is not Mr. Tombes his argument, that it muſt be known to us that they are ſanctified, neither from the inſtitution doth it appeare that they muſt be Diſciples before they are baptized, much leſſe that it muſt appear: The commiſſion to the Apoſtles, and from them to all the Miniſters of the Word to the end of the world, is to make Diſciples of all nations, baptizing and teaching them what Chriſt ſhall command. The parties to be baptized, are all nations, without any reſtriction at all; their commiſſion is, to baptize all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and this in reference to that nationall covenant that then was among the Jews, only the publike worſhip was limited to the Temple then, now to no place, make Diſciples, is no limitation of perſons: Their commiſſion was to make all nations Diſciples, which they were to execute, <hi>pro viribus,</hi> to the uttermoſt of their power; the conjunction of baptiſme, and teaching, with making Diſciples, was not with reſpect to any perſonall reſtriction, but it is <hi>conjunctio mediorum ad finem,</hi> make all nations Diſciples; the meaning is, by baptiſme and teaching: Now, the ſetting down of theſe words, making Diſciples; firſt is, becauſe that was the end of their commiſſion firſt, in intention, and muſt firſt be propoſed: as in all operations is neceſſary, as if a man will have an houſe built, a city conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, an enemy taken; the firſt thing that he propoſeth, is the thing that he will have done, and after directeth, or conſulteth about the means, though they muſt uſe the means before they get the end, I have already ſpoken to this, and ſhall more fully in my arguments that I intend for childrens baptiſine: For, that which Maſter Tombes ſaith, then the children of Infidels might be baptized, I have already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, that it is not incapacity of the childe that diſableth him from baptiſme, it is the fault of the parent that will not bring his childe, nor will undertake to bring up his childe in Chriſtian doctrine; (nor is he that is an Infidell, herein to be believed) but in Chriſt, Jewes and Gentiles are all one, and a childe as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Chriſtian Religion, (according to his education) though his father be an Heathen, as if a Chriſtian; the reaſon why the ſeed of Abraham had a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, was, the Ordinances were only in his houſe, as many as came to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113690:27"/>of the Ordinances, were circumciſed, though not of Abrahams ſeed; they that were bought with money, or ſojourned in Abrahams houſe, nay, though they were reckoned as a family diſtinct from Abrahams, and the males reckoned not as Abrahams males, but their own males; yet, if they deſired to eate the Paſſeover, their males muſt be circumciſed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. Thoſe that joyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Ordinances, and claim their intereſt in baptiſime, and relation in Chriſt, to be his Diſciples, they muſt be baptized, and their families, and as many as they can undertake for, to bring to the outward means, if they can undertake for whole nations, the commiſſioners may not refuſe them: they muſt be ſuffered to come, if any will undertake to bring them, though children. Now, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by undertaking to bring their children to hearing and to learning, what is the way of God, do no more then their dutie, and what they can readily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and do bring their children to Church, and take order for their catechizing, which (were the parents as carefull as they ought) were a great means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Religion and Piety among men, and is often required in the Scripture from the father. That is, by this Anabaptiſticall tenet laid only upon the Miniſter, which turneth into a great incumbrance, and neglect of the inſtruction of the people, whereby many have been enforced to fall into that inexcuſable error that all men have the office of a Miniſter, if baptized themſelves, and have gifts, ſuch as the people ſhall approve of: But, grant that the nations muſt be made Diſciples, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt be baptized, and that all nations muſt believe before Diſciples? doth it follow, that every party muſt believe that is baptized, <hi>quod convenit parti, quapars convenit toti gratia iſtius partis,</hi> that which agreeth to any part, agreeth to the whole, by reaſon of the part; but not to every part? the whole man ſeeth with his eye (I ſpeak <hi>de actu videndi</hi>) but not with any other member, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gotten the knowledge by the eye, the ſoul implieth other members <hi>more imperato,</hi> to do their office: So the Magiſtrates that are not only the ſenſe, but the underſtanding of the nations believing may be baptized, and by the duty of their place, require others to be baptized alſo: <hi>Non quicquid totius etiam partis eſt, in totis integrantibus,</hi> a man muſt ſee before he go into the river to be waſhed, he ſeeth with his eye, not with his foot; but when he is waſhed, his foot may be waſhed alſo: the nation believeth by the Magiſtrate by whoſe authority the whole nation is put to ſchool to Chriſt, and is baptized, which is an externall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and may be required by the Magiſtrate: as for faith, we have no Lords of faith, here every man muſt give an account of his faith to the Lord of faith, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, upon his day. In the mean time, it is a moſt inſolent arrogancy, and contrary to Scripture, for any man to judge of anothers faith. Saint Paul ſaith, not as having dominion over your faith, but as helpers of your joy: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. and Saint Peter, not as Lords over the flock: if therefore they are not Lords, how come they to be Judges? what do Lordſhip conſiſt in a name, or in judicature? names
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113690:28"/>be but weake and childiſh apprehenſions of things, natures only yeeld diſtinct knowledge: Moſes could no ſooner take upon him to judge of wrong done among brethren, but preſently they aske, Who made him a Prince, a Lord, a Judge, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating that judgement belongeth to a Lord: Wee doe much declaime againſt Lordſhip and dominion over other mens conſciences and faith, yet not only Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, but every man will take upon him to judge without ſcruple, this man hath faith, and that man hath none: it is true, charity doth permit men privatly to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, but not condemne the faith of another: Baptiſme is an externall duty, ſuch as man can take notice of whether done or not: and if a man be called to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whether he hath baptized ſuch a perſon or not, or whether he went or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried an Infant to be baptized, who baptized him? he may be able to prove theſe things by humane teſtimony, and therefore they are of humane cognizance: but who hath faith, and who not, no man breathing can give any teſtimony thereto, and therefore man cannot judge: But ſome man will ſay, the foot doth not ſee, becauſe not capable for want of organs; but every man is capable of faith, that is not the queſtion, whether all are capable of faith, I mean men of all conditions; but whether faith be of humane cognizance, neither is that argument of any force that faith is neceſſary to make Baptiſme of any efficacie, therefore untill the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are acquainted that the perſons to be baptized have faith, they may not baptize them by the ſame rule, becauſe no humane action can be well done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith, no humane action can be required of any man by the Civill Magiſtrate, &amp; ſo at one blow al humane ſociety is deſtroied; but man muſt require all duties of men that they can judge of leaving the inner part of it to the judgement of God, who only can judge the heart: for as the neglect of a duty is ſinful, ſo no ſin ſo great as to enter upon the Prerogatives of God, who only can judge the heart, ſo that whatſoever is pretended from any ſpeech of beleeving before Baptiſme: yet no one place where the profeſſion of faith is required of the perſon to be baptized.</p>
            <p>The third argument is taken from the practice of the Apoſtles and John the Baptiſt, which ſaith he, are the beſt Expoſitors of the Inſtitution, but I deny it, the expoſition cannot goe before the text, John the Baptiſt that never lived to ſee the inſtitution could not expound the words he never heard of: but he affirmeth that baptiſme cannot be adminiſtred to Infants after the ſame manner as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and John the Baptiſt did adminiſter it; for confirmation whereof he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the Jewes did confeſſe their ſinnes before Baptiſme, and the Apoſtles before Baptiſme, did require ſhews of faith and repentance.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they did confeſſe ſins before Baptiſme, he proveth out of Mat. 3.6. they were baptized of John in Jordan confeſſing their ſins: but doth this prove that every particular perſon did confeſſe his ſinnes to John the Baptiſt, and that this confeſſion was before Baptiſme, or that it was an orall confeſſion? none of all theſe things are neceſſarily drawne out of the words; the words are, Jeruſalem
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113690:28"/>and all Judea, and the region round about Jordan were baptized confeſſing their ſinnes. Now I have formerly ſhewed that a Nation, or Country, or City may be ſaid to doe a thing, though the organicall part principall men only doe it. Again, the text ſaith, that they were baptized confeſſing their ſinnes, implying that the act of Baptiſme was a confeſſion of ſinne, as a man that waſheth doth by waſhing confeſſe (though he ſay nothing) that he was defiled, but if an orall confeſſion which the words do not yeeld, yet whether they made their confeſſion before or after baptiſme, is not ſaid, nor can be proved out of the Text; neither can a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept be drawn from an hiſtoricall narration, that theſe men did confeſſe their ſins, it is as much as it can prove, that it is lawfull for thoſe that can confeſſe their ſins ſo to do; but all that may be baptized muſt confeſſe their ſins, will no way fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: For the ſecond place, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.10. that is, ſome miſtaken place.</p>
            <p>He further affirmeth, that the Apoſtles did require before baptiſme, ſhewes of faith, and repentance, and citeth many places out of the Acts; whereas not one place that he citeth, proveth any ſuch thing, that the Apoſtles did require any man to make any ſhew of his faith, or repentance before baptiſme; it is true, they teach men to believe and repent, but not take any account, or require them, or any perſon to give any account to any Miniſter before they were baptized, let that be proved, and the buſineſſe is ended, to uſe his phraſe; but, to give a full anſwer to all that can be alledged of that kinde from Scripture, I ſay, that the Apoſtles did indeed preach faith, repentance, and baptiſme altogether, but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was ſaid of faith and repentance, in reference to baptiſme, was either do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall, or hiſtoricall; what was doctrinall, was without any implication of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it: what is hiſtorically related of faith, and repentance, cannot imply any confeſſion or manifeſtation, otherwiſe then in the very act of baptiſme it ſelf, ſeeing it was impoſſible for the Apoſtles to baptize nations, and countries, and cities, if no credence had been given to the doctrine of baptiſme; ſo that their declaration that they believed and were baptized, might well be related by the Hiſtorian, though nothing were intended but that, that they were baptized: For, when Hiſtorians relate any fact done, they take liberty to obſerve the neceſſary motives and circumſtances of the fact, without any other implication, then that the fact was done; nay, had not the Holy Ghoſt mentioned any beleeving at all, but only ſaid that they were baptized, we might have inferred from the fact, without raſhneſſe, that if Peter, or Paul, or any of the Apoſtles did baptize, them that Judea, Jeruſalem, that is, the prevailing party did beleeve, that there was ſome kinde of credit given to their doctrine, that they did believe there was ſome kinde of good or benefit that was like to come of baptiſme, or otherwiſe they would not have endured one or two men to have baptized them, but that a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſion of faith in a catecheticall way, whereof the Apoſtles did, and of duty ought
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113690:29"/>to take account, that is not ſaid; I hope, to make appear on juſt occaſion was not done.</p>
            <p>The fourth argument is taken from the next age immediately ſucceding the Apoſtles; what is ſaid concerning that point, is not argumentative, it dependeth only upon humane teſtimony, and men that give teſtimony thereto, are partially related where their teſtimony is agreed upon, that they did ſay ſo, as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, yet their credit is queſtioned by him that diſliketh their ſaying; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that part of the work, out of which any thing is alledged, is proclaimed ſpurious, and that very author that we are content to alledge, with honour, when he ſpeaketh for us, him we beſpatter and vilifie, when againſt us; ſo that what can be ſaid of this kind, ſavoreth rather of affection, oſtentation of reading, then of argument, and yeeldeth matter of concertation, rather then ſatisfaction; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I leave the Reader that deſireth to know more of this matter, to Dr. Holmes, and others, that may wreſtle with Mr. Tombes in this point, my reſolution being only to deal with him in ſuch things as may carry ſhews of argument out of Scripture, and ſo I come to the next argument.</p>
            <p>The firſt argument is of the ſame nature with this, that the ages that did uſe baptiſme, took it upon wrong principles, as a tradition and imitation of Jewiſh circumciſion, without univerſall practice, mixed with other errors. Among Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall traditions, many were vainly reported and taken up to countenance ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall errors, as delivered from the Apoſtles; if ſome have diſclaimed the proof of Scripture for childrens baptiſme, and held it notwithſtanding lawfull from wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker grounds, that doth not any way weaken the authority of Scripture, and ſtrength of reaſon taken from thence. If any one hath proved baptiſme lawfull from Apoſtolicall tradition, that doth not hinder me, or any other from proving it lawfull by Scripture, neither doth the mixing it with errors in the ſame perſon, make the baptiſme of Infants erroneous, if ſo, all truths would quickly be turned into errors, ſeeing few men have been without their ſlips, which yet have not only held, but defended and propagated with admiration many pretious truths: Mr. Tombes would be loth, if his Anabaptiſme be convicted erroneous, that all that he hath, or ſhall hereafter ſpeak, ſhould be therefore reputed erroneous: by the ſame reaſon, all the truths that were taught among Papiſts, are <hi>eo nomine</hi> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, becauſe they taught them: and ſo not only the doctrine of the Trinity, but the incarnation of Chriſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the dead, were therefore erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, becauſe thoſe that held <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, held likewiſe many other hereſies, and ſo his tenth argument <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>wered.</p>
            <p>His 6, 7, 8, and 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> neer alike, and all to little purpoſe, that I had thought wholly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> them, but that men would have given ſome other conſtruction then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> were weak, and therefore omitted, I ſhall therefore ſay ſomething of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t men willing to be deceived, ſhould place ſtrength, where indeed there is none.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:113690:29"/>
            <p>He telleth us in his ſixth argument, that Infants baptiſme hath cauſed many inventions to ſupport it, and hath occaſioned defect in Church policy, but proveth none of that which he ſaith: he only affirmeth, that Infants-baptiſime was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſureties and Epiſcopall confirmation: and that it brought in Church-covenant as a preparation to the Lords Supper, for abuſes that may creep in with any duty, they do not take away the goodneſſe or lawfulneſſe of the duty it ſelf.</p>
            <p>His ſeventh argument accuſeth baptiſme of Infants, with four errors: Firſt, that baptiſme conferreth grace by the work done: The ſecond is regeneration: The third, Infants dying are ſaved by the faith done: The fourth, regenerate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may fall from grace.</p>
            <p>To theſe two arguments, I plainly ſay, that none of all theſe things are occaſioned by Infants baptiſme, or if ſo, men may not doubt of the goodneſſe of all ſuch things as wicked men may, or will take occaſion to be offended at: for then Chriſt and the Goſpel ſhould be principally queſtioned, the great ſtumbling ſtone and rock of offence; ſo that occaſion of offence is an argument, rather of goodneſſe then of fault, Satan being moſt ready to entice us to corrupt our beſt actions.</p>
            <p>What, doth baptizing Infants imply the conferring of grace by the work done? nay, we ſay of Baptiſme, as Saint Paul of circumciſion, that is, not baptiſme that is outward in the ceremony, but that which is of the heart; but the praiſe of that is not of man, but of God: we cannot praiſe men for baptiſme of the heart, God baptizeth, ſeeth, judgeth the heart, we baptiſe the body, but leave the reſidue to God only; in ſteed of Chriſt, we teach thoſe children that by their parents are brought to be enrolled the diſciples of Chriſt, the things that Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmanded us, and tell the baptized, when they come to be catechiſed, that they muſt have the effect of their baptiſme by faith in Chriſt, and not by the work done. What Mr. Tombes, are all Pedobaptiſts Papiſts? theſe are ſtrange calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and why muſt Infants baptiſme neceſſarily imply, that the regenerate may fall away from grace? can none of your baptized perſons that are baptized being of full yeers fall away from the effect and benefit of their baptiſme? if that be not an hereſie, that ſuch men as are judged believers by your Miniſters, and ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged fit for baptiſme, and baptized, cannot ever after fall away from grace, I know not what is. I hope Religion and knowledge of God, is not brought to that outward formality that all ſhould conſiſt in your humane judicature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it ſeems, Mr. Tombes, when he baptizeth any he will promiſe the parties he baptizeth, that they ſhall never fall from grace. I have heard many ignorant people uſe this argument, but that Mr. Tombes, a man cried up for learning, ſhould uſe ſuch an argument, is admirable and ſtrange to me; and certainly, by this Mr. Tombes doth plainly confute himſelf guilty of that opinion, that baptiſme doth conferre grace by the work done: For he inferreth, that if children may be baptized in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, then men may fall away from grace, becauſe many, not withſtanding their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113690:30"/>baptiſme, become wicked afterward, doth not this imply, that if they were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, they were gracious? if baptiſme do not conferre grace by the work done, how can it be inferred, that ſuch men, as after baptiſme turn wicked, do fall away from grace? Saint Paul, ſpeaking of falſe teachers, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. ſaith of them, they went from us, becauſe they were not of us: not that they fell away from grace, but they deſerted the profeſſion, becauſe they were not gracious: but, ſaith Mr. Tombes, if baptiſme be adminiſtred to Infants, and they walk not according to their profeſſion, they fall from grace, no ſuch matter unleſſe Mr. Tombes will ſay, baptiſme cannot be adminiſtred but to the gracious, they fall from baptiſme, and ſo will many that Mr. Tombes, or any the moſt diſcerning of them all, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the caution that can be taken, or elſe it were a moſt happy caſe to come under their hands which cannot be imagined, unleſſe it flow from the oper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the work done, ſome of them that paſſe their examination will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be unfaithull, or at leaſt may be ſuch, for ought they can do to prevent it; ſo that if they do deceive them and obtain baptiſme, then baptiſme muſt conferre the grace, or they may remain ungracious ſtill; and ſo notwithſtanding their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, they cannot be ſaid to fall away from grace which they never had, though they ſhould renounce their baptiſme, muchleſſe by not walking anſwerable to the profeſſion into which they are baptized, or not behaving themſelves as Diſciples ought to do.</p>
            <p>The eighth Argument is taken from this, That baptiſme of Infants hath cauſed many faults and abuſes in diſcipline, worſhip, and converſation; this is likewiſe only ſaid, nothing proved in it, he reckoneth ten of theſe: Firſt, private baptiſme: Secondly, baptiſme by women: Thirdly, of unborn Infants: Fourthly, Baptizing Infants of uncertain progeny: Fifthly, they that are baptized in the the name of the Lord, know not the Lord: Sixthly, it hath brought in the admiſſion of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and prophane perſons into the Church, and unto the Lords Supper; for who can deny rightly the right of the Church to the baptized? Seventhly, it p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rverteth the order of diſcipline; that firſt a man be baptized, and after among the cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed: Eighthly, the ſacrament of baptiſme is turned into a prophane meeting to feaſt together. Ninthly, men forget baptiſme; ſo that it hath the force of a carnall right, and not a ſpirituall inſtitution: Tenthly, it taketh away, or at leaſt dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the zeal and induſtry of knowing the Goſpell: But, be all theſe faults? and are all of theſe flowing from Infants baptiſme?</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew, that many of theſe have no affinity at all with Infants bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Firſt, private baptiſme hath nothing to do with Infants baptiſme; for that Infants may be baptized publikely; nay, Lawes may be made, requiring their publike baptiſme, though Infants; nay, the Directory is at this time ſo penned, and in all times publike baptiſme was principally aimed at and deſired; and for the moſt part ſo performed; what he meaneth by private baptiſme, I do
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113690:30"/>not know; baptiſme in an houſe among ſo many as make a congregation, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcerne how that can well be accounted any ſuch fault: I am ſure he hath not proved it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He telleth us that baptizing of Infants hath brought in the baptizing by women, as though Miniſters may not baptize children as well as women.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The baptizing of Infants hath brought in the baptizing of children not brought to light: for my part, I can ſay nothing, but wonder at ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As for baptizing of children of uncertaine progenie; I know nothing of it, but that if any man that is a Chriſtian himſelfe will undertake to bring him up a Diſciple of Chriſts, ſuch a childe may be baptized.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are baptized in the name of the Lord that know not the Lord: what inconvenience from that? It is true, St. Paul ſaith, No man can call upon him of whom he hath not heard: It would indeed put on the forme of ſome probablity (if it were referred unto the perſon that did call on the name of the Lord) that it were ſomething abſurd: but doth it follow, becauſe no man can call on him of whom he hath not heard; therefore he cannot call on the name of God in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of any but ſuch as have heard of God? none can pray but thoſe that have faith: but may not a faithfull man pray for an Infidell? may not a Chriſtian parent pray for his childe, becauſe the childe doth not know the Lord? this were very ſtrange: as for the childs conſent, I ſay ſo farre as concernes the Covenant between God and man which is ſealed in Baptiſme, conſent is not required on our part to the obligation: we are bound to obedience, and are under the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of condemnation if we conſent not: and this is the very reaſon why circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which had as great a reſpect to the circumciſion of the heart as baptiſme, was as vaine, and nothing without faith as baptiſme was, yet ſtamped on the infants of the Jewes, wherein the Scripture is not ſilent; therefore this argument is not of any force that baptiſme is not to be adminiſtred to Infants, becauſe they doe not conſent, unleſſe the conſent of the party to be baptized were required to the obligation: if the childe were free from thoſe duties unto which he is tyed by his baptiſme untill he had conſented thereunto, it were a great wrong to baptize him and thereby lay a yoke upon him without his conſent, from which he were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe free; but whether he conſent or not, the obligation of obedience and faith lyeth on him, and the ſanction of wrath and condemnation attendeth on the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell and diſobedient whether they conſent or not, whether they are baptized or not, ſo that conſent both to obedience, and faith, and baptiſme; whether bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme be repreſented to them as already done, or to be done, is required of him that is <hi>adultus</hi> or of yeares, as a duty, not as liberty; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fuſing to conſent is a ſinne and puniſhable both by God and man, though theſe conſiſt much in internalls, of which only God can judge and puniſh: faith and obedience
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113690:31"/>of the heart; but as for the externalls of Gods worſhip, ſuch as are the externall rite of baptiſme that is to be performed in the ſight of men, and men may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire him that is of yeares to conſent to his baptiſme, laying the neglect on him as a ſinne, and puniſhing him for it as for adultery, fornication, or any other pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like offence, leaving the matter of faith which is private, to the judgement of God: ſo likewiſe may the Nations receive baptiſme for the whole, as all other externalls, requiring parents to bring their children as before: I have thought good to ſpeake ſomething to this point, becauſe it ſeemeth to carry ſome ſhew of reaſon with it, that no man ſhould be tyed to a Covenant unto which hee never gave any conſent, which in free covenants is true, though in publike covenants we are tyed by the covenants of our Anceſtors, and are bound by thoſe lawes wee are borne under, made by the conſent of our parents; but in the caſe between God and us, he made us, and giveth lawes to us, under which we muſt live or dye (I take Lawes here in a generall ſenſe to ſignifie direction for faith and repentance, as well as any other rules of life) not by vertue of our owne conſent, but Gods ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute right and authority.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Mr. Tombs telleth us, that baptizing of Infants hath brought the admiſſion of ignorant and prophane perſons unto the communion of the Church, and to the Lords Supper; for who can deny rightly the rite of the Church to the baptized? ſo he.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that the engagement of the parent, to inſtruct his childe (which is but his duty) will certainly be a great meanes to ſet men upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their duty therein, when men ſhall ſolemnly in the preſence of God before a congregation be charged with the bringing up of their children in the feare of God, that they muſt looke to their owne converſation that it be exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary to their children; if this be not performed by the parents, yet the charging it upon them out of Gods word, cannot but be a meanes rather to keep out igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and prophaneneſſe then to bring them in; can any means be uſed by man more available then to inſtruct children in their tender years in the knowledge of God? Certainly God hath informed us, that this is the moſt laſting know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that wee learned in tender yeares, and our experience doth abundantly confirme this. Now what greater care can bee had by the Church then in ſuch a ſolemne and ſacramentall manner for a man to bee charged with the education of his childe as a Scholler of Chriſt, as ſoon as he is able to learne any thing? if this be a way to introduce prophaneneſſe and ignorance, I know not what can keep it out; but he implyeth as a great ſinne, that ignorant perſons ſhould be admitted into communion of the Church, and the Lords Supper; for this admittance into the communion of the Church, if any thing may be argued from thence touching the unlawfulneſſe of Infants baptiſme, a juſt and due tract ought to be inſtituted, wherein the whole queſtion muſt be ſtated; what is meant by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113690:31"/>communion of the Church, whether he underſtand the viſible or inviſible Church, whoſe office it is to admit, and whoſe to ſhut out of the Churches communion? what be the rites of a viſible and what of an inviſible Church? how can the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant come and demand the Lords Supper, which he diſtinguiſheth from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church (but how I cannot tell) untill they be inſtructed to know the Lords body to remember the death of Chriſt, and examine themſelves, which they are commanded to doe, and then eat? but where is the Miniſter commanded to give the Sacrament to all that are in the Church, or elſe to turne them out of the Church? theſe things muſt be proved plainly, or elſe otherwiſe the argument drawne from hence againſt childrens baptiſme is <hi>abignotioribus:</hi> Chriſt giveth you a charge to baptize all Nations: you ſay nay: we ſhall then let in ignorant and prophane perſons into the Church; you will not baptize any untill they be fit to receive the Sacrament: you were as good ſay, you will make commiſſions your ſelves: Chriſt bids baptize and teach: you ſay there is more in the matter then ſo: you will baptize when you pleaſe, and whom you pleaſe, they that will bee baptized muſt paſſe your cenſure, and ſtay your leaſure.</p>
            <p>Chriſt hids you teach, and ſo much examination as is needfull for teaching may be deduced from thence: but did God give you in charge to admit and refuſe, and give you any rules by which ye might walke in the diſcharge of this duty? if ſo, ye might then juſtly plead this right, and make that an argument to remove all that ſtandeth in its way. But I wonder extremely at the in temperate zeale of thoſe that plead the duty of admitting and refuſing of men <hi>ex officio</hi> from and to Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper; and herein the Lords Supper is the moſt cryed up priviledge which you here fall upon (whether out of your owne opinion as it ſeems by ſome is ſuſpected, or to confute your adverſaries) and make this as a medium to prove that Infants may not be baptized, becauſe none may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lords Supper that are wicked; though for my part I doe not underſtand the conſequence how baptizing infants and charging their parents to bring them up in the fear of God would be a means to cheriſh and foſter up ignorance and ſin. But here men cry out againſt liberty to come to the Lords Supper, as if that would pollute the Sacrament, and countenance ſin; as though men might not have liberty to come to the Lords Supper upon their own examination, and yet might juſtly be puniſhed for their ſins when they can be proved againſt them: may not men make choice of their owne habitations and drinke when they pleaſe, and yet be juſtly puniſhed for adultery and drunkenneſſe? I do not know but the Magiſtrate may ſuppreſſe and puniſh ſin, though men may be allowed their liberty to receive Sacraments: For my part, I wiſh ſome ſtricter courſe were taken with ſin.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh fault laid to the charge of Infants baptiſme, is that, it perverts the order of diſcipline, that firſt a man be baptized, and after among the catechized; but who I pray you, Mr. Tombes did lay downe this for an order of Diſcipline? it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113690:32"/>ſeems Sacraments are ſubſervient principally to Diſcipline: I had thought the uſe of Sacraments had been for confirmation of doctrine.</p>
            <p>But let us once heare where this diſcipline is, what footſteps in the doctrine or practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: As for the practice of the Apoſtles, there is nothing found but converſion, and baptizing, without any interpoſition of time: that of <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.5, 6. there Jeruſalem, Judea, and all the region round about Jordan, came to John the Baptiſt, and were baptized of him; as like <hi>Acts</hi> 2. no catechiſing either of theſe perſons: if ever they meant to know Chriſt, muſt be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed after their baptiſme, or not at all; I underſtand not any ſuch duty of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing, if not comprehended in the duty of teaching; and doth this ſeem a thing ſo ſtrange to you, that men ſhould be taught after they are baptized? What? may not men be taught after they have bargained to be diſciples? This is all one, as if a man ſhould bargain with a School-maſter, that his ſon ſhould be his ſcholler, and from that day forward, the School-maſter ſhould never teach him; but this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dependeth upon the uſe of the Ancients, then authority of the Word.</p>
            <p>The three laſt confute themſelves; as for recrimination, I ſee the Anabaptiſts ſo ſoundly paid with abuſes and faults, that have been laid to their charges by others, that I ſhall not meddle with them in this point, <hi>uſus per ſe, abuſus per accidens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ninth Reaſon, that which cauſeth unneceſſary diſputes, that cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by any certain rule, that is deſervedly doubtfull: but the tenet of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants baptiſme is ſuch. All theſe diſputes are determined by a certain rule; when the commiſſion plainly chargeth the Miniſters to baptize all the world, ſo as they can make them diſciples, if any will undertake to bring them up in the fear of God, and inſtruction of the Goſpel: or they of yeers do undertake for themſelves ſubmiſſion to the Goſpel, they may be baptized, this is the rule of the Word: Abraham had not only right to circumciſe his own children, but he might buy a childe and circumciſe it; nay, if he bought it, he muſt circumciſe it.</p>
            <p>But grant that they muſt be taught firſt, tell me how will Mr. Tombes ſatisfie the doubts that may ariſe from hence? how much they muſt learn firſt, how long they muſt be catechumeni? ſecondly, who muſt judge of their ſufficiency? third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what if any ſhould baptize them before they were fit? whether that muſt be accounted a void act, and the party put again among the catechumeni? fourthly, whether, if this accounted valid, whether the party that was baptized before he were ſufficiently catechized, muſt for ever after remain ignorant? together with many other of the like nature, which I ſhall put among my reaſons for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens baptiſme.</p>
            <p>The tenth Reaſon is the ſame with the firſt, only there he handleth <hi>accidens ſine ſubjecto,</hi> here <hi>in ſubjecto;</hi> there he ſaith, it was mixed with other errors: here, that thoſe that held Infants baptiſme, held other errors; therefore I conceive that already anſwered.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:113690:32"/>
            <p>The eleventh, Pedobaptiſts agree not among themſelves, when Anabaptiſts do this, may be an Argument, not till then; and yet anſwerable, that men may ſooner agree in evill then good, as ariſing from a more common principle.</p>
            <p>And now I am at laſt come to his laſt Reaſon, and that a weighty one, ſaith Mr. Tombes: But it is taken only from a ſeeming effect of Infants baptiſme; if there be any weight in an Argument, from an effect, that is, <hi>ab effectu, proximo, &amp; per ſe;</hi> but this doth but ſeem to take away one end, and, perhaps, the primary end of baptiſme; that it ſhould be a ſigne the baptized ſheweth himſelf a diſciple, and confeſſeth the faith. Mr. Tombes telleth us, that many things argue, that it ſhould be ſuch a ſigne, but keepeth his arguments to himſelf; for my part, I know none, I know nothing charged upon the party to be baptized, as a preparation to his baptiſme: as for profeſſion of faith, that is no where required; its true, Philip did teach the Eunuch baptiſme, and faith, but profeſſion of faith he taught him not: It is likewiſe true that St. Luke doth hiſtorically relate, that the Eunuch did confeſſe his faith, but of this before.</p>
            <p>But Mr. Tombes doth prove that men muſt confeſſe their faith before baptiſme, becauſe baptiſme is a ſigne that the baptized ſheweth himſelf a diſciple, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelf a diſciple. To this, I firſt ſay, that baptiſme may be a ſigne of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but not a ſacramentall ſigne: A ſacramentall ſigne is to ſignifie what Chriſt hath ſet it to ſignifie, namely, food and nouriſhment; this is the end of a ſacrament, to lead our infirmities to the apprehenſion of the great things of God; to comprehend the vertue and efficacy of the body and blood of Chriſt, the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the fulneſſe of Chriſt, to lead our faith by the authority of God, to the apprehenſion of the things of God. It is true, our duty is annexed to receiving of ſacraments, whereunto we are bound by vertue of the command of Chriſt; but the ſignification of the ſacrament is not in our duty, but in Gods mercy; were not our duty converſant about an incomprehenſible object, we ſhould have had no need of ſacraments: But, for Mr. Tombes to deny ſacraments to be viſible ſignes of grace, without giving any reaſon for it, when St. Luke doth plainly tell us, that baptiſme doth waſh away ſin, <hi>Acts</hi> 22, 16. ariſe and be baptized, and waſh away thy ſin: and St. Paul doth tell us plainly, that the bread which we break, is the communion of the body of Chriſt, ſhewing that it is a diſtribution of the body of Chriſt; communication is properly, <hi>ſuperiorum ad inferiorae;</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I have read in Ariſt. Topic. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Partic.</hi> 6. Keck. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.72. that <hi>participare eſt ſuſcipere ejus quod communicatur definitionem;</hi> and Keckerman in the quoted place ſaith, <hi>effective individua, multa communicant: ut ignis cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> aquae;</hi> where you ſee, that communication is ſtill rendred by giving the whole nature and definitions as <hi>in univerſali,</hi> or in exciting <hi>qualitatem ſimilarem,</hi> a like quality in another body; whereby it muſt appear, that Chriſt in the ſacrament, doth communicate or diſtribute ſome grace among us: as for our duties, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:113690:33"/>vertue of the command are annexed to the receiving of the ſacrament, thoſe are externall to the nature of the ſacrament, though neceſſary to the efficacy thereof unto us: This muſt needs be a declining cauſe, that enforceth the ſtrongeſt patron of it in its defence, to deny the nature of a ſacrament.</p>
            <p>But ſee further: Mr. Tombes ſaith, that baptiſme is a ſigne of profeſſion. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is taken popularly and materially for the Art or Trade that is profeſſed, and then men may be ſaid to wear ſome badge or ſigne of his profeſſion; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in a proper and ſtrict ſenſe, Profeſſion is nothing elſe, but a ſigne of ſomething in the heart or minde of him that doth profeſſe; ſo that profeſſion of our faith is but a ſigne of our faith, and a ſigne of that profeſsion is but a ſigne of a ſigne; nay, profeſſion it ſelf is more manifeſt then any ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be, and therefore needeth no ſigne; but grant it were the ſigne of our profeſſion, what were that to prove that profeſsion muſt be before baptiſme? ſure, <hi>ſignum &amp; ſignatum</hi> be <hi>ſimul natura,</hi> the ſigne and thing ſignified, are of the ſame continuance, one cannot be before another: Here is in this argument another cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance; that baptiſme is frequently put for doctrine: therefore doctrine muſt go before baptiſme, nay rather, then baptiſme doth teach: for that which is any where tranſlated metaphorically, muſt have reſemblance with the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſignification: as if a man ſhall call his ſon the ſtaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of his age, the ſon muſt ſuſtain his father in his feeble condition: though I do not know how any of theſe places do prove any ſuch thing, that baptiſme is taken for doctrine, otherwiſe then materially, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 10.37. John is ſaid to preach baptiſme: ſo is he ſaid to preach repentance. As for Mr. Tombes Argument from witchcraft, which he confuteth, I leave every judicious Reader to think what he pleaſeth, as not being worthy the conſideration of a Divine; and thus I conceive Mr. Tombs Argument anſwered. I come now at laſt, to mine own Arguments for Infants baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that in mans judgement ought to be eſteemed fit for the kingdome of God, are by man to be admitted to the priviledges of the kingdome, <hi>viz.</hi> baptiſme; but all Infants in mans judgement are to be eſteemed fit for the kingdome of God, therefore all Infants muſt be admitted to the priviledges of the kingdome, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.13.</p>
            <p>I have already diſcuſſed this point, Chriſt findeth fault with his Diſciples, for not ſuffering little children to come, and ſaith not, I know theſe are of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God; but telleth his Diſciples, not only they, that were brought, but ſuch as they, and that not only ſuch as they in his eſtimation, but their view, otherwiſe there had been no ground of a rebuke, but commendation; rebukes be inſtructions for the time to come, at leaſt, it is not well done; do ſo no more; when you ſee any ſuch as theſe are, ſuffer them, and forbid them not. You ſee the precept for the future is generall, men do not uſe to reprove but to the purpoſe, that the thing reproved be no more done; therefore the Diſciples were to eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113690:33"/>not them only, but ſuch as they were (and that in an aſſigned likneſſe, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that they were little children) as fit for the kingdome of God, and upon that ground ſuffer them to come to Chriſt. If theſe and the like had only been fit for the kingdome of God in the eſtimation of Chriſt by his omniſcience, here had not been matter of reproof, but commendation: Chriſt would then have ſaid rather, ye did well to forbid the little children to come to me, for you did not know whether the kingdome of God did belong to them; neither can I give you any direction concerning other children for the time to come, becauſe you cannot tell to whom the kingdome of heaven doth belong; however, let theſe come; for I know the kingdome of heaven doth belong to them, and ſuch elect children as theſe are; but ye ſee Chriſt doth rebuke them, and thereby giveth them directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the time to come, which he could not have done, if the likeneſſe had been in ſecret, and things only known to God.</p>
            <p>But here Mr. Tombes and Mr. Blackwell, and others, will tell me, by this rule, Turks children, and Infidels may be brought to baptiſme. If any will bring them, and aſſume the inſtruction of them in the doctrine of the Goſpel, I know not but they may: and if Turks would part with their children to Chriſtians, I think it were a very charitable thing ſo to do: For, the promiſe was never ſo tied to Abrahams loynes, neither for ought I know, to any believers, but to education in the family of Abraham, or any other believing family.</p>
            <p>But they will further ſay then, by the ſame reaſon are they to be admitted to other benefits, namely, to hearing of the Word, and the other ſacrament: Anſw. I ſay, they are admitted to the reſidue of the Oracles of God, as ſoon as nature or grace do make them fit for them, they may have right before they can uſe them: they are firſt admitted to come to Chriſt for a bleſſing, before they are capable of inſtruction: and preparation for the ſacrament of the Lords Supper, is charged as a duty, which is no where charged on the parties to be baptized.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Sacrament, that requireth no preparation in the ſubject, is to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to every ſubject; but baptiſme is a ſacrament to be adminiſtred without any preparation in the ſubject, therefore baptiſme is to be adminſtred to every ſubject, every perſon, all nations.</p>
            <p>That Sacrament that in the ſigne and ſignification, is preparative to all other grace that is to be adminiſtred without any preparation of the ſubject: but bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in the ſigne and ſignification is preparative to all other grace, therefore it is to be adminiſtred without any preparation: the major is true, or otherwiſe there would a proceſſe in <hi>infinitum;</hi> if that which were preparative to all other graces ſhould have preparations to that, and that muſt have other preparations; and ſo in <hi>infinitum.</hi> The minor I ſhall prove out of Scripture, and plain reaſon drawn from then: <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. as many as are baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt: This doth probably prove, that men that are baptized, are baptized
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:113690:34"/>into Chriſt, which could not be affirmed, if they were in Chriſt before baptiſme; they could not be ſaid to be baptized into Chiſt, if they had been in Chriſt before, which, if faith and repentance muſt be manifeſt before baptiſme muſt be affirmed, he that believeth and is penitent is in Chriſt without doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome men will ſay, may not man believe before baptiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I anſwer no, he cannot, untill Chriſt baptiſe him with the Holy Ghoſt. Now, Chriſt baptizeth when he pleaſeth, either before, in, or after miniſteriall baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But, if Chriſt hath baptized him before, what need the Miniſter bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Chriſts baptiſme is not known to the Miniſter, whatſoever confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of faith is made, he muſt therefore baptize, in obedience to the command of Chriſt, and leave the baptiſme of Chriſt to him.</p>
            <p>How would the Anabaptiſts inſult in the cleerneſſe of ſuch a text? And here I cannot but note a notable ſubtilty of the Anabaptiſts, I will not ſay how common with other heretiques, when they have cited a Text, and put a gloſſe upon it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect to the argument of the place, they preſently cry the Scripture is all ours, crying down all the labours of the learned that is ſpent, though never ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and piouſly. For the cleering of the Text, that is, Tongues, that is Art: gives us Scripture; we have the Scripture, and then we can carry away the people, take heed that no man ſpoile you through Philoſophy and vain deceit, and this ſhall ſerve their turn, to anſwer all they underſtand not. If a man tell them that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy is converſant about nature, and ſuch things of reaſon as are too low for the things of faith, and therefore have principles contrary to doctrine of faith, as out of nothing, nothing is made; and therefore make the firſt matter eternall, contrary to the doctrine of the creation, from a privation to an habite, no return, that which is dead cannot live again, contrary to the reſurrection: but Logick is without any matter of its own, but teacheth men only how to find out the truth of any diſcourſe, written or ſpoken. Oh, then Logick is nothing but falacies, and herein many ſchollers concurre with them to hide their own ignorance, whereas indeed, falacies be no part of Logick, unleſſe you will ſay, no reaſon is reaſon: it is true, Logicians do mention falacies, as a man may teach a young workman what faults he may commit, whence ſome ignorant man may affirm, that the skill of ſuch a trade was only in faults, as theſe do, who only count Logick falacies; and here they have ſuch fooleries, to make the world believe, that reaſon was an Aſſe to their fancy, that men may wonder at them, they can ſhew how fooliſh a thing Logick is, they can prove a ſheep have eight legs, two before, and two behind; two on the right ſide, and two on the left. My Logick can do more then his, and yet we ſhall be both fools if we want Logick, to know this is no Logick: Firſt, I can prove a ſheep hath ſixteen legs, by ſetting him between four men, one
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:113690:34"/>before the ſheep, the other behinde him, and on each ſide one; this ſheep will have four legs before one man, and four behinde, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which make ſixteen, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latives have no abſolute nature: before and behind, may be the ſame thing in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reſpects, the ſame foot is before, and on the right or left ſide: this Logick can diſcover well enough, without the help of a fool to flout at that he knoweth not. I impute not this to Mr. Tombes, but to the ignorant, that cry, all is their own by ſuch a wile as this, as though none did regard Scripture but they, and all the Scriptures were cleerly theirs, what was ſpoken againſt them, was againſt Scripture, ſet by humane authority and tradition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in the ſigne it is preparative to all purity, it is waſhing ſo much faith as muſt cauſe men of yeares to ſubmit to baptiſme is neceſſary, without which the Apoſtles could not have baptized; but faith and repentance whereby the heart ſhould be purged, that thoſe muſt be had before the party may be baptized, is an evacuation of the ſigne, and fruſtrateth the ſignification: it cannot be denyed that faith and repentance are required to the efficacie of baptiſme, but ſubſequent to the Sacrament, the water doth ſacramentally waſh away ſinnes: ſo Ananias Act. 22.16. ſaith to Paul, Why tarrieſt thou, ariſe and be baptized, and waſh away thy ſinnes? Now waſhing doth ſuppoſe nothing in the ſubject but foulneſſe, the bloud of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſinne, 1 John 1.7. all the vertue of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is in the bloud of Chriſt. Now can any man ſay that the bloud of Chriſt cannot purge unleſſe the party be purged before? if faith and repentance were required before baptiſme, then baptiſme could not offer the bloud of Chriſt to purge ſinne, becauſe the party were cleanſed before baptiſme, then Ananias could not have ſaid, Be baptized and waſh away thy ſinne; but waſh thy ſinne firſt, and then be baptized. Act. 15.9. St. Peter ſheweth that faith doth purifie the heart. Now it is true, faith doth receive the Word and Sacraments, and maketh one and the other effectuall; but both Word and Sacrament doe propoſe Chriſt, the Word to the eare, Sacrament to other ſenſes: Baptiſme doth repreſent the bloud of Chriſt waſhing, and ſenſe doth looke on the waſhing of water, and faith on the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe annexed. Now as the word is propoſed to the eare, ſo water is tendred, and the body waſhed with water; whence faith doth collect the purgation of the ſoul from the teſtimony of God; water is no more the immediate object of faith then the word; it is the authority of God in the word that is the object of faith, as likewiſe the bloud of Chriſt in baptiſme; they that beleeve, and they that beleeve not, heare the word, and it is no prophanation of the word to preach it to an Infidell, neither is it any prophanation of baptiſme to baptize an Infidell; yet it is hard to make him heare patiently that in no meaſure doth beleeve unleſſe miracles, or in defect of them ſome aſſiſtance of the Civill Magiſtrate doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre; ſo that baptiſme is but an offering of the purgation by the bloud of Chriſt to the eye and the body, as the word doth to the eare, and may be tendered as the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113690:35"/>word to all Nations, the power of the one and the other is by faith in Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed unto us in the ſacrament of baptiſme or the word: baptiſme cannot worke as baptiſme till after adminiſtration, whatſoever is ſaid of it before is but the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the word; the waſhing of water doth ſacramentally ſtrengthen our faith: no duty of preparation charged on any, no man ever reprehended for receiving baptiſme unworthily; though the Miniſter hath baptiſme charged on him as part of his duty, yet never any caution given to Miniſters in generall, or to Titus or Timothy to take heed that they baptize no unworthy perſons; nor any ſinne or puniſhment charged on any Miniſter for baptizing any raſhly or without due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination; no precept concerning any difference, but baptize and teach all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the end that they may become the Diſciples of Chriſt. Now where no Law is, there is no tranſgreſſion; where God doth not charge ſinne, how dare any mortall man ſay this or that is ſinfull? if any preparation be required let the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bee ſhewed where that was taught, where baptiſme was deferred till any competent preparation were manifeſt? what Scripture is directed to the catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni; nay what one ſentence of Scripture is applicable to them, that is not appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to Chriſtians at all times, as well after as before baptiſme? Baptiſme is a religious rite which men are eaſily perſwaded out of principles of nature to embrace, as may be ſeen in all Idolatrous worſhips; they have their religious rites which they are perſwaded come from the appointment of their gods, upon which ground they receive them. Now that God did appoint baptiſme is no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, and ſo we muſt tender it to Nations by the appointment of Chriſt, which though they receive but as an Infidell doth the word; yet when faith commeth they make uſe of it. Therefore the Apoſtles argue to move newneſſe of life from baptiſme already received. So Romans 6.3.4, 5. St. Paul argueth what uſe wee ſhould make of our baptiſme; namely, that wee ſhould riſe with Chriſt; but though the moſt noble way of arguing be from cauſes, and therefore in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords ſupper, where the worthy receiving of that doth depend on an antecedent cauſe; there faith is ſaid to obtaine the whole vertue of the worke. Joh. 6.35. I am the bread, he that commeth to me ſhall never hunger, and he that beleeveth on me ſhall never thirſt, v. 47. He that beleeveth hath everlaſting life, 51. Hee that eateth of this bread ſhall live for ever: Whereby he plainly ſaith, That he that beleeveth eateth my fleſh, this bread which is my fleſh ſacramentally, and made ſuch to me by faith. Never any ſuch doctrine as this, he that beleeveth is baptized, becauſe no doctrine is extant precedent to baptiſme in reference to the Gentiles. See all the Epiſtles to the Rom. Corinthians, and the reſidue, all are written to Churches already baptized. Paul declared the whole counſell of God, and yet not one word what ſhould be the carriage of the Catechumeni, or the Miniſters towards them, as if he ſhould ſuppoſe none under the right of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell that will not firſt bee baptized, and received by the commandement of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:113690:35"/>Chriſt: ſo he that will teach any thing in St. Pauls Epiſtles, they muſt teach them to the baptized to whom they are directed; as for the Catechumeni, nothing is written or directed either to them or concerning them. As for thoſe hiſtories of the Acts, the greater part were Jews in Covenant with God already; unto whom Peter did indeed preach repentance in reference to that bloud that they were guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of in killing the Lord of glory; not as preparation to baptiſme, but repentance and baptiſme are both exhorted unto as precedent to the gift of the Holy Ghoſt; whereas if ſuch preparation had been needfull to baptiſme, Peter ſhould have ſtayed for the gift of the Holy Ghoſt to manifeſt their fitneſſe, or at leaſt given them ſome directions by which they might manifeſt their fitneſſe, or ſhew their repentance and faith, which he never did. St. Luke doth indeed ſay, They that gladly received the word were baptized; but that they manifeſted it any way but by receiving baptiſme gladly doth not appeare; and this was ground enough for an Hiſtorian to ſay they gladly received the word, wherein they were exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be baptized when they were gladly baptized.</p>
            <p>As for that ſtory of Cornelius that was indeed a pure Gentile. Though Peter had commiſſion enough to have gone to him by the command of Chriſt, Mat. 28.19. and to have baptized him and taught him the commands of Chriſt, yet it is plaine Peter did not underſtand the Commiſſion, therefore God for Peters owne ſatisfaction, and the ſatisfaction of them of the circumciſion, was pleaſed in all that ſtory to goe before Peter in a miraculous way; Peter was ſo farre from bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of Cornelius, that he was hardly perſwaded to goe to him or preach to him, but as God did go before him by miracles, which when they of the circumciſion ſaw, the text ſaith, they were aſtoniſhed: And of this very ſtory St. Peter, Act. 15. and other places maketh uſe of to ſatisfie the Jewes touching the calling of the Gentiles: but this was the mercy of God during the infancie of the Church to uſe ſuch extraordinary meanes for the drawing off the Jewes from that ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall diſtinction that God himſelfe had put between Jewes and Gentiles, but in the orderly adminiſtration God ſent the Holy Ghoſt, though by extraordinary manifeſtations, yet in a ſeaſonable time when firſt he had tendered the meanes of grace: As for the falling of the Holy Choſt upon the Apoſtles in cloven tongues, Act. 2. that came ſeaſonably upon them when they had occaſion to uſe them, and after had been baptized; but the Holy Ghoſt promiſed in v. 28. is promiſed after Peter had preached repentance and baptiſme; nay on many after they were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, Repent and be baptized, and ye ſhall receive the holy Ghoſt: ſhewing that preaching and baptizing are but the tenders of grace, neither the one nor the other of any force unleſſe the Holy Ghoſt come. Now though the manner of the giving the Holy Ghoſt be different, yet the ſeaſon is according to the way of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, God will have outward means firſt tendered, and after he will bleſſe it where he pleaſeth, among which outward meanes theſe are chiefe, if not all can
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:113690:36"/>or ought to be uſed by way of tender baptiſme, and teaching, which is all that is tendred in the commiſſion, whatſoever is is babbled to the contrary: baptiſing is ſet before teaching the commands of Chriſt, as I have formerly manifeſted; and indeed, it were a ſtrange thing for the ſacrament of baptiſme to be tendered to men that were already clean, and approved, declared and manifeſted to be clean; it is true, it may be tendered to men that profeſſe their faith, becauſe man cannot judge them faithfull, notwithſtanding any profeſſion, and therefore bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe them; but if they could know and judge them faithfull, they might give them the Lords ſupper, in which all Chriſt is communicated, and baptiſme ſhould not be needfull; baptiſme is the ſeal of the tender of Chriſt, and of the purging power of his blood, not of our communion or partaking of Chriſt, that is ſealed in the other ſacrament.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the ſignification, it is preparative to all other graces, it ſignifieth regeneration; and therefore it is called regeneration, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. Except ye be regenerate by water and the Spirit, ye cannot enter into the kingdome of heaven. Now, certainly the Holy Ghoſt would not ſet forth the grace of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme by regeneration, or newbirth, if any grace had been preparative to it, it is not poſſible that any life or motion ſhould be imagined before regeneration: It is true, in <hi>John</hi> 3.5. Except ye be born by water and the Spirit, unleſſe ye be by water and the Spirit; that which we tranſlate born, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>be,</hi> and <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. Baptiſme is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the laver of regeneration. Leſt men may vulgarly imagine, that men are ſpiritually begotten by the Word, and were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſome time in their mothers belly, the church, before they were brought forth by baptiſme: during which time, they were to be catechumens, and made fit to be received into the Church: that word which is tranſlated born, <hi>John</hi> 3. in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. is tranſlated begotten, I have begotten you through the Goſpel: For, there it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and indeed, there can be no imagination of life before there is a being, before begetting; it is true, <hi>adultus</hi> muſt have faith, ſuch as it is, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, humane: before he can be baptized, he muſt be willing by ſome inclination or other: it were barbarous to baptize a grown man againſt his will, which could not be gotten but by ſome kinde of credence, though it might be juſt with man to puniſh him with death that ſhould refuſe, as it is with God to puniſh with eternall death, ſuch as deſpiſe baptiſme; yet that Miniſters ſhould refuſe to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe any man that ſhall deſire baptiſme, untill he hath ſaving faith, is to require actions of life, and reaſon from a man before he were begotten, or cleanneſſe and purity before he were waſhed. Again, that ſacrament that was adminiſtred unto all the churches of the Gentiles in the Scripture mentioned, without any mention in the Scripture, of any preparative grace that muſt it ſelf be the ſymbol of the firſt grace, and preparative of all other graces: But baptiſme is ſuch, therefore baptiſm is preparative to all other graces. Let all the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles be ſearched,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:113690:36"/>and ye ſhall finde they were all written to baptized perſons, that they are full of exhortations to faith, and ſometimes arguments drawn from baptiſme paſt, to move them to repentance and newneſſe of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. St. Paul doth indeed tell them that they were buried by baptiſm with Chriſt, but what doth he collect out of that? therefore repent and believe, but doth he at any time, ſpeaking of faith, and repentance, argue from thence to baptiſme, and tell any of them, if they would believe and repent, they ſhould be baptized? which the right method of handling the doctrine of the Goſpel would have required, if faith and repentance had been preparatives; but I am confident, if any man ſhall take on him to teach faith, and repentance, as preparatives to baptiſme, he muſt either make his Text, or draw that out of it that will not come: he that will teach any doctrine other then ſo much as may make them willing to be baptized, and repute them diſciples, and teach them as diſciples of Chriſt unbaptized, muſt follow no Apoſtolicall Precept or Example. That which is drawn out of the commiſsion, is without ground, that teaching muſt go before baptizing, becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is ſet firſt: For, firſt the phraſe of the words is changed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whereas had there been a methodicall enumeration of things that ought to have been performed in order one before another, the ſtile ought not to have been altered; it ſhould have been, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Go, teach and baptize; and therefore thoſe that would gather any thing out of the order of the words, muſt be enforced to read them ſo, which the Text will not permit. Again, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>riſt.</hi> in the Imperative mood, which ſtandeth for a Future, whereas the words, baptizing and teaching what I command, are both Preſent. Again, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ye ſhall make diſciples, is the end, and ought to be the firſt ſet down, and declared to thoſe that ſhall be imployed about the means, as I have formerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſo the ſtile doth clearely manifeſt, ye ſhall make all the world diſciples, baptizing them, and teaching them whatſoever I command, which is as much as by ſo doing, ye ſhall make them diſciples: as if a man ſhould ſay ſowing in ſeaſon, and making good choice of your ſeed and land, ye ſhall have a good crop; here is plainly intended, that theſe Participiall expreſsions, this ſowing and making good choice ſhall be taken up for the mean, and the crop is to be expected after, as the ſucceſſe and event of them: as for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to learn, and therefore ſome collect, that it doth imply a learning with profit, that is nothing to the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; if there be any thing in that, it is in the ſucceſſe, and it hath the vertue of a promiſe, and is eſtimated by God, limited and extended according to the good pleaſure of God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 48.17. I am the Lord thy God, that teacheth thee to profit: Paul plants, Apollo watereth, it is God that giveth the ſucceſſe; and if it ſhould ſtand in that ſenſe as a preparation to baptiſme in the commiſsion, it muſt contain a manifeſt falſhood, or prove undeniably univerſall grace, if they ſhall teach with profit all nations, and baptize them; or at leaſt, an univerſall nationall acceptation
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:113690:37"/>of the Goſpell, teaching with profit can admit of no milder ſenſe then that; and if every perſon muſt be taught with profit before he be baptized, then none ought to be baptized but the elect of God; and it were a ſin for any Miniſter to baptize any other but ſuch as received profit by the word, the word worketh to the hurt of the reprobate whatſoever ſhew of profit it may ſeem to have.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reaſon, That doctrine that taketh away the diſtinction of the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that is a falſe doctrine; but Anabaptiſme doth take away the diſtinction of the two Sacraments, <hi>ergo,</hi> the doctrine of the Anabaptiſts is a falſe doctrine. That doctrine that requireth preparation to both Sacraments, taketh away the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Sacraments; but Anabaptiſts require preparation to both Sacraments, therefore Anabaptiſts take away the difference of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>The difference doth conſiſt in this, that the Sacrament of baptiſme is prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the Lords Supper, ſacramentally giving that to us which we ſtand in need of, to make us fit for the Lords Supper: I ſay, ſacramentally, not that God cannot or doth not take his owne time of calling ſometime before we are partaker of either Sacrament, ſometimes after we have both Sacraments; yea and after we have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully prophaned the Lords Supper: but Sacraments have their proper uſe and ſignification, and are as all other duties lyable to abuſe. Wee muſt behave our ſelves as men under the meanes: we have our duties charged upon us of God, whereof ſome are officiall, ſome perſonall belonging to every mans perſon, about the performance of all which, we may ſinne either by omiſſion or miſuſe; but all the good that we receive by word or ſacraments is of God: what we doe by way of office that lyeth charged on us by the rule that we receive from God, which is to baptize all Nations and teach them; the ſucceſſe is of God, and the account of faith muſt be given to God; we can take ſome account of ſome workes, to wit, thoſe that are externall; but of faith and of ſuch workes as are imminent the thoughts of the heart, we can ſay nothing to them. Now the communion that is between Chriſt and us, is ſet downe in Scripture by Chriſts being or dwelling in us, and we in him; we muſt firſt be in Chriſt before he can be in us: we were in Chriſt by election before the foundation of the world, and therefore may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into Chriſt before we can have faith; nay we are ſaid to be baptized into Chriſt, Rom. 6.3. ſo many of you are baptized into Chriſt Jeſus, and the grace of baptiſme is ſaid to be wrought by the Spirit, by the Spirit ye are baptized into one body, 1 Cor. 12.13. and Gal. 3.27. As many as are baptized into Chriſt have put on Chriſt: Chriſt is never ſaid to be conveyed into us by baptiſme, but by faith. Epheſ. 3.17. That Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith: what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally ours by faith, is ſacramentally ours by the Lords ſupper: he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that eateh Chriſt in the Lords ſupper, Chriſt is in him. Iohn. 6.56. Hee that eateth my fleſh dwelleth in me, and I in him: but Chriſt is never laid to be in us by baptiſme, but we are baptiſed into Chriſt; he is not baptized into us, but he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:113690:37"/>into us in the Lords ſupper, for which faith is required as a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the habitation of Chriſt in us is aſcribed to faith as a meanes as before, that Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith; but our birth in Chriſt, or regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raion is not at all aſcribed to faith, but to the Spirit and water, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. Except a man be born by water and the Spirit: and to the Word, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. I have begotten you through the Word, but never are we ſaid, either to be born or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by faith: the acts of faith, are growth, life, and fruits of ſanctification, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.35. Thoſe that believe and come to Chriſt, are ſaid to eat and drink Chriſt: For, he that cometh unto Chriſt, is promiſed he ſhall never hunger; and he that believeth in him, ſhall never thirſt. And this vertue is aſcribed to the body and blood of Chriſt, from whence Divines do juſtly gather, that he that believeth, doth eat the fleſh, and drink the blood of Chriſt, but no intimation in Scripture from whence any man can collect, that he that believeth is baptized, unleſſe it be <hi>à po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriori:</hi> For, he that doth believe, muſt firſt be baptized by the Spirit, before he can believe; and thus are the graces offered in the ſacraments, kept diſtinct, which otherwiſe would be the ſame: that the grace of baptiſme is initiall, that of the Lords ſupper is perfective, which may further be maniſted thus: our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hath two parts, the proffer of grace, and the acceptance of grace proffered: The firſt is by the Word, the Spirit, and Baptiſme; the other is by the Word, Spirit, Faith, and the Lords ſupper. I have here added faith, becauſe the Scripture doth ſo, making faith an inſtrument by which we receive Chriſt: but Chriſt muſt be prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to us by his Spirit and Word, before we can receive him, which is expreſſed in the word calling, as diſtinct from juſtification, and goeth before juſtification, in which we have the firſt act of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. Whom he predeſtinateth, them he alſo called, whom he called, them he alſo juſtified; we are not called by faith, but we are juſtified by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28. and 5.1. Baptiſme is the ſeal and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods work in us, which had need to be moſt cleerly manifeſted, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed unto us, as having moſt of God, and leaſt of us, that we might ſubmit to it, wherunto we are moſt averſe; therefore what hath moſt of us in it, that pleaſeth us beſt: as works better then faith, and faith, as we look on it in our ſelves, as a qualification is more delightfull to us then as it is in its own nature, working hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, teaching us to deny our ſelves, and reſt on God: men do uſe to magnifie faith, but too many under a falſe apprehenſion, even of ſecrecie and liberty before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> faith is not a boaſting quality, nor to be pleaded before men, but God; and this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cap.</hi> 2. doth handle at large, ſhewing, that men are very inclinable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of faith before men, and rely on works before God; and herein the deceitfulneſſe of our hearts is very great, when we conceive we deal with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>-power, then we finde the things of faith apprehended moſt weakly of any thing, we can pleaſe our ſelves better in the opinion of our works then of faith, but when we come to deal with man, we are ſure we treat of colours before blind
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:113690:38"/>men: there we can boldly talk, we may ſpeak as freely as travellers, we cannot be diſproved, whereby it cometh to paſſe, often times, that heart that is leaſt upright, is moſt bold; faith is indeed, in time of need, very heroick in her exploits, in that ſhe acteth by the power of God, but aſcribeth little of her beſt actions to her ſelf; ſhe is alwayes converſant with God, and therefore cannot but be conſcious of much weakneſſe and infirmity; faith is ſo always loaden with difficulties, that ſhe hath very little to ſay of her ſelf; there muſt be great preparation on Gods part, before there can be any ſenſe or feeling in man of the things of faith; there muſt be the mighty operation of the Word and Spirit, and God is pleaſed to adde bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm too, for faith to work upon: theſe things are of mighty operation, and ſo they had need, conſidering the ſloth of heart that is in us to believe: it is well, if after the Word and ſacrament of baptiſme, faith do come. God layeth it as a ground and foundation for faith to work upon, and accordingly all the arguments of Scripture are to raiſe us to walk worthy of amendment of life, and to riſe with Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. as if it ſhould be ſaid, God hath offered you grace in baptiſme, therefore accept of it; ye are born anew in baptiſme, let it appear in your converſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 4. That which maketh the admiſſion into the Church meerly arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that is a falſe doctrine; but the doctrine of Anabaptiſts maketh admiſſion into the Church meerly arbitrary, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the major is plain; for, that nothing is more directly contrary to the ſervice of God then will-worſhip, but denying any that are tendred according to the mind of Chriſt in the Word, and requiring ſuch diſpoſition in the party to be baptized, as the Miniſter pleaſeth, without any rule from Gods Word, is to make the publike ſervice of God, or at leaſt a great part of it, wholly arbytrary; and this doth appear to flow from their doctrine: not yet any man durſt affirm what was the meaſure of faith to be required how much he muſt believe that muſt be baptized, by means whereof the whole matter depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on the will of the Baptizer, a thing moſt contrary to the nature of Religion; it cannot be imagined that the Holy Ghoſt would have been ſo ſilent in giving rules for the Miniſters to walk by in the triall of the faith of the perſon to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, if any ſuch charge had lain upon his office. He muſt baptize believers only, ſaith Mr. Tombes, and the Anabaptiſts, but no Scripture directeth what, or how much he muſt believe; muſt it be as much as the Miniſter ſhall think fit, then ſome Miniſters will baptize with very ſmall triall, others will be very hardly ſatisfied: ſome will baptize as ſoon as the childe can be taught to ſay he believeth in Chriſt, others not till ten or twelve, others twenty yeers of age; wherein no man can either ſatisfie his own conſcience, or any reaſonable man; for that he walketh without rules, neither doth this difficulty from this doctrine come from accidental miſconſtructions or phanſies, but inevitable neceſſity from the doctrine it ſelf, that the Miniſter muſt baptize none but believers; yet cannot tell how much, or what he muſt believe before he be fit for baptiſme, unleſſe he walk by rules of mans making, without any intimation from Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:113690:38"/>
            <p n="5">5. That doctrine that giveth man that power which is divine, that doctrine is blaſphemous and falſe; but the doctrine of the Anabaptiſts giveth man that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer which is divine, therefore the doctrine of Anabaptiſts is blaſphemous and falſe.</p>
            <p>That doctrine that giveth man power to judge of faith in another, that doctrine giveth man that power that is divine; but the Anabaptiſt giveth men power to judge of faith in another; therefore the Anabaptiſt, that power that is divine.</p>
            <p>Faith is in the heart: with the heart man beleeveth to righteouſneſſe, and with the mouth he confeſſeth to ſalvation, Rom. 10.10. He therefore that judgeth of faith, muſt judge the heart which is proper to God. I the Lord try the heart, Jer. 17.10. Neither will it ſerve his turne to ſay, that he judgeth by rules of charity if this charge lay upon his office; to judge charitably it is one thing, another to judge <hi>ex officio;</hi> for the judgement of charity can never pronounce the perſon ſo judged to be ſuch as he is judged by charity to be: judgements of charity are not alwaies true, if it be poſſible we have warrant enough to judge it ſo by charity: if children may poſſibly be ſuch as the Kingdome of heaven doe belong too, wee may in charity judge them ſuch: but if we are tyed by our office to baptize none but beleevers, it will not ſerve turne to ſay we judge them ſuch by charity, to prove that we muſt baptize none but ſuch as are beleevers, ſeeing we may by charity judge many beleevers which yet are not beleevers: againe judgement of faith is denied to belong to the Apoſtles themſelves, not that we have dominion of your faith, 2 Cor. 1.24. If God had appointed Miniſters to have judged of mens faith before they had baptized them, he would have given them ſome rules by which they ſhould have been able to walke, which he hath not done; he hath annexed baptiſme to the Miniſters calling to let men know that the grace of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme commeth immediatly from Chriſt; therefore he ſent the ſeale of it by that calling that came immediately from him, but hath promiſed thoſe officers of his no ſpeciall qualifications whereby they ſhall have abilities to diſcern the faith of men more then other men have; the judgement of charity, is not a Miniſteriall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification that belongeth to every man, and is no Miniſteriall qualification.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That doctrine that denieth the interpretation of the promiſe made to Abraham which S. Paul maketh that is a falſe doctrine; but the doctrine of Anabaptiſts deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the interpretation of the promiſe made to Abraham wch St. Paul maketh: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the doctrine of the Anabaptiſts is falſe. Thoſe that deny the bleſſing of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and in him of all the Nations of the earth to be the Goſpel preached to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham in reference to the Gentiles after their call, deny the interpretation that S. Paul maketh of the promiſe made to Abraham: but the Anabaptiſts deny the bleſſing of Abraham, and in him of all the Nations of the earth, to be the Goſpell preached to Abraham in reference to the Gentiles after their call; therefore the Anabaptiſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the interpretation made to Abraham which S. Paul maketh; the words of S. Paul
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:113690:39"/>are plain, Gal. 3.8. the Scripture foreſeeing that God would juſtifie the heathen through faith, preached before the Goſpel unto Abraham, ſaying, In thee ſhall all Nations be bleſſed; where ye ſee plainly S. Paul affirmeth the promiſe to Abraham to be the Goſpel, and the Nations to be converted Gentiles, and that in the promiſe made to Abraham, there was a Propheſie of the converſion of the Gentiles; and the Gentiles under the Goſpell had Abrahams bleſſing, that is a bleſſing to them and their ſeed, as Abraham had to him and his ſeed: ſo that it is apparent that thoſe which deny the bleſſing to the ſeed of the Gentiles, the bleſſing of the promiſe, deny Abrahams bleſſing to the Gentiles; which is directly to deny the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of St. Paul concerning Abrahams bleſſing, and to deny that the bleſſing to Abraham was the Goſpell, or that the promiſe was a Propheſie of the converſion of the Gentiles under the Goſpell; all which things are plainly affirmed by St. Paul.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That doctrine that denieth the benefit or grace of circumciſion to be offered in baptiſme, that doctrine is falſe: but the doctrine of Anabaptiſts is a doctrine that denieth the benefit and grace of circumciſion to be offered in baptiſme; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the doctrine of the Anabaptiſts is falſe. That doctrine which denieth what St. Paul affirmeth, is a falſe doctrine: but that doctrine that denieth the benefit or grace of circumciſion to be offered in baptiſme, that doctrine denieth what St. Paul affirmeth; therefore that doctrine denieth the benefit and grace of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be offered in baptiſme, is a falſe doctrine.</p>
            <p>The place wherein St. Paul doth affirme that we have the benefit of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by baptiſme, is Colloſſ. 2.11, 12. Let the argument be weighed, I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to it in my anſwer to Mr. Tombes. In the which verſe St. Paul affirmeth they were circumciſed, that was not literally true; therefore he affirmeth in a figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or metonymicall ſenſe, <hi>ſigni pro ſignato,</hi> the thing ſignified by circumciſion: and he further ſheweth, how the benefit they were partakers of had reſemblance with circumciſion; circumciſion did cut off the body by a ſynecdoche, part for the whole, but they put off the whole body, but it was the body of ſin. Now this is done by the circumciſion of Chriſt; it was this circumciſion of Chriſt that made the circumciſion of our fathers of any vertue: this had been as true of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, that they were circumciſed in putting off the body of the ſinnes of the fleſh by the circumciſion of Chriſt; whereof their legall circumciſion was but a type, and Chriſts circumciſion did put an end to that circumciſion; yet the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians were circumciſed in Chriſt: how could that be? the text plainly ſaith, they put off the body of the ſinnes of the fleſh, and that was their circumciſion in the circumciſion of Chriſt; it was the benefit of circumciſion to the Jewes, which they had though they wanted the ceremony? Now all this benefit commeth unto you by being in Chriſt, get but into Chriſt and all is done; to put off the body is to dye; Chriſt dyed, if ye be in him, all that he did you did; he was circumciſed, ye
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:113690:39"/>are circumciſed; he died, ye die; if in him; thus were your fathers in Chriſt by circumciſion: ſo are ye in Chriſt by baptiſme, buried with him in baptiſme: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be plainer then the grace and benefit of circumciſion was offered to the Coloſſians in baptiſme.</p>
            <p>That doctrine that refuſeth to hear and obey the rationall and manly phraſe of the doctrine of the Goſpell, and reduce all to the ſenſitive and childiſh delivery of the Law, that is an unfaithfull and diſobedient doctrine; but the doctrine of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts refuſeth to heare and obey the rationall and manly phraſe of the doctrine of the Goſpell, and reduce all to the ſenſitive and childiſh delivery of the Law, therefore the doctrine of the Anabaptiſts is an unfaithfull and diſobedient do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; God was pleaſed to deliver the ſervice, which conſiſted in ceremonies and outward performances in ſuch manner, that every externall was directed to them the length, heighth of their Temple, and of every thing that was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, to ſhew that God would be the author of all things in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: The colour, length of the curtains, of their altars, and every carved thing, were directed immediatly by God; the place where the Temple ſhould ſtand: If we ſhould rigorouſly look for particular rules in this kinde, as thoſe Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts do in point of baptiſme look for the like direction for adminiſtration of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, as of circumciſion; and for want thereof, to neglect what the Holy Ghoſt hath ſaid concerning the nature of baptiſme, and giving direction to have it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to all nations, thereby leaving the precept or duty of baptiſme without any lawfull uſe, for want of ſuch ſenſitive and particular direction as they had under the Law, we might be condemned for will-worſhip, for building Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches without a pattern and direction from God, how high, or how long they ſhould be, together with many things of the like nature; refuſe to pray pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely or meet to ſerve God becauſe he had appointed no place: the truth is, what they ſay againſt baptizing of Infants doth conclude againſt any baptizing at all: For, if the particular aſſignation of the perſons to be baptized muſt be dinſtiguiſhed by any qualification, for want of any ſuch direction, we ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to leave all unbaptized: Baptize all nations, ſaith Chriſt, and <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. three thouſand ſouls were added: <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12. men and women; theſe may compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all, male and female, without neceſſary inference, that they were grown men and women.</p>
            <p>Now, if we leave this ſenſitive and childiſh way, and walk by the reaſonable ſenſe of Scripture, how cleerly doth the Scripture give ſatisfaction in this point, I pray you obſerve? Firſt, Chriſt doth command to baptize all nations: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he telleth, that the promiſe belonging to any, doth entitle him to baptiſme, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. Thirdly, that the promiſe is the ſame to Abraham, and the Goſpel preached to the Gentiles, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. that the promiſe was to Abraham and his ſeed; that baptiſme doth circumciſe us by ingrafting us into Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:113690:40"/>By what rational excuſes can we excuſe our ſelves for diſobediences to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt, commanding us to baptize all nations, if we refuſe any, that by a nationall covenant are brought unto us?</p>
            <p n="8">8. That doctrine, which under pretence of walking by Scripture, ſupport all their doctrine by falacies, and falſe arguments, that doctrine is erroneous and falſe; but the doctrine of Anabaptiſts is ſuch, I do challenge all the Anabaptiſts, and in particular Mr. Tombes, to produce any argument againſt Infants baptiſme from Scripture, or ſound reaſon, that ſhall reaſonably conclude from the words without any addition or ſubſtraction, or may agree with the ſenſe and argument of the words produced, then I ſhall account Mr. Tombes his ſceptiques more tolerable; in the mean time, I wiſh he might receive ſatisfaction, and ſpend his time in confirmation of his weaker brethern.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
